<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Learning on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/tags/learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Learning on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 15:01:35 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/tags/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>So Who Wants to Volunteer?</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/so-who-wants-to-volunteer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 15:01:35 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/so-who-wants-to-volunteer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In yesterday&amp;rsquo;s Yoga class, our instructor wanted to demonstrate a certain asana (pose). She could have easily done it herself, but she wanted a volunteer, perhaps so that she could point out common mistakes people make in this asana. So she asked &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;who wants to volunteer?&amp;rdquo;. As is common in such a situation, most people look around trying to deflect attention. I often do that too, but this time I just raised my hand, albeit a little reluctantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I did an OK job being a model, but there was a useful lesson there &amp;ndash; even though being the center of attention was uncomfortable, I got more feedback on my posture than I normally would. The attention went away as the others got busy with trying the asana on their own, but the feedback stayed &amp;ndash; a net win for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s useful to apply this little idea on other situations in life where we often forgo learning for comfort. The position of comfort is hard to leave, so it&amp;rsquo;s important to consciously make the choice to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rediscovering Podcasts</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/rediscovering-podcasts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 15:50:52 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/rediscovering-podcasts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This summer, I was interviewing at several companies. Among other things, it involved a lot of travel, and there was little I could do while traveling. If I was driving, I’d mostly listen to my usual Spotify playlists, although they got boring pretty soon. Taking the train allowed me to read in addition, but I’d usually get distracted or fall asleep since the interviews were exhausting. Soon enough, all this travel time started feeling wasteful, but I wanted to reclaim it, so I constantly tried to find ways to engage in something productive, or learn something new. Then one day I was reading an article in which CEOs of some companies described how they made their commutes productive. One of the ideas was to listen to audiobooks. I didn’t have any books in mind, but I immediately remembered how I’d once wanted to try podcasts, and never did. I downloaded an &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.bambuna.podcastaddict&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;Android app&lt;/a&gt; and loaded some interesting podcasts. I quickly realized that this was what I was looking for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know why I only recently discovered how nice it is to listen to podcasts while driving. It&amp;#39;s educative + makes me feel less lonely.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nishant Totla (@nishanttotla) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nishanttotla/status/634283994704535552&#34;&gt;August 20, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with listening to some podcasts about people sharing their experiences, and soon moved on to human behavior and social skills. I also tried some economics, culture, and science. I found podcasts refreshing for several reasons. First of all, I was listening to very stimulating and engaging content, which excited me and kept me alert. This was especially welcome during long lonely drives, often in rush hour traffic. Second, podcasts often featured people having a conversation, where I would laugh and grimace and feel actively involved. Most importantly though, I learned a great deal about diverse topics, and this is something I love to do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m just going to emphasize that podcasts are brilliant and unrivaled when you want to productively use time when only your auditory senses are free. This is their biggest advantage compared to all other information media, especially seeing how everyone is constantly “engaged” these days. Podcasts are a regular fixture for drives now, and I’m gradually trying to add them to other tasks like cooking, cleaning, and in general anything that doesn’t require immense concentration. Of course, there are still times when I just want silence, or music, but in general, I’m a big fan of trying to find opportunities to learn small bits that could eventually add up to major life changes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>