<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 15:25:25 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>February 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2017-02/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 15:25:25 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2017-02/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:ba0e22dee794a25c4a033332b484e270&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.currentaffairs.org/2016/10/some-troublesome-questions-for-liberals-on-borders&#34;&gt;Some Troublesome Questions for Liberals on Borders&lt;/a&gt; [Current Affairs] &amp;ndash; As the last few months continue to heavily challenge our belief systems and ideals, I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying a lot harder to consolidate my own principles, and what liberalism means for me. Immigration is being talked about a lot these days, and this article raises pertinent questions about the way we argue for it. In summary, we need to do a much better job at constructing more solid (including moral) arguments for immigration, rather than just relying on the economic ones.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/2017/02/russians-engineer-brilliant-slot-machine-cheat-casinos-no-fix/&#34;&gt;Russians Engineer a Brilliant Slot Machine Cheat &amp;ndash; And Casinos Have No Fix&lt;/a&gt; [Wired] &amp;ndash; A Russian company found a way to reverse-engineer the pseudo-random number generator algorithms of some casinos, and managed to win much more than slot machines usually give. This is the story of how they operate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.t5eiitm.org/2017/02/chronicle-imprisonment-foretold/&#34;&gt;A Chronicle Of An Imprisonment Foretold&lt;/a&gt; [The Fifth Estate][TW: sexual harassment] &amp;ndash; A story of sexual harassment on the IIT Madras campus. It highlights the victim&amp;rsquo;s personal experience and the ineffectiveness of systems designed to deal with cases like these. Looking back to my time at IIT Bombay, none of this comes across as a great surprise, and I can only begin to imagine the plight of students who silently suffer harassment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.hansardsociety.org.uk/parliaments-around-the-world-what-can-architecture-can-teach-us-about-democracy/&#34;&gt;Parliaments around the world: what can architecture teach us about democracy?&lt;/a&gt; [Hansard Society] &amp;ndash; This very intriguing article takes a look at how Parliaments are structured in countries around the world. The idea is to try and understand how political culture is shaped by architecture and also expressed through it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://nymag.com/selectall/2017/02/the-magical-rationalism-of-elon-musk-and-the-prophets-of-ai.html&#34;&gt;The Magical Rationalism of Elon Musk and the Prophets of AI&lt;/a&gt; [NYMag] &amp;ndash; Are those who worry about how AI will make humans irrelevant just doomsday prophets, using the power of &amp;ldquo;magical rationalism&amp;rdquo; to make the risks appear legitimate?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://security.googleblog.com/2017/02/announcing-first-sha1-collision.html&#34;&gt;Announcing the first SHA1 collision&lt;/a&gt; [Google Security Blog] &amp;ndash; The Google Security team announced the first SHA-1 collision. The computation they required for it is massive, but still accessible by today&amp;rsquo;s standards, which means it&amp;rsquo;s only a matter of time all systems using SHA-1 need to move away from it. Also check &lt;a href=&#34;http://shattered.io/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more information. This announcement was possibly overshadowed by &amp;ldquo;Cloudbleed&amp;rdquo;, the Cloudflare bug that was revealed on the same day. I haven&amp;rsquo;t yet read the analysis, so that&amp;rsquo;ll probably make it into the next month&amp;rsquo;s log.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;movies-and-tv-shows:ba0e22dee794a25c4a033332b484e270&#34;&gt;Movies and TV Shows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4846340/&#34;&gt;Hidden Figures&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; The little-told and uplifting story of the role of black women at NASA during the 50s and 60s. As the US competed with the Soviet Union in the space race, several black women played key roles in enabling the first manned space flight and the moon mission, destroying barriers and stereotypes along the way. This is interesting particularly in contrast with the Civil Rights movement, which was at its peak during the same period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1740299/&#34;&gt;The Man in the High Castle&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I binged through Season 2 of this gripping alternative history series, which imagines what the world might have looked like had the Allies lost WWII. Highly recommended for history buffs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music:ba0e22dee794a25c4a033332b484e270&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to more of Zeb Bangash lately, and find this song quite beautiful. This song also reminds me of Spring, and makes me feel quite optimistic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/277961505&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:ba0e22dee794a25c4a033332b484e270&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://voyager.jpl.nasa.gov/where/&#34;&gt;Where are the Voyagers?&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A NASA JPL link that tracks the live location of the two Voyager spacecrafts. Both are interstellar spacecraft, and have been a source of fascination for me since childhood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E41rudbp-n0&#34;&gt;Dama Dam Mast Qalandar By Runa Laila, Abida Parveen, Asha Bhosle &amp;amp; Atif Aslam&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Sharing this song in memory of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://scroll.in/article/829667/pakistan-suicide-bombing-why-isis-feels-so-threatened-by-sindhs-lal-shahbaz-qalandar-shrine&#34;&gt;horrible terror attack on the Qalandar shrine&lt;/a&gt; in Sindh, which the song&amp;rsquo;s title alludes to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shmoop.com&#34;&gt;Shmoop&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A website that contains several study guides. Particularly interesting for me are humanities topics that I do not have a great background in, such as history, literary criticism, etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.elleuk.com/life-and-culture/culture/articles/a33897/rape-sexual-assault-survivor-perpetrator-ted-talk/&#34;&gt;This Rape Survivor And The Man Who Raped Her Have Teamed Up To Tell Their Story&lt;/a&gt; [TW: rape] &amp;ndash; Not sure how I feel about this one, but it is an unusual case of a rape victim and her rapist coming together (voluntarily) to talk about it. While their message seems agreeable (I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually seen the video itself), there are legitimate issues around providing a platform and voice to a rapist on this subject, points which this article aptly raises.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deciding to Stop</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/deciding-to-stop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:44:06 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/deciding-to-stop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a slow reader with a short attention span, but I&amp;rsquo;d like to read a lot more books
than I currently manage. So I&amp;rsquo;m like the armchair analyst who dreams of changing the
world &amp;ndash; tons of ambition, but lack of skills (and possibly desire?). A recurrent
problem for me has been that I start some books, partly or nearly finish them, have
no interest in continuing, but can&amp;rsquo;t start other books until I finish the earlier ones.
Obviously there&amp;rsquo;s merit to sticking it out, but more often than not, time could be better
spent reading books out of which I could derive most value, rather than struggle with ones
that are neither adding much value nor getting done (I&amp;rsquo;m looking at you
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/19438058-zen-and-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance&#34;&gt;Robert Pirsig&lt;/a&gt;). What I&amp;rsquo;m suggesting isn&amp;rsquo;t
groundbreaking, but it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember &amp;ndash; the guilt and pressure of finishing
a book is a strong deterrent to moving on and reading more books that you can actually
finish. The same applies to TV shows, jobs, relationships (but we won&amp;rsquo;t go there).
It&amp;rsquo;s tempting to simply view all of this as the sunk cost fallacy, but stating out
the special case is always useful. That&amp;rsquo;s why we have the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/books/shortcuts/2014/jul/07/hawking-index-give-up-on-books-capital-fifty-shades&#34;&gt;Hawking Index&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>January 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2017-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 22:27:53 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2017-01/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There are some old posts here, just because I&amp;rsquo;m still catching up with the backlog
from the last 4-5 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:522ff2422ef90d5eff638eb49e6ceed5&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2017/01/my-president-was-black/508793&#34;&gt;My President was Black&lt;/a&gt; [The Atlantic] &amp;ndash; A really long (in six parts) and powerful article by Ta-Nehisi Coates on the rise and political career of Barack Obama. It talks about Obama&amp;rsquo;s childhood in Hawaii, the influences that shaped his outlook and policies, and the recent election &amp;ndash; all viewed from the lens of race and history as well. If there&amp;rsquo;s one long article you read this month, let this be it!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://niskanencenter.org/blog/defense-liberty-cant-without-identity-politics&#34;&gt;The Defense of Liberty can&amp;rsquo;t do without Identity Politics&lt;/a&gt; [Niskanen Center] &amp;ndash; Identity politics has been recently maligned as one of the major causes of general dissatisfaction with the government. This is a solid essay that explains in good terms why Trump&amp;rsquo;s election is no reason to get rid of identity politics. In fact, we need more of it to make sure the rights of oppressed groups are protected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@Bahujan_Power/pioneering-a-survey-of-caste-in-the-diasporas-6e5a27cd82ef#.xx82xrhfh&#34;&gt;Spearheading a Survey of Caste in South Asian Diasporas&lt;/a&gt; [Medium] &amp;ndash; There&amp;rsquo;s some background in this article, with personal stories, and link to a survey set up by the Dalit American Foundation and co-sponsored by Ambedkar International Mission, Ambedkar Association of North America, and the Dalit American Women’s Federation. It&amp;rsquo;s a fascinating look into how the caste system works among the Indian diaspora.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://thingofthings.wordpress.com/2016/04/05/amateur-sociology-considered-harmful/&#34;&gt;Amateur Sociology Considered Harmful&lt;/a&gt; [Things of Things] &amp;ndash; A highly recommended post on the pitfalls of amateur sociology &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s fun but we have to be much more careful about assuming it actually describes the world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2016/09/for-kidney-health-roller-coaster-therapy/501278/&#34;&gt;A Health Benefit of Roller Coasters&lt;/a&gt; [The Atlantic] &amp;ndash; This is truly wacky research. In a unique, home-spun experiment, researchers found that centripetal force could help people pass kidney stones—before they become a serious health care cost.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/01/11/fashion/peter-thiel-donald-trump-silicon-valley-technology-gawker.html&#34;&gt;Peter Thiel, Trump’s Tech Pal, Explains Himself&lt;/a&gt; [The New York Times] &amp;ndash; An interview with Peter Thiel about his behavior during the last presidential election. His responses make it evidently clear that he hasn&amp;rsquo;t fully considered the damaging positions of the candidate he supported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2016/04/america-tyranny-donald-trump.html&#34;&gt;Democracies end when they are too democratic&lt;/a&gt; [NYMag] &amp;ndash; An article from May that I finally managed to read. While I don&amp;rsquo;t agree with all points, it now comes across as extremely prescient about the events that followed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@yonatanzunger/trial-balloon-for-a-coup-e024990891d5#.e9vzbei2p&#34;&gt;Trial Balloon for a Coup?&lt;/a&gt; [Medium] &amp;ndash; This is a speculative article that argues that the current administration&amp;rsquo;s imposition of the Muslim ban, then backing off on some points, followed by the confusion that followed was a way of testing the limits of the system. Quoting, &amp;ldquo;Yesterday was the trial balloon for a coup d’état against the United States. It gave them useful information&amp;rdquo;. There&amp;rsquo;s also &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@jakefuentes/the-immigration-ban-is-a-headfake-and-were-falling-for-it-b8910e78f0c5#.wcck2msz1&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; that constructs a similar hypothesis &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;We’ve just tested the country’s willingness to capitulate to a fascist regime&amp;rdquo;. On the second article, I disagree with the tone that protests have limited efficacy, but agree that much bigger and stronger organization is key.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;movies-and-tv-shows:522ff2422ef90d5eff638eb49e6ceed5&#34;&gt;Movies and TV Shows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched several good movies this month, though there are still more I have to catch up on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4341582/&#34;&gt;Queen of Katwe&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A feel-good movie about a little girl in Uganda who&amp;rsquo;s a Chess prodigy, and goes on to rapidly achieve great success. The best part is that this is based on the true story of Phiona Mutesi, who grew up in a slum in Katwe, learned to play Chess there, and eventually became an international champion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4900716/&#34;&gt;Kapoor &amp;amp; Sons&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;d watched this movie before, but watched it again on the flight back to San Francisco. I think it needs a mention, because even after the second watch, it was an extremely well-made and delicately sensitive Bollywood movie. It surely is one of my favorite Hindi movies from the new generation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt5946128/&#34;&gt;Dear Zindagi&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Another Hindi movie that deserves a mention. Bollywood tends to poorly treat many complex issues, and mental health remains one of them, so it&amp;rsquo;s refreshing to see a generally mature movie centered around mental health issues and therapy (which is still a big taboo in India).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3783958/&#34;&gt;La La Land&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Nominated for 14 academy awards, and every bit worth that. Each frame feels like art, and Emma Stone in particular is a very good actress. That said, there&amp;rsquo;s something ironic about a movie about saving Jazz with all-white cast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adronitis</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/adronitis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 15:09:14 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/adronitis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a word that struck me immediately. I found it on one of those &lt;a href=&#34;http://thoughtcatalog.com/brianna-wiest/2016/02/40-words-for-emotions-youve-felt-but-couldnt-explain/3/&#34;&gt;listicles&lt;/a&gt;
that pull up obscure words that mean very specific things, and then advertize to
young adults trying to make sense of their emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adronitis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;n. frustration with how long it takes to get to know someone—spending the first few weeks chatting in their psychological entryway, with each subsequent conversation like entering a different anteroom, each a little closer to the center of the house—wishing instead that you could start there and work your way out, exchanging your deepest secrets first, before easing into casualness, until you’ve built up enough mystery over the years to ask them where they’re from, and what they do for a living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d be willing to bet this is not even a real word &amp;ndash; searching didn&amp;rsquo;t yield
conclusive results. But the meaning, and imagery it depicts, is spot on, and something
I&amp;rsquo;ve strongly felt about making friends lately.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Being a Tourist in India</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently got back to California after spending four full weeks in India. My
previous trip was two years ago, at the end
of 2014. Until moving to the US in 2012, I&amp;rsquo;d only ever lived in India.
Immediately after moving, life in California seemed very attractive, especially by
virtue of the things India could not offer (primarily better facilities,
a more peaceful lifestyle, and opportunities for individual growth). Whenever I visited
India after that, I&amp;rsquo;d often complain about the lack of infrastructure, pollution,
poor traffic, general disorder, and a host of other problems that might
affect any developing country. Typical NRI behavior, I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trip was so different though! Although it was my first proper
long vacation in over four years, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t explain everything. Over the last
two years, my life in the US hasn&amp;rsquo;t exactly been a smooth ride, and I&amp;rsquo;ve felt
increasing loneliness, conflated with other personal struggles, including those
with healthcare and bureaucracy. All of that has surely dulled the sheen that
California once held for me. It&amp;rsquo;s not a radical idea that each place has its
problems, but to truly feel and internalize it, and move past the
first world fetishism that many in India grow up with is quite
empowering. I&amp;rsquo;ve also been extremely fortunate in the last 2-3 years to
have traveled to multiple places and made friends with people
from diverse backgrounds.
As a result, I find that I&amp;rsquo;m quite willing to look past trivial (and
sometimes even big) inconveniences and focus on the positives whenever I travel
to a new place. Once again, none of this is very unique, and seasoned travelers
are often quite patient people (I&amp;rsquo;m not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I felt compelled to write about this is that adopting a different attitude
made my recent India experience extremely positive. On an absolute level, the India
I went to did not feel remarkably different. Some infrastructure had improved for
sure, but a lot still felt the same. Traffic was noticeably worse, air quality poor,
and the streets dirty. These aren&amp;rsquo;t new problems, as any Indian will tell you, and
they&amp;rsquo;ve annoyed me a lot in the past. This time though, I had decided to travel like
I&amp;rsquo;d travel to any other country &amp;ndash; as a tourist. This might feel like a small thing,
but it was an epiphany. I found it easier to ignore a lot of the negative
aspects, and focus on the good things &amp;ndash; and India does have a lot of good things
to offer. In the past, I&amp;rsquo;d get tired of being in India after about three
weeks and want to return, but this time I did not quite feel like coming back. Of
course, going to India is different from visiting any other country, since I&amp;rsquo;ve
grown up there, and it remains one of the likely countries I could move to in the
future. Still, this new attitude was helpful with realizing what really mattered
and what was tolerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to add the disclaimer that all of this says nothing about
actually living in India&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Additionally, this is not a good attitude to adopt
if one is living in a place, since it can very easily breed apathy. Still, as I
continue to evaluate whether or not I want to move to India in the near future,
this helped me think more clearly and filter out the unimportant considerations.
Without that, I&amp;rsquo;m predisposed to hyperbolizing annoyances and never creating a
balanced picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;I often complain that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what it&amp;rsquo;s like to live as an independent adult in India, since I left right after college.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was Asked to Give a Motivational Speech</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/i-was-asked-motivational-speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 15:29:03 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/i-was-asked-motivational-speech/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;On December 18, 2016, my parents celebrated the 25th anniversary of Totla Hospital.
It has been a long and impressive journey for them, starting out
from literally nothing when they arrived in Aurangabad, to having built a very
successful and highly respected hospital in the city. To celebrate this anniversary,
they had organized a grand function, inviting a lot of former patients, friends, family,
and others out of the gigantic community they&amp;rsquo;ve built during this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks prior, I was asked to speak at the event. Several people in the city know
me due to some good exam results from 2008 that got a lot of publicity,
though I have always found it hard to deal with the attention.
As a result, I&amp;rsquo;ve often overcompensated and vehemently opposed anything that would
draw similar attention to me. Besides, I always maintained that good exam results
are down to a lot of luck, and mine were too long in the past anyway. So while
my first reaction was to protest the fact that I even had to speak at the event,
I later decided that this was a rare opportunity to engage with the people of
Aurangabad (the event was expected to have 1500 attendees!) and put forward my point
of view. It took me some days to come up with the key points, and roughly a day to write
them down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expectation was that I&amp;rsquo;d say something motivational, given all my &amp;ldquo;success&amp;rdquo;.
Instead, I decided to talk about things I personally feel strongly about, including
questioning what success means. Here&amp;rsquo;s my original draft of the speech. The actual
transcript differs slightly because I improvised on stage, but it sticks to the outline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speech-outline:c926fc76b4b01d7c5aa3351fb0bb8c80&#34;&gt;Speech Outline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good evening everyone, my name is Nishant Totla, and I&amp;rsquo;m the son of Dr Rajgopal Totla
and Santosh Totla. Today I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about how I think about success, looking
at the past. I wanted to say something motivational, but I think it is far
more important to talk about what success means and the factors
behind it, before trying to motivate others towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll only talk for 10 minutes, but my talk is meant for young
students aspiring to be successful, and their parents who want to support them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does success look like? We&amp;rsquo;ve all seen what it looks like in the newspapers.
You know, people see all these flashy results, or news about how some kid
out of college is getting a huge salary, and wonder if they&amp;rsquo;re being left behind.
Well let me tell you this &amp;ndash; news like this is meant to deceive, not inform.
It hides all the other factors that are involved in becoming a successful person.
I have done well enough in the last few years that many people consider me
successful. But from my point of view, looking back, here is what I think
contributes to success. There are, broadly speaking, four things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privilege&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(and to some extent, talent)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[I define what each of them mean]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that the only thing in your hands, is hard work. Successful people
often downplay the role of other things in their success, and they are often
as important as hard work. Don&amp;rsquo;t let any successful person tell you they were not lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll give you an example. When my parents arrived in Aurangabad a long time
ago to start Totla Hospital, they came with no money and support,
just a strong desire to start practicing and serve people. They did not have
the privilege of a comfortable familiar place, or financial backing. But
they worked really hard, and were fortunate to be supported by some amazing people
in this journey, which makes them as successful as they are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own case, I had everything one can ask for &amp;ndash; I worked very hard, I
was lucky in many places (like not falling sick at the wrong times), and
I was very privileged because my parents supported me at every step, despite
all the inconvenience it caused them. I could not have achieved anything without
support from them, the hospital staff, family, and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went to college, I met some people who had nothing like what I had.
There were people from really poor families, or very unfortunate circumstances,
who worked really hard to get there, and did well in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born in Aurangabad, and grew up here for a good part of my life.
I&amp;rsquo;ve heard a lot of times that our region lacks infrastructure and awareness
for our youth to be successful. I agree that we still have a lot of
catching up to do, and it will happen with time. But with the above points,
my message to all of you who hold aspirations to be successful is this &amp;ndash;
remember that situations will never be perfect. You will probably not get
all these things, and the only thing you can do is to be sincere in your efforts
and work hard. The rest is not always in your control. To the parents, my
message is that if your kids fail despite hard work, recognize that many other factors are involved, and don&amp;rsquo;t blame them right away. Their talents
might be elsewhere, or they might have just been unlucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now I will move on to the second part &amp;ndash; what is success?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, I used to believe that doing well in school was success.
Then I believed doing well in competitive examinations, and getting into a good
college was success. Then I thought getting a good job was success. But after all
those things, and some more experience, I want to say that these things are
not as important as we think. Yes they help, and we must work hard towards them,
but they don&amp;rsquo;t define us. Lot of people in good colleges end up
unsuccessful, and many remarkable people in the world did not
go to a very good college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I look at what my parents have achieved, they have no doubt built and
done a lot of great things over the last 25 years. But the most important thing that
I believe makes them successful is their kindness and compassion for their patients.
When so many patients speak highly of them, it is not because they have great
education and degrees. It is because they understand people&amp;rsquo;s pain, empathize with
them, and they are kind. In the long term, it is these qualities that will give you
a lot more success and happiness, than just things on paper. Right now, when I
think about what I want to do in the future, it is always related to how I can
help people &amp;ndash; especially those are are poor, or lack privilege. Look at so many
rich people (such as Bill Gates), who end up living very modest lives and
help others through philanthropy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a society, we need to start telling people that it is not only these
fancy achievements that make a person successful and useful to society. The will
to help people around us, and kindness are extremely underrated qualities that
should be cultivated from a young age. Let us stop narrowly defining what success
means, and instead focus on what we can do to become happy and satisfied with
our lives. I cannot tell you how to achieve that, because you must find it
for yourself. What I can tell you though, is to work hard, and not
get caught up in narrow definitions of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ummmm:c926fc76b4b01d7c5aa3351fb0bb8c80&#34;&gt;Ummmm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, probably sounds like one of those cheesy speeches that doesn&amp;rsquo;t really say anything
actionable (because it is!), but it was my first attempt at putting these ideas out there.
More selfishly, I have started relishing the opportunity to speak publicly, thanks partly
to my job that has given me several chances to present my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/umang.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;I had the outline on my phone!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have become much more
comfortable and confident on stage, and have begun treating each occasion like an
exciting opportunity to be enjoyed, rather than a scary challenge to overcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>December 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2016-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 13:12:53 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2016-12/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There are some old posts here, just because I&amp;rsquo;m still catching up with the backlog
from the last 4-5 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:4511ef69dc4e83813633e87570ad385e&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://carnegieendowment.org/2013/09/10/five-trends-shaping-india-s-voting-landscape-pub-52870&#34;&gt;Five Trends Shaping India’s Voting Landscape&lt;/a&gt; [Carnegie Endowment] &amp;ndash; Interesting analysis of voting trends and factors affecting elections in India. It touches upon some numbers illustrating patterns around voter turnout, effect of state elections, translation of votes to seats, etc. This was written before the 2014 election though, so some of the analysis might have to be changed as a result. There are more interesting articles &lt;a href=&#34;http://carnegieendowment.org/specialprojects/IndiaDecides2014/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@BigMeanInternet/lego-marx-de65004b8678#.ex51oew2g&#34;&gt;Lego Marx&lt;/a&gt; [Medium] &amp;ndash; This is a great read because it refines and describes very clearly the combination of intersectionality and Marxism. It talks about &amp;ldquo;materialism&amp;rdquo; as the scientific method which can be used to describe various class conflicts in the Marxism mould. It has influenced my thinking a lot recently. The article also cites an essay from the late-70s by French women’s liberation theorist Christine Delphy called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.feministes-radicales.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/christine-delphy-a-materialist-feminism-is-possible.pdf&#34;&gt;“A Materialist Feminism is possible”&lt;/a&gt; as inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://thegauntlife.blogspot.com/2016/12/running-in-trumpland.html&#34;&gt;Running in TrumpLand&lt;/a&gt; [The Gaunt Life] &amp;ndash; Sam Robinson is a long-distance runner who lives in the Bay Area. He grew up in the rural mid-west, and describes the transformation of the places he knew when young, to what they&amp;rsquo;ve become now. This is a particularly good read in the light of the recent election, and a rare perspective of someone who has actually seen and lived through the &amp;ldquo;ignored rust belt&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/07/05/magazine/what-happens-when-a-state-is-run-by-movie-stars.html&#34;&gt;What Happens When a State Is Run by Movie Stars?&lt;/a&gt; [The New York Times Magazine] &amp;ndash; An old article from last year that describes the fanatical politics of Tamil Nadu. This came up in my feed again as Jayalalithaa died earlier this month, and is a fascinating read.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://nymag.com/thecut/2015/05/i-was-a-proud-non-breeder-i-changed-my-mind.html&#34;&gt;I Was a Proud Non-Breeder. Then I Changed My Mind.&lt;/a&gt; [The Cut] &amp;ndash; Article from a journalist who had vowed to be child-free at 27 but found herself changing her mind later (for her own reasons). She explains her reasons in this post. To quote from the article &amp;ldquo;Not long ago, I learned the Arabic word Ya’aburnee from a friend’s cheesy Facebook graphic. Literally, “you bury me,” it means wanting to die before a loved one so as not to have to face the world without him or her in it. It’s a word that captures exactly my feeling for my husband. Part of the reason I didn’t want kids was because I feared they’d come between us, but if he were gone, I’d be frantic to hold on to a piece of him. Grasping this didn’t make me want a baby, exactly, but it started pushing me from “no” to, well, ambivalent.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newstatesman.com/science-tech/internet/2016/12/movie-doesn-t-exist-and-redditors-who-think-it-does&#34;&gt;The movie that doesn’t exist and the Redditors who think it does&lt;/a&gt; [NewStatesman] &amp;ndash; Over the years, hundreds of people online have shared memories of a cheesy nineties movie called “Shazaam”. There is no evidence that such a film was ever made. This article talks about the quirks of collective memory. There&amp;rsquo;s also a subreddit that abounds in things like these: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/MandelaEffect/&#34;&gt;/r/MandelaEffect&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music:4511ef69dc4e83813633e87570ad385e&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dilruba Na Raazi &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/avradeep.bhowmik/&#34;&gt;Avradeep&lt;/a&gt; introduced me to this song recently, calling it an earworm. He was right!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/279982238&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;movies-and-tv-shows:4511ef69dc4e83813633e87570ad385e&#34;&gt;Movies and TV Shows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1740299/&#34;&gt;The Man in the High Castle&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I binged through Season 1 of this gripping alternative history series, which imagines what the world might have looked like had the Allies lost WWII. Highly recommended for history buffs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;travel:4511ef69dc4e83813633e87570ad385e&#34;&gt;Travel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tokyo, Japan &amp;ndash; I finally took some vacation days and traveled to a new country for the year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:4511ef69dc4e83813633e87570ad385e&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://alltheflightdeals.com&#34;&gt;All the Flight Deals&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;m always on the lookout for new innovative attempts to find cheap flight deals. This new one came up on my feed, and the UX is designed to show the cheapest tickets out of an airport to &lt;em&gt;anywhere&lt;/em&gt; in the world. Useful when you want to plan a vacation based on ticket availability. There are some more features as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.indivisibleguide.com/&#34;&gt;Indivisible: A Practical Guide For Resisting the Trump Agenda&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A really comprehensive collection of information where former congressional staffers reveal best practices for making Congress listen. This is in response to the urgent to form a front against the racist and bigoted agenda of the incoming administration. This originally started out as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1DzOz3Y6D8g_MNXHNMJYAz1b41_cn535aU5UsN7Lj8X8/mobilebasic&#34;&gt;Google Doc&lt;/a&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s also a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/the-crowd-sourced-guide-to-fighting-trumps-agenda&#34;&gt;New Yorker article&lt;/a&gt; describing the story behind it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wrote a short Docker tutorial for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.creativebloq.com/net-magazine&#34;&gt;Netmag&lt;/a&gt;, a UK magazine. This is the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve done something like this, and I&amp;rsquo;m pretty excited! The issue goes on sale in late January.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/schooloflifechannel/videos&#34;&gt;The School of Life YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A series of eclectic and interesting short videos on various philosophical topics. The perfect content for watching during breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alison-jackson.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Alison Jackson&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Alison Jackson is a British artist, and some of her art portrays the &amp;ldquo;intimate, often salacious, imagined private moments of media icons&amp;rdquo;. These aren&amp;rsquo;t real images, but very intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://anchoreditions.com/blog/dorothea-lange-censored-photographs&#34;&gt;Dorothea Lange’s Censored Photographs of FDR’s Japanese Concentration Camps&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Dorothea Lange was hired by the U.S. government to make a photographic record of the &amp;ldquo;evacuation&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;relocation&amp;rdquo; of Japanese-Americans in 1942. She was eager to take the commission, despite being opposed to the effort, as she believed &amp;ldquo;a true record of the evacuation would be valuable in the future.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=23X14HS4gLk&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t Be a Sucker - 1947&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash;  The US Military produced this anti-fascist film the wake of WWII. It deconstructs the [sic] politically motivated social engineering of Germany by the Nazi regime. Pretty relevant today, and a sad reminder of how much the US has regressed in the time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/churning/&#34;&gt;/r/churning&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I recently learned of this subreddit for learning more about hacking credit card rewards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016 Year in Review</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/2016-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 01:20:02 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/2016-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Precisely a year ago, I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/off-to-hawaii&#34;&gt;Hawaii&lt;/a&gt; to try and
regain some sanity after what was a terrible 2015.
It offered little apart from endless pain, suffering, depression,
lack of community, and an uncontrollable feeling of helplessness.
So much so that the second half of the Hawaii trip was full of
panic attacks and attempts to cut the trip short. I was due to start a new job upon returning, and my Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis was still pending. I had no idea how I was going
to deal after getting back, manage personal relationships, and stop feeling
that life was pointless every other day&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2016 for me was a story in two parts &amp;ndash; pre-September, and post. The first part was
incredibly hard with a few positive blips, while the second was rosy,
with renewed hope going into 2017. I&amp;rsquo;m going to avoid any mention of politics
in this post, even though the events of the year deeply affected me on a personal level.
Although 2016 was painful to live through, it will be memorable. This is a feeling
I had failed to experience for several years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;master-s-thesis:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Master&amp;rsquo;s Thesis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big part of my woes was my Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis, which had dragged out for too long. After
failing to finish it at the end of 2015 and getting on filing fee status&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, expecting
to get done with it by February. But lack of progress for extended periods (in part due
to severe depression), coupled with a full-time job, and spending most of my free time
struggling with the thesis was a recipe for disaster. I failed to finish it by the May
deadline, had to register for the summer session (and pay nearly $2000 for it). Despite
finally managing to make good progress by the end of July and get a draft ready,
my committee refused to sign it, and the EECS department showed an immense lack
of desire to help me out. This left me looking at a $16000 tuition payment for the Fall
semester. I fought the bureaucracy and it was only in mid-November that I managed
to get the thesis submitted, in time to extend my immigration status, without which
I&amp;rsquo;d be forced to leave the country. The details of that
will be the subject of another post, but if there&amp;rsquo;s a lesson to be learned, it is that
&lt;em&gt;the department is not your friend&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/commencement.gif&#34; style=&#34;width:70%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Commencement - Pradeep walked on the same day&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, after over four years of struggle at UC Berkeley, I&amp;rsquo;m finally out of that
depressing environment and looking at better things, with at least a degree to show.
I even got to walk for commencement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;health:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Health&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this front, the year was mostly bad. I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned depression a few times
already, but 2016 was remarkable because I&amp;rsquo;m
finally ending a year on a reasonably good note. If the first half was about
lack of motivation, often to the extent of death ideation, then the second half
presented a renewed faith in my own abilities, along with a future that I at least
want to consider. Thanks to input from my girlfriend and some close friends, I also
got the opportunity to deeply introspect and work on personal flaws that have
always caused me great anxiety. Health issues for someone very close to me
were also a factor in an utterly disappointing time for the first part of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, I continued to work on my chronic physical injuries, with the hope of
one day getting back to endurance running and biking. I have a pretty solid understanding
of shoulder and hip anatomy as a result, and have tried literally every rehab technique
out there. Hopefully 2017 is the year I get a breakthrough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;work:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started working at Docker as a software engineer in early 2016.
I recovered some of the productivity I lost during grad
school, and got several new opportunities and experiences along the way. For one,
I learned a lot about working on open-source projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/github.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;My GitHub profile has never looked greener&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I got to &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016&#34;&gt;travel to multiple conferences&lt;/a&gt;
and give talks. These were among the primary reasons I had joined Docker in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/talk.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;First conference talk, at ContainerCamp 2016, London&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were slow periods too, but the year was overall a positive change on the work front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;travel:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Travel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all problems, 2016 was one of the best years for travel. Traveling was
easier since I had more money, opportunities, and time (post September).
I did make several trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boulder and Rocky Mountain National Park, Colorado (May) for a long weekend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seattle and Olympic National Park, Washington (June) for DockerCon, extended the trip by a few days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crater Lake National Park, Oregon (July) for a random weekend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/colorado.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/craterlake.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;White snow at 12,000ft in Rocky Mountain National Park, and deep blue water at Crater Lake&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;London, UK (September) for ContainerCamp, spent 4 extra days exploring the city&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;St. Louis, Missouri (September) for Strange Loop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bike camping trip to Samuel P Taylor State Park (September)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berlin, Germany (October) for the Docker Distributed Systems Summit, plus 3 extra days to explore the city&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mendocino, California (October) for a relaxing weekend getaway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/london.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/bikecamping.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/berlin.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/mendocino.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;London, start of the bike camping trip in SF, festival of lights at the Berliner Dom, California coastline in Mendocino&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portland, Oregon (November) for a friend&amp;rsquo;s bachelor trip weekend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maui, Hawaii (November) for the Thanksgiving break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tokyo, Japan (December) for vacation, and (finally) a new country for 2016&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;India (December), also for vacation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/portland.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/maui.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/tokyo.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:80%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Hipster Indian food in Portland, stunning ridges in Maui, street market in Tokyo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, this includes 3 international trips, 4 national parks, and several new
cities. I also spend a lot of time exploring locally in Oakland and San Francisco.
Up until the late May trip to Colorado, the only travel I had done was a weekend
trip to Seattle in March, but I&amp;rsquo;m glad with the way things turned out in the second
half of the year&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-highlights:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Other Highlights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I fulfilled a long standing dream of watching Arsenal play at the Emirates stadium. During my trip to London in September, I managed to get a ticket to the Arsenal vs Southampton game and thoroughly enjoyed it. Interestingly, just the month before, I&amp;rsquo;d watched the team play MLS All-Stars during their US tour but had no idea I&amp;rsquo;d actually be traveling to London soon after!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/emirates.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Arsenal vs Southampton at the Emirates Stadium in September&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wrote a short Docker tutorial for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.creativebloq.com/net-magazine&#34;&gt;Netmag&lt;/a&gt;, a UK magazine. This is the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve done something like this, and I&amp;rsquo;m pretty excited! The issue goes on sale in late January 2017.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some close friends got married (and several others got engaged). Wedding season was a lot of fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After several years of being indifferent, I celebrated my birthday (in difficult circumstances too, following my thesis rejection!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vasuki, Vaishnavi, and I organized a Bollywood costume themed Diwali party at our apartment, the first such party I&amp;rsquo;ve been part of organizing!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My adventure of the year was jumping into the freezing cold water of Crater Lake, after failing to carry swimming shorts but judging that the opportunity was not to be missed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;After some hiking on Wizard Island, I found the courage to jump into the frigid waters of Crater Lake! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/8Z2L1XKchn&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/8Z2L1XKchn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Traveler Boy (@nrt_travel) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nrt_travel/status/754849467581341696&#34;&gt;July 18, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I made the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/why-i-moved-to-static-website&#34;&gt;current version of my website and blog&lt;/a&gt; this year. It was a lot of work, but has been a net positive effort because it encouraged me to write more easily and frequently (hopefully more next year).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;looking-at-2017:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Looking at 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a private list of specific goals to pursue to next year, but the most
important thing I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to is settling down. For
too long now, life has felt like someone else in the driver&amp;rsquo;s seat, and I want to
end that. Hopefully, that will free up some time to devote to things I actually care
about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:1&#34;&gt;The irony here is that I&amp;rsquo;m still pretty privileged and &amp;ldquo;successful&amp;rdquo;, and that only adds up to a lot of guilt. One of my major goals is to get over this chronic depression.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:2&#34;&gt;A special kind of student registration that you can avail when only a thesis is due, and all course requirements are done. The upside is that you&amp;rsquo;re no longer required to pay tuition and can get a job.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:3&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a curious thing how despite being utterly depressed for long periods, my travelogue is pretty elaborate. It was more chance than anything that I managed to cover as much ground as I did, but satisfying that I took the opportunities that came my way. When I tried to reach out to a friend saying I was really sad, he mentioned that&amp;rsquo;s not at all how my Instagram profile looked like. Now you have another example of the pain hidden behind glittery social media profiles.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>August-November 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2016-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 13:40:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2016-11/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Given all the travel and being busy over August to November, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really get
much time to write or update the monthly log. I&amp;rsquo;m finally able to put something
together at the end of November, collecting everything for the last four months
in one place. These months have not only been eventful personally, but also politically.
The fallout of the election of Donald Trump has affected me a lot, and forced me to read
a lot more than I usually do. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to cover through everything in this log, and the
following one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:32da4def5c89171ea5d9ed8eeb1daa50&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/technology-37527719&#34;&gt;Has the US just given away the internet?&lt;/a&gt; [BBC News] &amp;ndash; A brief overview article that describes the background behind the recent decision to remove ICANN from US government oversight. Quoting the article, &amp;ldquo;The switch ends a transition that has essentially been in the works for around two decades, removing a dominant power the US had by circumstance rather than intention, and one which was causing friction in the international community.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@theonlytoby/history-tells-us-what-will-happen-next-with-brexit-trump-a3fefd154714#.vsypl0lw8&#34;&gt;History tells us what may happen next with Brexit &amp;amp; Trump&lt;/a&gt; [Medium] &amp;ndash; Several people are eager to dismiss Donald Trump as just another Republican
president. Personally, I&amp;rsquo;m extremely paranoid and afraid given the striking similarities
between Trump and many other fascist authoritarian demagogues littered throughout history.
This article (not the only one) articulates why that paranoia isn&amp;rsquo;t pointless rambling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@jhalderm/want-to-know-if-the-election-was-hacked-look-at-the-ballots-c61a6113b0ba#.wr4h9scx8&#34;&gt;Want to Know if the Election was Hacked? Look at the Ballots&lt;/a&gt; [Medium] &amp;ndash; A Computer Science professor from Michigan writes about how the implementation
of elections in America is extremely vulnerable to malicious attacks. While a lot of the
talk on &amp;ldquo;hacking&amp;rdquo; the election has already been done in mainstream media, several people
probably still treat it as science fiction. This article presents how it&amp;rsquo;s entirely
possible, and has probably already happened. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/dec/05/us-election-recount-michigan-donald-trump-hillary-clinton&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a Guardian news story&lt;/a&gt; that shows
how the Michigan recount might be affected just by shoddy machines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nybooks.com/daily/2016/11/10/trump-election-autocracy-rules-for-survival/&#34;&gt;Autocracy: Rules for Survival&lt;/a&gt; [NYR Daily] &amp;ndash; Wisdom from a seasoned Putin fighter, Masha Gessen, on how to deal with a Putin-wannabe. In her own words, &amp;ldquo;I have lived in autocracies most of my life, and have spent much of my career writing about Vladimir Putin’s Russia. I have learned a few rules for surviving in an autocracy and salvaging your sanity and self-respect. It might be worth considering them now.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lesswrong.com/lw/2pv/intellectual_hipsters_and_metacontrarianism/&#34;&gt;Intellectual Hipsters and Meta-Contrarianism&lt;/a&gt; [LessWrong] &amp;ndash; An old post I&amp;rsquo;d read a long
time ago, and pulled up again recently. Based on the (mostly political) discussions over
the last few weeks, it has felt extremely relevant. I strongly recommend reading this
post. On several issues, I feel that my own behavior has shifted around from
&amp;ldquo;mainstream&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;contrarian&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;meta-contrarian&amp;rdquo; (back and forth too). The
important point is in the conclusion &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;If meta-contrarianism is a real tendency in
over-intelligent people, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean they should immediately abandon their beliefs;
that would just be meta-meta-contrarianism. It means that they need to recognize the
meta-contrarian tendency within themselves and so be extra suspicious and careful about
a desire to believe something contrary to the prevailing contrarian wisdom, especially
if they really enjoy doing so.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a ton of other election coverage I&amp;rsquo;ve shared on Twitter, Facebook, or in direct
messages to people. There&amp;rsquo;s also some more I&amp;rsquo;d like to add here, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/12/03/opinion/sunday/why-blue-states-are-the-real-tea-party.html&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2016/12/hillary-clinton-working-class/509477&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salon.com/2016/12/03/fake-news-a-fake-president-and-a-fake-country-welcome-to-america-land-of-no-context/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;books:32da4def5c89171ea5d9ed8eeb1daa50&#34;&gt;Books&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really need to get back to reading more. I&amp;rsquo;ve barely read any books this year, but I
did manage to finish one that I started way back in May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2657.To_Kill_a_Mockingbird&#34;&gt;To Kill a Mockingbird&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve read really few books all my life, much less classics. It&amp;rsquo;s a striking commentary on race and how it functions in America (including, in my opinion, up to the modern day).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;travel:32da4def5c89171ea5d9ed8eeb1daa50&#34;&gt;Travel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to travel the following places during this time&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;London, UK &amp;ndash; For the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/containercamp-pwlconf-strangeloop&#34;&gt;ContainerCamp&lt;/a&gt; conference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;St. Louis, Missouri &amp;ndash; For the &lt;a href=&#34;(/blog/containercamp-pwlconf-strangeloop&#34;&gt;PWLConf and Strange Loop&lt;/a&gt;) conferences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berlin, Germany &amp;ndash; For the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/containercamp-pwlconf-strangeloop&#34;&gt;Docker Distributed Systems Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maui, Hawaii &amp;ndash; For vacation!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this travel, despite being very tiring, was a great deal of fun and made me very happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;movies-and-tv-shows:32da4def5c89171ea5d9ed8eeb1daa50&#34;&gt;Movies and TV Shows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4574334&#34;&gt;Stranger Things&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Everyone has raved about this show enough, so I don&amp;rsquo;t need to write a lot, but the charm of 80s suburban America (I&amp;rsquo;ve seen a lot of this on TV growing up) creats a nostalgia factor for a time that I never lived. It reminded me a lot of the X-Files as well. The Soundtrack is memorable too. Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/175929311&#34;&gt;video link&lt;/a&gt; for references.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2401256/&#34;&gt;The Night Of&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A short series that I&amp;rsquo;d label as a dark criminal justice drama. I highly recommend this to anyone who&amp;rsquo;s interested in that kind of thing. The slow-paced movement with powerful character development makes it quite a gripping series.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4818930/&#34;&gt;Waiting&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A sensible Bollywood drama that shows two individuals coping in different ways with the loss of their respective spouses, and finding friendship in each other.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt5743656/&#34;&gt;Phobia&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A good Bollywood thriller, after a long time. Good performance by Radhika Apte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2948356/&#34;&gt;Zootopia&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Like most good animated movies, Zootopia is funny and well-made. The reason it stood out for me though, was because it portrays social classes really well. Think discrimination, stereotypes, oppression &amp;ndash; there&amp;rsquo;s everything.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt5571734/&#34;&gt;Pink&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Another good Bollywood movie, this time a criminal justice drama, built around the issues of sexual assualt and consent. One of the more mature presentations on the topic in Bollywood, especially given its reputation of miserably failing on these topics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:32da4def5c89171ea5d9ed8eeb1daa50&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wonder-bot.com/&#34;&gt;Wonder Bot&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A chat bot that you can tell something, and it&amp;rsquo;ll remember for you. Basically a natural-language KV store of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/Computerphile/videos&#34;&gt;Phile YouTube channels&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A series of easy to understand videos on various topics, like computer science, mathematics, philosophy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2QzAl4HIXY8&#34;&gt;Coke Studio for the Deaf&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; How would a deaf person percieve and experience music? This video explores.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/10/13/us/politics/david-mccraw-trump-letter.html&#34;&gt;The Times’s Lawyer Responds to Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Just pretty badass. With the current state of politics, we do need more fearless journalism and patronage for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference Travel in 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 03:32:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been fortunate to have traveled extensively during the Fall of 2016.
A good chunk of that travel was because of work. Back in September, I visited London
and St. Louis (Missouri), and attended three different conferences. Later in October,
I flew back to Europe, this time to Berlin to attend my fourth conference in two months&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
This post focuses on the conferences. I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about the sightseeing I did
in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;containercamp:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;ContainerCamp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://container.camp/uk/2016&#34;&gt;ContainerCamp&lt;/a&gt; was a one day conference in London, focusing
on topics in software container technology, with 12 talks by people in different
areas. I gave a talk on the project I&amp;rsquo;m currently working on,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.github.com/docker/swarmkit&#34;&gt;Docker SwarmKit&lt;/a&gt;,
the open-source container orchestration framework, which was also my
first conference talk ever! That I would be delivering this talk was confirmed
rather late, which gave me little time to prepare and get a UK visa, but things
somehow worked out (my visa arrived the morning I was scheduled to leave), and I
made it to London &amp;ndash; my second visit to the city after last year&amp;rsquo;s UK trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference itself was held at Picturehouse Central, a movie theater in
Piccadilly Circus, which I thought was a very unique venue for a conference.
Talks were projected on to a huge movie screen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;From the source: how &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/docker&#34;&gt;@docker&lt;/a&gt; sees orchestration and tolerating failure in orchestration &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nishanttotla&#34;&gt;@nishanttotla&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/containercamp&#34;&gt;@containercamp&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Ju7OH8qeCB&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Ju7OH8qeCB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alex Ellis (@alexellisuk) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alexellisuk/status/774194023208738816&#34;&gt;September 9, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I did a decent job for a first talk, which also included a live demo and
a shoutout by Mark Shuttleworth! The talk video is
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SLHMkVQnJOs&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, in case you&amp;rsquo;re interested.
Among other talks, I particularly enjoyed the following ones&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Utf-A4rODH8&#34;&gt;Building a container from scratch in Go&lt;/a&gt; by Liz Rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0z3yusiCOCk&#34;&gt;Why we need a different container purely for apps&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All talks, including the ones above are on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCvksXSnLqIVM_uFB7xyrsSg&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After ContainerCamp, I had roughly four days to explore London. From there, I flew
directly to St. Louis, for the next couple of conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;papers-we-love-conference-pwlconf:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;Papers We Love Conference (PWLConf)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://paperswelove.org/&#34;&gt;Papers We Love&lt;/a&gt; is a series of meetups in different cities
around the world, where people come together to discuss research papers they love
from different fields. Given its popularity, the organizers decided to set up the
first PWL conference, which was co-located with Strange Loop in St. Louis.
PWLConf was actually the only conference I was meant to attend, until some
fortuitous events allowed me to attend Strange Loop as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the talks, particularly because they were quite academic in
nature, and I&amp;rsquo;ve missed academic talks since leaving grad school. There were some
I particularly enjoyed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gxf5glthqrk&amp;amp;index=1&amp;amp;list=PLGRqfvsPiRShwIXMA5P3WR_9LgBOAdvw4&#34;&gt;Randomized Gossip Methods&lt;/a&gt; by Dahlia Malkhi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aR_UOSGEizE&amp;amp;list=PLGRqfvsPiRShwIXMA5P3WR_9LgBOAdvw4&amp;amp;index=5&#34;&gt;Design Philosophy in Networked Systems&lt;/a&gt; by Justine Sherry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, all videos are on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLGRqfvsPiRShwIXMA5P3WR_9LgBOAdvw4&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;strange-loop:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;Strange Loop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My attendance at Strange Loop was fortunate. Strange Loop is an annual software
conference held in St. Louis, covering really intriguing and eclectic topics
related to software, mathematics, or their applications to other areas. Other
industry conferences that I&amp;rsquo;ve been to have had extremely specific focus, including
a lot of vendors advertising their products. Strange Loop was nothing like that, and
all talks I attended could basically be put under one umbrella &amp;ndash;
&amp;ldquo;the joy of Computer Science&amp;rdquo;. I also got to meet and talk to some people whom
I&amp;rsquo;d only followed on Twitter before. Since there were too many parallel tracks,
I couldn&amp;rsquo;t attend all interesting talks, but out of the ones I did, some really
stood out&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C4rT0lgJr6U&#34;&gt;Government Hacking and Human Rights: The Why and the How&lt;/a&gt; by Amie Stepanovich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fNe1i7nVbXI&#34;&gt;Humanities x Technology&lt;/a&gt; by Ashley Nelson-Hornstein&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HfD9IMZ9rKY&#34;&gt;Systems programming as a swiss army knife&lt;/a&gt; by Julia Evans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, all talk videos are now online on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C4rT0lgJr6U&amp;amp;list=PLcGKfGEEONaDvuLDFFKRfzbsaBuVVXdYa&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;, and worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;docker-distributed-systems-summit:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;Docker Distributed Systems Summit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small invitation-only event, the summit was a great way to meet people
directly engaged in the Docker community. A part of the attraction was also the
chance to visit Berlin for the first time. Once again, late confirmations led to
rushed planning, and some good fortune allowed me to get a visa in time. My job was
only to attend the talks, engage with people, and lead some discussions. I thought
this was a great format for two reasons &amp;ndash; I got to learn more about Docker&amp;rsquo;s
other products myself, and the small size of the conference enabled many
personal interactions that allowed for deeper conversations.
The &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.docker.com/2016/10/docker-distributed-system-summit-videos-podcast-episodes/&#34;&gt;official blog post&lt;/a&gt; contains links to
the talk videos, slides, and other information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-conference-travel-in-general:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;On Conference Travel in General&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, these were rewarding trips, albeit tiring. Being away from home for all
these days sounds great in principle, but as I found out, travel is rather
disruptive when it&amp;rsquo;s not purely for vacation. Still, I&amp;rsquo;m incredibly lucky to
have had all these opportunities. In fact, this was one of the primary reasons I
joined Docker. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to doing more of this in 2017, but
probably with a little more focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;I also attended a fifth conference this year, back in June &amp;ndash; DockerCon 2016. This was my first DockerCon, and a pretty interesting affair. For one, it gave me significant motivation to work hard preceding the event, and the project I was working on was at the center of major announcements. I also ended up staying for the week in Seattle, so that was great as well. I decided not to write much about DockerCon in this post because I barely attended any talks (booth duty!), and enough has already been written by others about it.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>July 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2016-07/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 13:40:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2016-07/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:4d953b0173aaaefba5610e347008259b&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsj.com/articles/the-day-i-got-my-green-card-1467385905&#34;&gt;The Day I Got My Green Card&lt;/a&gt; [The Wall Street Journal] &amp;ndash; Amidst general gloom and doom, a rare positive story about immigration. Several people (immigrants and citizens) regularly face struggles here, when it comes to issues of inclusion and acceptance in an increasingly polarized world. If you read this though, you&amp;rsquo;ll feel that a lot of luck was still involved in the outcome being positive, and it&amp;rsquo;s hard to ignore the immense privilege the author has.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeed.com/priyaalikaelias/shame-shame-pappi-shame?utm_term=.krvo1aEB3#.qtJO1obld&#34;&gt;Dudes, You Have GOT To Stop Shaming The Women You Have Casual Sex With&lt;/a&gt; [BuzzFeed] &amp;ndash; A short article about how the idea that women can&amp;rsquo;t really handle casual sex is just a stereotype. Women can certainly want casual sex, but some men can&amp;rsquo;t seem to accept that fact.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/2015/05/volcanoes-cascades-quiet-lately/&#34;&gt;Why Have Volcanoes in the Cascades Been So Quiet Lately?&lt;/a&gt; [Wired] &amp;ndash; I have gradually become more and more fascinated with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cascade_Volcanoes&#34;&gt;Cascade volcanoes&lt;/a&gt; and the associated geological history. I found this article via Googling, and it briefly describes the Cascade subduction zone, following which it tries to analyze why the volcanic arc has been rather quiet lately.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thenewsminute.com/article/being-queer-iit-my-time-campus-left-me-scars-last-lifetime-46749&#34;&gt;Being queer in an IIT: ‘My time on campus left me scars to last a lifetime’&lt;/a&gt; [The News Minute] &amp;ndash; A man&amp;rsquo;s account of how his life at an IIT (in the early 2000s) was painful due to the homophobic and heteronormative culture of the time. I don&amp;rsquo;t think things were any different when I was at IIT Bombay, and feel sad for not speaking out against said culture. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested, &lt;a href=&#34;http://orinam.net/student-response-campus-homophobia-bengaluru/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is another related article.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/what-you-should-know-if-you-want-to-work-remotely-and-t-1783928805&#34;&gt;What You Should Know If You Want to Work Remotely and Travel the World&lt;/a&gt; [Lifehacker] &amp;ndash; A good article to read if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in satisfying your wanderlust while still keeping a full-time job that allows you to work remotely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeed.com/azeenghorayshi/michael-katze-investigation?utm_term=.ve8RL5GWA#.hhZgPJBxa&#34;&gt;“He Thinks He’s Untouchable”&lt;/a&gt; [BuzzFeed] &amp;ndash; Michael Katze, famous for his studies of Ebola and the flu, ran a lab at the University of Washington where intoxication and sexual harassment went unchecked, and he misused public resources for personal gain, according to two investigations. This is another story in the line of recent revelations detailing sexual harassment on prominent university campuses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-14432401&#34;&gt;What is fracking and why is it controversial?&lt;/a&gt; [BBC News] &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve been hearing a lot about fracking in the news, and was curious, so googled to find this article that describes briefly what fracking is, it&amp;rsquo;s advantages, and potential negative impact. Fracking has been used in North America with a great deal of success recently, helping drive down oil prices. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hydraulic_fracturing_in_the_United_States&#34;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; Wikipedia article covers North America in great detail.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;movies-and-tv-shows:4d953b0173aaaefba5610e347008259b&#34;&gt;Movies and TV Shows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0359950/&#34;&gt;The Secret Life of Walter Mitty&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;d been wanting to watch this movie for a while now, and I did this week. The storyline is ridiculous and strange and makes no sense on one hand, but it was so beautiful and inspiring on the other. I would like to stick with the latter, and recommend it to you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2929690/&#34;&gt;Margarita, with a Straw&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; This is a movie about a girl with cerebral palsy, and it explores her sexuality. It&amp;rsquo;s really rare to have a movie that treats disabled individuals like normal people with normal desires, and it&amp;rsquo;s very refreshing. In addition, it&amp;rsquo;s also a movie that explores homosexuality in a respectable way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:4d953b0173aaaefba5610e347008259b&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://forestry.io/&#34;&gt;Forestry.io&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A CMS for Hugo and Jekyll sites. I&amp;rsquo;ll watch this closely, if it can deliver, because the simplicity of a CMS, combined with the power of static sites could be a huge win!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/explainlikeimfive/comments/3du1qm/eli5_why_is_it_so_controversial_when_someone_says/&#34;&gt;ELI5: Why is it so controversial when someone says &amp;ldquo;All Lives Matter&amp;rdquo; instead of &amp;ldquo;Black Lives Matter&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; For all the people who feel threateaned by the Black Lives Matter movement, and just keep repeating &amp;ldquo;All Lives Matter&amp;rdquo; in response, here&amp;rsquo;s a great read, with a really simple analogy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pokemon.com/us/pokemon-video-games/pokemon-go/&#34;&gt;Pokémon Go&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; This is a new exciting augmented-reality game that I started playing this week. The idea is that you use your phone as a Pokedex to catch and battle Pokemon in the real world. Similar in principle to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ingress.com/&#34;&gt;Ingress&lt;/a&gt;, which was launched more than 3 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MRBZDmf1jSw&#34;&gt;My Dinner with Andre (We are bored)&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I discovered this really articulate monologue and liked it. It seems fairly relevant, especially after I wrote about Pokémon Go above.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>June 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2016-06/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 13:40:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2016-06/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:7f01c44aac0808d0d8513388625a0bcb&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeed.com/katiejmbaker/heres-the-powerful-letter-the-stanford-victim-read-to-her-ra?utm_term=.bwwlobVyk#.gsqJBEQDP&#34;&gt;Here Is The Powerful Letter The Stanford Victim Read Aloud To Her Attacker&lt;/a&gt; [BuzzFeed] &amp;ndash; An unconscious woman was raped by a 20 year old Stanford student behind a dumpster, and he was convicted but only got jail time of 6 months as punishment. This article is powerful, and has been evoking a lot of outrage over the awful treatment that rape victims are regularly subjected to, and the leniancy of the sentence. You&amp;rsquo;ve likely seen it shared everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vitals.lifehacker.com/the-medical-screenings-all-men-need-and-when-1779846310&#34;&gt;The Medical Screenings All Men Need, and When&lt;/a&gt; [Lifehacker] &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve been considering figuring out a regular medical treatment plan (annual health checkup etc.) and this article seemed like a good starting point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/culture/culture-desk/how-silicon-valley-nails-silicon-valley&#34;&gt;How &amp;ldquo;Silicon Valley&amp;rdquo; Nails Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt; [The New Yorker] &amp;ndash; A lot of amazing behind the scenes info about how Silicon Valley (the show) is created. And in some cases, real life is even weirder than the show, even though the show is meant to be a caricature of the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeed.com/devangp/aavite-rovay-nai?utm_term=.wy3e0EKJo#.eiYYn8x4&#34;&gt;Indians are never taught to talk to their parents as adults, and that’s a problem&lt;/a&gt; [BuzzFeed] &amp;ndash; Continuing the series of some genuinely good articles on BuzzFeed, this one focuses on how interactions between Indian kids and parents are comically shallow on the emotional front, especially when the kids grow up. While this has not entirely been my experience, I can relate to some of it, and definitely have friends who can relate to all of it. It also appears that the original article appeared on a blog, then Reddit, then here, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried to track down the source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@violetblue/but-he-does-good-work-6710df9d9029#.uz90bya0k&#34;&gt;“But he does good work.”&lt;/a&gt; [Medium] &amp;ndash; One of the stories behind Tor project evangelist Jacob Appelbaum and the sexual harassment and rape charges against him. It also touches upon the deep rooted culture in the tech that protects harassers. Violet Blue (the author) also reveals details about her interactions with Appelbaum in the past.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jxyzabc.blogspot.com/2016/06/counter-advice-for-phd.html&#34;&gt;Counter-Advice for the PhD&lt;/a&gt; [Jean Yang] &amp;ndash; A lot of successful academics give advice that doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense for those who are new or struggling, because they forget what it was actually like to be in that position. This post addresses some of that, and would have been very helpful had I read it at the start of my (failed) PhD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://a16z.com/2016/06/23/options-timing/&#34;&gt;The Lack of Options for (Startup Employees’) Options&lt;/a&gt; [Andreessen Horowitz] &amp;ndash; This post from the VC firm talks about how the 10 year exercise window doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense, and amounts to a &amp;ldquo;transfer&amp;rdquo; of wealth from newer employees to older ones who quit. It has been controversial this month, especially given that it does not provide any good alternative solutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dangelo.quora.com/10-Year-Exercise-Periods-Make-Sense?share=1&#34;&gt;10-Year Exercise Periods Make Sense&lt;/a&gt; [Quora] &amp;ndash; Adam D&amp;rsquo;Angelo, the co-founder and CEO of Quora responded to the above post, coming out in favor of the 10 year exercise window. Note that Quora was the first company to implement it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music:7f01c44aac0808d0d8513388625a0bcb&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Masala Coffee is a band from Kerala. I don&amp;rsquo;t know much about them, except that this cover is beautiful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AB2ACJ22fhY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;movies-and-tv-shows:7f01c44aac0808d0d8513388625a0bcb&#34;&gt;Movies and TV Shows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2575988/&#34;&gt;Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I first watched a bit of the show when it first came out, but didn&amp;rsquo;t find it quite appealing. But after having worked at a software startup for a few months now, I can appreciate the satire and humor much better. It&amp;rsquo;s crude, brash, over the top, and does a great job at making fun of the seemingly strange culture that pervades Silicon Valley. If you find an aspect of the show offensive or peculiar (eg. overt sexism, racism, conceit, etc.), then remember that the real thing is even weirder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4044364/&#34;&gt;Citizenfour&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A thrilling documentary about Edward Snowden&amp;rsquo;s correspondence with the journalists who helped him break the story on government surveillance. It features all the real people involved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4434004/&#34;&gt;Udta Punjab&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A chilling movie about the drug menace that&amp;rsquo;s supposed to be cripping the state of Punjab (India). It&amp;rsquo;s one of the few Bollywood movies that doesn&amp;rsquo;t sugar coat things, and presents a legitimately grim picture. Highly recommended, and glad it avoided most censorship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:7f01c44aac0808d0d8513388625a0bcb&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bankofamerica.com/privacy/accounts-cards/shopsafe.go&#34;&gt;ShopSafe&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Bank of America offers a program where you can create a temporary credit card online, that links to an existing card you own (one level of indirection). You can also set an expiry date and maximum (possibly recurring) limit on the card! This is extremely useful in places where you don&amp;rsquo;t trust the vendor enough to provide your real credit card number. I&amp;rsquo;m going to use this extensively now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>May 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2016-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 13:40:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/monthly-2016-05/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:934191705702a94fc45e2007e1bfaf5f&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rkoutnik.com/2016/04/21/implementers-solvers-and-finders.html&#34;&gt;Implementers, Solvers, and Finders&lt;/a&gt; [rkoutnik.com] &amp;ndash; This article describes three types of roles software engineers can fulfill in a company. Implementers implement solutions handed to them, solvers solve problems handed to them, finders discover those problems. It points out how most engineers only become finders when they choose the management ladder, and how there might still be hope for those who don&amp;rsquo;t want to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@lydiapolgreen/why-people-pay-to-read-the-new-york-times-60720880e707#.n7zkrugsv&#34;&gt;Why people pay to read The New York Times&lt;/a&gt; [Medium] &amp;ndash; This is a brilliant point of view, and one that fully aligns with how I think of journalism in the digital age. At a time when Facebook and social media have immense control over platforms, there is still a lot of value in good journalism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://gizmodo.com/former-facebook-workers-we-routinely-suppressed-conser-1775461006&#34;&gt;Former Facebook Workers: We Routinely Suppressed Conservative News&lt;/a&gt; [Gizmodo] &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve long believed that the algorithms run by giant tech companies have immense power when it comes to swaying public opinion, even if inadvertently. But if there&amp;rsquo;s intent, things can get really tricky. It&amp;rsquo;s okay to have biases in news reporting, and be explicit about them, but for people to believe that the content they read online is organic is dangerous if it&amp;rsquo;s false. When viewed in conjunction with the above article, a few people at a few companies controlling the most used information channels sounds very dystopian, especially since accountability is suspect. Key lesson though? Get your news from multiple sources!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zachholman.com/posts/the-new-10-year-vesting-schedule&#34;&gt;The New 10-Year Vesting Schedule&lt;/a&gt; [zachholman.com] &amp;ndash; A timely and appropriate rant about how the rules around stock options are created such that regular startup employees have the least flexibility and control over how they can retain their hard-earned share in the company, while investors and founders get away with much more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeed.com/sonaligupta2/single-female-disabled-apps-are-saving-me-from-inaccessible?utm_term=.ugdnMXv5W#.vge5kwLAl&#34;&gt;Single With A Disability: Apps Are Saving Me From Awkward Dates And Awful Rishtas&lt;/a&gt; [BuzzFeed] &amp;ndash; A personal account of a woman with muscular dystrophy regarding her experience with dating and arranged marriage in India. Finding an accepting partner can be extremely challenging as a disabled person, and this is a rare story on the topic. I wish it were longer, but good read nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/01/fashion/modern-love-netflix-relationship.html&#34;&gt;The Entire Netflix History of Us&lt;/a&gt; [The New York Times] &amp;ndash; A story of when a couple broke up and their shared Netflix account was the only remaining connection between them. I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/column/modern-love&#34;&gt;Modern Love&lt;/a&gt; columns on NYT, because they explore the idea of love at levels and in contexts that are extremely thought-provoking. In many cases, they bring me agonizingly close to feeling painful emotions, but that is probably why I read them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/16/world/americas/dying-infants-and-no-medicine-inside-venezuelas-failing-hospitals.html&#34;&gt;Dying Infants and No Medicine: Inside Venezuela’s Failing Hospitals&lt;/a&gt; [The New York Times] &amp;ndash; I had no idea things were so bad in Venezuela. This article reports a disastrous failure of infrastructure in the country, under political instability and poor economic planning. In particular, hospitals seem to be very badly affected leading to growing mortality rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vox.com/2016/5/26/11790878/google-oracle-fight-explained&#34;&gt;Why Google&amp;rsquo;s victory in a copyright fight with Oracle is a big deal&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A short summary of the background between the Google vs. Oracle case that&amp;rsquo;s been all over the news. This includes the current status of the case and legal implications of either party winning. A good start if you know absolutely nothing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music:934191705702a94fc45e2007e1bfaf5f&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the good music I&amp;rsquo;ve recently discovered has been from Coke Studio, thanks to Soundcloud. Tum Naraz Ho is a soothing melody about the time when a person&amp;rsquo;s lover is upset with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/168257758&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shakar Wandaan Re is a very energetic composition with catchy and playful lyrics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/171491148&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shakar Wandaan Re is also a song from the Pakistani movie called &lt;em&gt;Ho Mann Jahaan&lt;/em&gt;. The movie version is more of a dance number, but still extremely likable and funky.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/231087059&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:934191705702a94fc45e2007e1bfaf5f&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blockstack.org/&#34;&gt;Blockstack&lt;/a&gt; is the application stack for building decentralized, blockchain-based applications that don&amp;rsquo;t need any servers to operate. Blockstack applications can be built quickly by plugging into Blockstack&amp;rsquo;s services for identity, naming, storage and authentication. I don&amp;rsquo;t quite understand how this works yet, but is very intriguing and will spend time understanding blockchains. &lt;a href=&#34;https://onename.com/&#34;&gt;Onename&lt;/a&gt; seems to be one such service.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://projectinclude.org/&#34;&gt;Project Include&lt;/a&gt; is a cool new initiative by some influential tech ladies to address diversity and inclusion in the tech industry, by creating an opt-in system of accountability for startups. The website also has some nice reading material that I&amp;rsquo;ll gradually make my way through.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11650721&#34;&gt;One of my research projects&lt;/a&gt; from my first year of grad school made it to the front page of Hacker News for a while on Saturday. It was unexpected, and probably not a big deal, but was cool since I haven&amp;rsquo;t been there before.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bayareadrama.company/the-domestic-crusaders&#34;&gt;The Domestic Crusaders&lt;/a&gt; was a play I watched on Saturday. This was Bay Area Drama Company&amp;rsquo;s version of the original play by Wajahat Ali, focusing on the Muslim immigrant experience in post &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt; America.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.twitter.com/2016/track-the-pulse-of-the-us-presidential-race&#34;&gt;Track the pulse of the US presidential race&lt;/a&gt; [Twitter Blog] &amp;ndash; Twitter often makes really neat visualizations using tweet data. This one explores &amp;ldquo;how the Twitter buzz about each candidate has shifted week over week since September&amp;rdquo;. Look &lt;a href=&#34;https://interactive.twitter.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should follow &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jaythenerdkid&#34;&gt;Aaminah&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter, she often does very intriguing tweetstorms. This month she&amp;rsquo;s done some amazing ones about mental illness. If you&amp;rsquo;ve experienced mental illness, or know someone who has, or just want to be helpful, read these: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jaythenerdkid/status/730131499262062592&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jaythenerdkid/status/730133438460727296&#34;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jaythenerdkid/status/730420676570566656&#34;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jaythenerdkid/status/730434924654804992&#34;&gt;four&lt;/a&gt;. Remember to scroll up and wait for all tweets to load.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nishanttotla/status/732313216768843776&#34;&gt;commencement&lt;/a&gt; this month as a Masters student. It was fun, especially since I couldn&amp;rsquo;t attend the one after college.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I visited Colorado this month! For more than two years now, I&amp;rsquo;ve really wanted to go there and never managed to. This time though, I took the initiative before a long weekend and finally did it! I also traveled with friends, something I don&amp;rsquo;t do quite often.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/MyDepressionLooksLike?src=hash&#34;&gt;#MyDepressionLooksLike&lt;/a&gt; seemed to be trending on Twitter for a little while, with people describing their experience of depression. It was strangely reassuring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.getairhelp.com/en/&#34;&gt;AirHelp&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A website that helps you get rightful compensation when your flight is delayed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/blog/2176-diversity-and-inclusion-at-github&#34;&gt;Diversity and Inclusion at GitHub&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; GitHub faced public criticism over harassment and poor work culture within the company, but have since worked hard to pull their act together. Good to see such a turnaround.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Like Watching Hands</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/i-like-watching-hands/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 11:21:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/i-like-watching-hands/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I work at cafés a lot, and like observing people. I try to not be creepy, but it&amp;rsquo;s intriguing to note how people do things, imagine what they might be working on, or their story. One thing in particular I&amp;rsquo;ve always loved is to see the act of people packing their bags &amp;ndash; laptop, pens, glasses etc. It&amp;rsquo;s weird, but recently I consciously realized this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I noticed that I also like to watch hands writing, typing, or performing a number of other complex tasks that are really accessible only to human hands. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why I&amp;rsquo;m sharing this, but is there anyone else out there who feels the same?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Brothers, Not the Brotherhood</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/brothers-not-the-brotherhood/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2016 12:55:36 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/brothers-not-the-brotherhood/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve grown to love this quote from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/33600.Shantaram&#34;&gt;Shantaram&lt;/a&gt;, a book by Gregory David Roberts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;custom-quote&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h1 class=&#34;icon-quote-left&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But I was alone, and for two reasons: The mafia was theirs, not mine. For them, the organisation always came first. But I was loyal to the men, not the mafia; to the brothers, not the brotherhood. I worked for the mafia, but I didn&#39;t join it. I&#39;m not a joiner. I never found a club or clan or idea that was more important to me than the men and women who believed in it.&lt;span class=&#34;author&#34;&gt; - Gregory David Roberts&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t read the book yet, so not entirely sure of the full context. But I particularly like to see in the context of any company I work at, and my relationship to it. My loyalty is to my friends, and the individuals who work at the company, not the institution itself. Companies (particularly tech companies) like to portray their work culture as a family. And it&amp;rsquo;s all too easy to believe in this &amp;ldquo;brotherhood&amp;rdquo;. But there is none. The company exists for its own interests, and you&amp;rsquo;re on your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bothra90&#34;&gt;Abhay&lt;/a&gt; for telling me about the quote. I hope to read the book in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>