<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Monthly-log on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Monthly-log on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:12:44 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>December 2017-January 2018</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2018-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:12:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2018-01/</guid>
      <description>Articles  India’s Hospitals Are Filling Up With Desperate Americans [Foreign Policy] &amp;ndash; A perspective on the medical tourism industry in India which talks about how this impacts healthcare access for poorer Indians.
 United States of South India: Can a southern collective get us a better deal from Delhi? [The News Minute] &amp;ndash; Economic arguments for why the states of southern India need to make a united political stand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>November 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:12:42 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-11/</guid>
      <description>Articles  The Glaring Blind Spot of the &amp;lsquo;Me Too&amp;rsquo; Movement [The Atlantic] &amp;ndash; Quoting from the article, &amp;ldquo;Though the #MeToo movement has made clear the insidiousness and prevalence of sexual harassment and assault, it has also been centered mostly on the experiences of white, affluent, and educated women. One doesn’t need to look far to see instances of women of color being forgotten or sidelined.&amp;rdquo; As much as we talk about intersectionality, we need to do better at applying it in practice when powerful movements like these take shape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>September-October 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 19:18:33 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-10/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve found little motivation to write in the last couple of months and so I haven&amp;rsquo;t bothered to publish the September log. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t stop consuming content &amp;ndash; to the contrary, I read more articles than ever, so this is going to be a really long list.
Articles  You Are the Product [London Review of Books] &amp;ndash; This is a long essay that critiques the mission of Facebook as a product and company, while considering the true role it plays in our individual and social lives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>August 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-08/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2017 17:35:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-08/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s been a hectic month with some travel and a move to San Francisco finally materializing. As a result, I haven&amp;rsquo;t had time to do much reading.
Articles  We Need to Talk About Digital Blackface in Reaction GIFs [Teen Vogue] &amp;ndash; This was something I had been thinking about from time to time, but of course this article articulately talks about the implications of non-black people overusing GIFs of black people online.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>July 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 23:14:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-07/</guid>
      <description>Articles  The Uninhabitable Earth [NYMag] &amp;ndash; A comprehensive look at the worst-case scenarios resulting from climate change in the coming decades. This article is decidedly alarmist, but deliberately so. As climate change denial becomes more common, it argues that an alarmist approach is required to counter it, especially as climate scientists continue to be cautious about long term effects. On a related note, there was another climate change article in the New York Times this month.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>June 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-06/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:27:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-06/</guid>
      <description>Articles  The Difference Between Liberalism and Leftism [Current Affairs] &amp;ndash; Simple explanation of the difference between liberalism and leftism (mostly focused on America) that you probably already know about, but the key here is an argument for collaboration between liberals and leftists. Quite often, people from either group refuse to work with those of the other group to steer the progressive movement. While the two might be fundamentally irreconcilable, short term collaboration makes sense.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>May 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 16:18:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-05/</guid>
      <description>Articles  ‘I don’t know who I am without it’: the truth about long-term antidepressant use [The Guardian] &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;Prescriptions have doubled in a decade, but very little is known about the effect of taking SSRIs for years and years. Is it a lifesaver or a happiness trap?&amp;rdquo; To be fair, this MUST NOT be taken as a case against antidepressants, which are the difference between life and death for many people.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>April 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-04/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 15:24:19 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-04/</guid>
      <description>Articles  The Fighter [The New York Times Magazine] &amp;ndash; Pulitzer Prize winning story about US Marine Sam Siatta&amp;rsquo;s traumatic experiences while serving in Afghanistan, and difficulties reintegrating into social life after coming back. It&amp;rsquo;s a long and powerful read.
 When Pixels Collide [sudoscript] &amp;ndash; For April Fool&amp;rsquo;s Day this year, Reddit launched an experiment, giving all its users a blank canvas called Place. Each user could place a pixel (out of 16 colors) anywhere on the canvas as many times as they wanted, waiting a few minutes between each time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>March 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-03/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 12:00:30 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-03/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s a full year of publishing a monthly log! The last time I stuck to something for that long, I got stock options.
Articles  The Trip Treatment [The New Yorker] &amp;ndash; The most comprehensive article I&amp;rsquo;ve ever read about the use of psychedelics for medical treatment (mostly addiction, anxiety, and other mental health conditions). There is renewed enthusiasm in the promise of psychedelic drugs for treatment (this article mostly focuses on psilocybin, the active compound in magic mushrooms), even as they continue to be outlawed, researchers face difficulties getting funding, and several scientific questions remain unanswered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>February 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-02/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 15:25:25 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-02/</guid>
      <description>Articles  Some Troublesome Questions for Liberals on Borders [Current Affairs] &amp;ndash; As the last few months continue to heavily challenge our belief systems and ideals, I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying a lot harder to consolidate my own principles, and what liberalism means for me. Immigration is being talked about a lot these days, and this article raises pertinent questions about the way we argue for it. In summary, we need to do a much better job at constructing more solid (including moral) arguments for immigration, rather than just relying on the economic ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>January 2017</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 22:27:53 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2017-01/</guid>
      <description>There are some old posts here, just because I&amp;rsquo;m still catching up with the backlog from the last 4-5 months.
Articles  My President was Black [The Atlantic] &amp;ndash; A really long (in six parts) and powerful article by Ta-Nehisi Coates on the rise and political career of Barack Obama. It talks about Obama&amp;rsquo;s childhood in Hawaii, the influences that shaped his outlook and policies, and the recent election &amp;ndash; all viewed from the lens of race and history as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>December 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 13:12:53 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-12/</guid>
      <description>There are some old posts here, just because I&amp;rsquo;m still catching up with the backlog from the last 4-5 months.
Articles  Five Trends Shaping India’s Voting Landscape [Carnegie Endowment] &amp;ndash; Interesting analysis of voting trends and factors affecting elections in India. It touches upon some numbers illustrating patterns around voter turnout, effect of state elections, translation of votes to seats, etc. This was written before the 2014 election though, so some of the analysis might have to be changed as a result.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>August-November 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 13:40:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-11/</guid>
      <description>Given all the travel and being busy over August to November, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really get much time to write or update the monthly log. I&amp;rsquo;m finally able to put something together at the end of November, collecting everything for the last four months in one place. These months have not only been eventful personally, but also politically. The fallout of the election of Donald Trump has affected me a lot, and forced me to read a lot more than I usually do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>July 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-07/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 13:40:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-07/</guid>
      <description>Articles  The Day I Got My Green Card [The Wall Street Journal] &amp;ndash; Amidst general gloom and doom, a rare positive story about immigration. Several people (immigrants and citizens) regularly face struggles here, when it comes to issues of inclusion and acceptance in an increasingly polarized world. If you read this though, you&amp;rsquo;ll feel that a lot of luck was still involved in the outcome being positive, and it&amp;rsquo;s hard to ignore the immense privilege the author has.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>June 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-06/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 13:40:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-06/</guid>
      <description>Articles  Here Is The Powerful Letter The Stanford Victim Read Aloud To Her Attacker [BuzzFeed] &amp;ndash; An unconscious woman was raped by a 20 year old Stanford student behind a dumpster, and he was convicted but only got jail time of 6 months as punishment. This article is powerful, and has been evoking a lot of outrage over the awful treatment that rape victims are regularly subjected to, and the leniancy of the sentence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>May 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 13:40:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-05/</guid>
      <description>Articles  Implementers, Solvers, and Finders [rkoutnik.com] &amp;ndash; This article describes three types of roles software engineers can fulfill in a company. Implementers implement solutions handed to them, solvers solve problems handed to them, finders discover those problems. It points out how most engineers only become finders when they choose the management ladder, and how there might still be hope for those who don&amp;rsquo;t want to.
 Why people pay to read The New York Times [Medium] &amp;ndash; This is a brilliant point of view, and one that fully aligns with how I think of journalism in the digital age.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>April 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-04/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2016 13:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/2016-04/</guid>
      <description>Articles  Beware Trivial Inconveniences [LessWrong] &amp;ndash; This is a nice post about how The Great Firewall of China works by making it a little inconvenient and time-consuming to view subversive sites, thereby discouraging casual exploration. Even though it&amp;rsquo;s easy to bypass it with little technical knowledge or instructions, most people don&amp;rsquo;t do it. There are many more situations where it&amp;rsquo;s easy to discourage people from doing certain things simply by making them slightly inconvenient.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a Monthly Log</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/creating-monthly-log/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 15:27:06 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/monthly-log/creating-monthly-log/</guid>
      <description>Note: This is a backdated post. It was actually published in August, but has been dated appropriately to preserve order of posts. It is a follow-up from my previous attempt to create a weekly log, which turned out to be too much of a commitment.
I recently got a cool idea from Constantin&amp;rsquo;s blog. On a more or less monthly basis, he writes about the books, podcasts, and other stuff he reads.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>