<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Travel on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/tags/travel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Travel on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/tags/travel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On Being a Tourist in India</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently got back to California after spending four full weeks in India. My
previous trip was two years ago, at the end
of 2014. Until moving to the US in 2012, I&amp;rsquo;d only ever lived in India.
Immediately after moving, life in California seemed very attractive, especially by
virtue of the things India could not offer (primarily better facilities,
a more peaceful lifestyle, and opportunities for individual growth). Whenever I visited
India after that, I&amp;rsquo;d often complain about the lack of infrastructure, pollution,
poor traffic, general disorder, and a host of other problems that might
affect any developing country. Typical NRI behavior, I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trip was so different though! It was my first proper
long vacation in over four years, although that doesn&amp;rsquo;t explain everything. Over the last
two years, my life in the US hasn&amp;rsquo;t exactly been a smooth ride, and I&amp;rsquo;ve felt
increasing loneliness, conflated with other personal struggles, including those
with healthcare and bureaucracy. All of that has surely dulled the sheen that
California once held for me. It&amp;rsquo;s not a radical idea that each place has its
problems, but to truly feel and internalize it, and move past the
first world fetishism that many in India grow up with is quite
empowering. I&amp;rsquo;ve also been extremely fortunate in the last 2-3 years to
have traveled to multiple places and made friends with people
from diverse backgrounds.
As a result, I find that I&amp;rsquo;m quite willing to look past trivial (and
sometimes even big) inconveniences and focus on the positives whenever I travel
to a new place. Once again, none of this is very unique, and seasoned travelers
are often quite patient people (I&amp;rsquo;m neither).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I felt compelled to write about this is that adopting a different attitude
made my recent India experience extremely positive. On an absolute level, the India
I went to did not feel remarkably different. Some infrastructure had improved for
sure, but a lot still felt the same. Traffic was noticeably worse, air quality poor,
and the streets dirty. These aren&amp;rsquo;t new problems, as any Indian will tell you, and
they&amp;rsquo;ve annoyed me a lot in the past. This time though, I had decided to travel like
I&amp;rsquo;d travel to any other country &amp;ndash; as a tourist. This might feel like a small thing,
but it was an epiphany. I found it easier to ignore a lot of the negative
aspects, and focus on the good things &amp;ndash; and India does have a lot of good things
to offer. In the past, I&amp;rsquo;d get tired of being in India after about three
weeks and want to return, but this time I did not quite feel like coming back. Of
course, going to India is different from visiting any other country, since I&amp;rsquo;ve
grown up there, and it remains one of the likely countries I could move to in the
future. Still, this new attitude was helpful with realizing what really mattered
and what was tolerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to add the disclaimer that all of this says nothing about
actually living in India&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Additionally, this is not a good attitude to adopt
if one is living in a place, since it can very easily breed apathy. Still, as I
continue to evaluate whether or not I want to move to India in the near future,
this helped me think more clearly and filter out the unimportant considerations.
Without that, I&amp;rsquo;m predisposed to hyperbolizing annoyances and never creating a
balanced picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;I often complain that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what it&amp;rsquo;s like to live as an independent adult in India, since I left right after college.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference Travel in 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 03:32:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been fortunate to have traveled extensively during the Fall of 2016.
A good chunk of that travel was because of work. Back in September, I visited London
and St. Louis (Missouri), and attended three different conferences. Later in October,
I flew back to Europe, this time to Berlin to attend my fourth conference in two months&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
This post focuses on the conferences. I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about the sightseeing I did
in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;containercamp:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;ContainerCamp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://container.camp/uk/2016&#34;&gt;ContainerCamp&lt;/a&gt; was a one day conference in London, focusing
on topics in software container technology, with 12 talks by people in different
areas. I gave a talk on the project I&amp;rsquo;m currently working on,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.github.com/docker/swarmkit&#34;&gt;Docker SwarmKit&lt;/a&gt;,
the open-source container orchestration framework, which was also my
first conference talk ever! That I would be delivering this talk was confirmed
rather late, which gave me little time to prepare and get a UK visa, but things
somehow worked out (my visa arrived the morning I was scheduled to leave), and I
made it to London &amp;ndash; my second visit to the city after last year&amp;rsquo;s UK trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference itself was held at Picturehouse Central, a movie theater in
Piccadilly Circus, which I thought was a very unique venue for a conference.
Talks were projected on to a huge movie screen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;From the source: how &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/docker&#34;&gt;@docker&lt;/a&gt; sees orchestration and tolerating failure in orchestration &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nishanttotla&#34;&gt;@nishanttotla&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/containercamp&#34;&gt;@containercamp&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Ju7OH8qeCB&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Ju7OH8qeCB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alex Ellis (@alexellisuk) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alexellisuk/status/774194023208738816&#34;&gt;September 9, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I did a decent job for a first talk, which also included a live demo and
a shoutout by Mark Shuttleworth! The talk video is
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SLHMkVQnJOs&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, in case you&amp;rsquo;re interested.
Among other talks, I particularly enjoyed the following ones&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Utf-A4rODH8&#34;&gt;Building a container from scratch in Go&lt;/a&gt; by Liz Rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0z3yusiCOCk&#34;&gt;Why we need a different container purely for apps&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All talks, including the ones above are on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCvksXSnLqIVM_uFB7xyrsSg&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After ContainerCamp, I had roughly four days to explore London. From there, I flew
directly to St. Louis, for the next couple of conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;papers-we-love-conference-pwlconf:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;Papers We Love Conference (PWLConf)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://paperswelove.org/&#34;&gt;Papers We Love&lt;/a&gt; is a series of meetups in different cities
around the world, where people come together to discuss research papers they love
from different fields. Given its popularity, the organizers decided to set up the
first PWL conference, which was co-located with Strange Loop in St. Louis.
PWLConf was actually the only conference I was meant to attend, until some
fortuitous events allowed me to attend Strange Loop as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the talks, particularly because they were quite academic in
nature, and I&amp;rsquo;ve missed academic talks since leaving grad school. There were some
I particularly enjoyed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gxf5glthqrk&amp;amp;index=1&amp;amp;list=PLGRqfvsPiRShwIXMA5P3WR_9LgBOAdvw4&#34;&gt;Randomized Gossip Methods&lt;/a&gt; by Dahlia Malkhi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aR_UOSGEizE&amp;amp;list=PLGRqfvsPiRShwIXMA5P3WR_9LgBOAdvw4&amp;amp;index=5&#34;&gt;Design Philosophy in Networked Systems&lt;/a&gt; by Justine Sherry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, all videos are on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLGRqfvsPiRShwIXMA5P3WR_9LgBOAdvw4&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;strange-loop:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;Strange Loop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My attendance at Strange Loop was fortunate. Strange Loop is an annual software
conference held in St. Louis, covering really intriguing and eclectic topics
related to software, mathematics, or their applications to other areas. Other
industry conferences that I&amp;rsquo;ve been to have had extremely specific focus, including
a lot of vendors advertising their products. Strange Loop was nothing like that, and
all talks I attended could basically be put under one umbrella &amp;ndash;
&amp;ldquo;the joy of Computer Science&amp;rdquo;. I also got to meet and talk to some people whom
I&amp;rsquo;d only followed on Twitter before. Since there were too many parallel tracks,
I couldn&amp;rsquo;t attend all interesting talks, but out of the ones I did, some really
stood out&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C4rT0lgJr6U&#34;&gt;Government Hacking and Human Rights: The Why and the How&lt;/a&gt; by Amie Stepanovich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fNe1i7nVbXI&#34;&gt;Humanities x Technology&lt;/a&gt; by Ashley Nelson-Hornstein&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HfD9IMZ9rKY&#34;&gt;Systems programming as a swiss army knife&lt;/a&gt; by Julia Evans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, all talk videos are now online on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C4rT0lgJr6U&amp;amp;list=PLcGKfGEEONaDvuLDFFKRfzbsaBuVVXdYa&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;, and worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;docker-distributed-systems-summit:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;Docker Distributed Systems Summit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small invitation-only event, the summit was a great way to meet people
directly engaged in the Docker community. A part of the attraction was also the
chance to visit Berlin for the first time. Once again, late confirmations led to
rushed planning, and some good fortune allowed me to get a visa in time. My job was
only to attend the talks, engage with people, and lead some discussions. I thought
this was a great format for two reasons &amp;ndash; I got to learn more about Docker&amp;rsquo;s
other products myself, and the small size of the conference enabled many
personal interactions that allowed for deeper conversations.
The &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.docker.com/2016/10/docker-distributed-system-summit-videos-podcast-episodes/&#34;&gt;official blog post&lt;/a&gt; contains links to
the talk videos, slides, and other information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-conference-travel-in-general:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;On Conference Travel in General&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, these were rewarding trips, albeit tiring. Being away from home for all
these days sounds great in principle, but as I found out, travel is rather
disruptive when it&amp;rsquo;s not purely for vacation. Still, I&amp;rsquo;m incredibly lucky to
have had all these opportunities. In fact, this was one of the primary reasons I
joined Docker. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to doing more of this in 2017, but
probably with a little more focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;I also attended a fifth conference this year, back in June &amp;ndash; DockerCon 2016. This was my first DockerCon, and a pretty interesting affair. For one, it gave me significant motivation to work hard preceding the event, and the project I was working on was at the center of major announcements. I also ended up staying for the week in Seattle, so that was great as well. I decided not to write much about DockerCon in this post because I barely attended any talks (booth duty!), and enough has already been written by others about it.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>