<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Travel on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/tags/travel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Travel on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 14:10:49 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/tags/travel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>First Total Solar Eclipse (August 2017)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/experiences/first-total-solar-eclipse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 14:10:49 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/experiences/first-total-solar-eclipse/</guid>
      <description>Was the hype worth it? YES! A hundred times YES! Nothing could really have prepared me for how spectacular and overwhelming it would be to witness a total solar eclipse for the first time. It was beautiful, strange, and emotionally evocative all at the same time.
Having made plans and reservations just about in time for the trip to Oregon, I was naturally looking forward to the event, as were millions of others who traveled far to see totality across the United States.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Portland (July 2017)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/experiences/portland-july-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 17:36:24 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/experiences/portland-july-2017/</guid>
      <description>July 14 &amp;ndash; 16, 2017  3 days  I was in Portland this weekend for a friend&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;bachelorette party&amp;rdquo;. Quotes because this wasn&amp;rsquo;t a traditional bachelorette party at all (ask me why). We spent three days in the city, mostly exploring the food scene and urban landscape. This was my second trip to Portland, and this time I could strongly feel the laid-back vibe the city has. People really love their lunches and dinners and leisurely coffees and local markets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Being a Tourist in India</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</guid>
      <description>I recently got back to California after spending four full weeks in India. My previous trip was two years ago, at the end of 2014. Until moving to the US in 2012, I&amp;rsquo;d only ever lived in India. Immediately after moving, life in California seemed very attractive, especially by virtue of the things India could not offer (primarily better facilities, a more peaceful lifestyle, and opportunities for individual growth). Whenever I visited India after that, I&amp;rsquo;d often complain about the lack of infrastructure, pollution, poor traffic, general disorder, and a host of other problems that might affect any developing country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maui (November 2016)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/experiences/maui-november-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 13:46:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/experiences/maui-november-2016/</guid>
      <description>November 24 &amp;ndash; 28, 2016  4 days  I visited Maui with V during the Thanksgiving break in 2016. It was a late booking and most tickets to Hawaii were rather expensive, but then we decided to not return on the Sunday after Thanksgiving (which is what most people do) and it suddenly made the tickets a few hundred dollars cheaper and the trip possible.
In total, we spent four days on the island, which was a good amount of time to cover a lot of ground.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference Travel in 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 03:32:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been fortunate to have traveled extensively during the Fall of 2016. A good chunk of that travel was because of work. Back in September, I visited London and St. Louis (Missouri), and attended three different conferences. Later in October, I flew back to Europe, this time to Berlin to attend my fourth conference in two months1. This post focuses on the conferences. I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about the sightseeing I did in future posts.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>