<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thoughts on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/tags/thoughts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thoughts on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:44:06 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/tags/thoughts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Deciding to Stop</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/deciding-to-stop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:44:06 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/deciding-to-stop/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a slow reader with a short attention span, but I&amp;rsquo;d like to read a lot more books than I currently manage. So I&amp;rsquo;m like the armchair analyst who dreams of changing the world &amp;ndash; tons of ambition, but lack of skills (and possibly desire?). A recurrent problem for me has been that I start some books, partly or nearly finish them, have no interest in continuing, but can&amp;rsquo;t start other books until I finish the earlier ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Being a Tourist in India</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</guid>
      <description>I recently got back to California after spending four full weeks in India. My previous trip was two years ago, at the end of 2014. Until moving to the US in 2012, I&amp;rsquo;d only ever lived in India. Immediately after moving, life in California seemed very attractive, especially by virtue of the things India could not offer (primarily better facilities, a more peaceful lifestyle, and opportunities for individual growth). Whenever I visited India after that, I&amp;rsquo;d often complain about the lack of infrastructure, pollution, poor traffic, general disorder, and a host of other problems that might affect any developing country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about Empathy</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/learning-about-empathy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2015 15:46:09 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/learning-about-empathy/</guid>
      <description>Empathy is such a simple concept to understand, yet so difficult to practice! Kids are taught about it. The word itself is lazily thrown around, assuming everyone knows how to empathize, that it’s something we’re naturally good at. Well we’re not! Even if we care enough to look outside our own busy lives to try and want to empathize with someone, it’s too easy to fall into the trap of making judgments or believing we know everything about another person’s situation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>