<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Technical on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.github.io/categories/technical/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Technical on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2016 13:35:12 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.github.io/categories/technical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Code Inside a VM</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.github.io/articles/building-code-inside-vm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2016 13:35:12 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.github.io/articles/building-code-inside-vm/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This post is based on the workflow I&amp;rsquo;ve been employing during my day to day work at Docker. When I first started, I chose to get a 13&amp;rsquo; Macbook Pro, which is a pretty solid machine to own. But a lot of the compiling and testing I needed to do needed a Linux distribution, so I had two options &amp;ndash; install Linux or use a Virtual Machine (VM). Installing VirtualBox and using a simple Ubuntu VM is a fairly straightforward solution, but there were two problems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I really wanted to continue writing code on OSX (personal preference)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think VirtualBox is very stable, and it would be a disaster to lose my work if something bad happened&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution was the continue writing code on the Mac, but build it inside the VM &amp;ndash; a win-win. But how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first solution I came up with involved using &lt;code&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt;, a very popular file synchronization tool for Unix-like systems. I set up one folder called &lt;code&gt;work&lt;/code&gt; on my Mac, and one on the VM, and used &lt;code&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt; to copy files from one to the other. Any changes were automatically detected using &lt;code&gt;inotify&lt;/code&gt; (or similar tools), and triggered a sync. I won&amp;rsquo;t describe that in detail because it&amp;rsquo;s not only fragile and prone to corruption&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but also too hard to set up&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. All this was before I discovered that I could mount folders (duh) and create a relatively stable solution. If this is something you&amp;rsquo;re interested in too, read on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;setting-up-a-mounted-folder-on-a-virtualbox-vm:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900&#34;&gt;Setting up a mounted folder on a VirtualBox VM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s relatively easy to create a VM using your Linux distribution of choice. I use Ubuntu 14.04 right now, but the setup should work in most cases. Once you&amp;rsquo;ve installed the VM, make sure you install &lt;code&gt;openssh-server&lt;/code&gt; to be able to SSH into it from the host&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The other requirement is Guest Additions, without which mounting won&amp;rsquo;t work. It&amp;rsquo;s straightforward to install, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://askubuntu.com/questions/22743/how-do-i-install-guest-additions-in-a-virtualbox-vm&#34;&gt;several articles&lt;/a&gt; online explain how to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get install openssh-server
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to create a mounted folder. Right click on the VM and go to Settings, under Shared Folders. There, mount your folder of choice as a Machine Folder, and give it a name. I mount the &lt;code&gt;work&lt;/code&gt; folder in my home directory, and call the mount &lt;code&gt;workmac&lt;/code&gt; (any name is fine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.github.io/images/vbox-shared-folder.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, SSH into the VM, then create a folder, which will be the mount point for the host folder. In my case, it&amp;rsquo;s in the home directory  and called &lt;code&gt;work-vm&lt;/code&gt;. The shared folder is mounted with 770 permissions with &lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; user and &lt;code&gt;vboxsf&lt;/code&gt; as the group. This is an inconvenience since you (the user) also want to have those permissions. This is done by adding the user to to &lt;code&gt;vboxsf&lt;/code&gt; group as follows&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo usermod -aG vboxsf $(whoami)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, mount the folder&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo mount -t vboxsf -o uid=$UID,gid=$(id -g) workmac work-vm
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change the mount and directory names as appropriate for you. And that&amp;rsquo;s it! Now you should be able to access a mirror of the host folder inside the VM without any of the messy &lt;code&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt; scripts. Note that if you reboot the VM, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to run the mount command again &amp;ndash; a requirement you can surpass by adding the line to you &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;advantages-of-this-setup:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900&#34;&gt;Advantages of this setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an extremely simple setup that has worked for me (and others I helped) each time. While for me, the reasons to do this centered around personal preference, I feel there are at least two good reasons to do it anyway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The environment inside a VM can be precisely controlled, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to depend on, or mess with the host (Mac). It&amp;rsquo;s really easy to upgrade, or redo if things are failing. This also makes it easy to quickly experiment with different build environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The setup is easier to reproduce and share with someone else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, my use cases haven&amp;rsquo;t presented any disadvantages, though I suspect there could be situations where this couldn&amp;rsquo;t work. Feel free to share your experiences in the comments. The next step I&amp;rsquo;d like to explore would be to create a similar dev environment &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ybrikman.com/writing/2015/05/19/docker-osx-dev/&#34;&gt;using Docker&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:1&#34;&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t want to know how git config files can go crazy.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:2&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m surprised I even had to patience to go through all the steps.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:3&#34;&gt;To save some trouble if your Mac reboots, you might want to set a static IP address for the VM. How to do that is beyond the scope of this post.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:0845bcb07a42949b6056d62ad8760900:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Systems Resources</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.github.io/articles/distributed-systems-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 16:25:04 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.github.io/articles/distributed-systems-resources/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I started working on distributed systems in early 2016. Given that I had little to no background, I started trying to cover as much as possible from the literature out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this (dynamically updated) post, I intend to keep track of all good resources I come across in this quest. This includes not only research papers and books, but also good blogs, people to follow and discussions/meetups that could be helpful. It’s overwhelming to begin with, but everything that’s worthwhile has to start somewhere! This is obviously not a complete list, but hopefully the union of content within all entries on the list will be complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;blogs:dc4816fae14320f2f4f74f4d0f551d32&#34;&gt;Blogs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://the-paper-trail.org/&#34;&gt;The Paper Trail&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HenryR&#34;&gt;Henry Robinson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;books:dc4816fae14320f2f4f74f4d0f551d32&#34;&gt;Books&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;research-papers:dc4816fae14320f2f4f74f4d0f551d32&#34;&gt;Research Papers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;people:dc4816fae14320f2f4f74f4d0f551d32&#34;&gt;People&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HenryR&#34;&gt;Henry Robinson&lt;/a&gt;, Cloudera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/pbailis&#34;&gt;Peter Bailis&lt;/a&gt;, Stanford University&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;meetups:dc4816fae14320f2f4f74f4d0f551d32&#34;&gt;Meetups&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Papers We Love [&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/papers_we_love&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/papers-we-love-too/&#34;&gt;San Francisco&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;want-to-contribute-to-this-post:dc4816fae14320f2f4f74f4d0f551d32&#34;&gt;Want to Contribute to this post?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to make suggestions or &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nishanttotla/hugo-blog-skeleton/blob/master/content/articles/distributed-systems-resources.md&#34;&gt;submit a PR&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>