<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on nRT</title>
    <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 13:37:44 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nishanttotla.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s Talk About Aziz Ansari</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/lets-talk-about-aziz-ansari/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 13:37:44 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/lets-talk-about-aziz-ansari/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: This is a controversial topic, and I have tried to be as sensitive as possible. The reason for writing about it is to collect my own thoughts and hopefully have a (civil) discussion in the comments section. Hateful comments and ad hominem attacks are not appreciated and will be removed. Also note that this post has been written keeping mostly a cis-heterosexual perspective in mind. This is necessarily limited, but helps with specificity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2017 Year in Review</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/2017-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 18:43:39 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/2017-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>I started posting these yearly review posts two years ago, and each time I&amp;rsquo;ve failed to finish before the New Year&amp;rsquo;s Eve. This time is no different. Regardless, I think the effort is worthwhile and rewarding, especially for a cynical person like me who often has a hard time appreciating the good things in life. Unlike the doom and gloom of 2015 and 2016, my hindsight perception of 2017 is much more positive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving To San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/moving-to-san-francisco/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 14:27:43 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/moving-to-san-francisco/</guid>
      <description>Today, I officially completed my move to San Francisco, giving up keys to my beloved apartment in Berkeley. When I moved to Berkeley on my birthday in 2012, I&amp;rsquo;d started out as an excited young person looking forward to great experiences and a successful time in the PhD program. Things turned out to be quite different in reality, but Berkeley has had a significant impact on my preferences, identity, and world view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Acting Class</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/about-acting-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 22:56:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/about-acting-class/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to try acting for a really long time, since college in fact. Back then I never managed to get started and it just became one of those bucket list items. While I was preparing for my recent conference talk (April), my co-worker (and co-speaker) Drew suggested that an acting class might really help with public speaking. I love speaking, so when a few days later my friend Vijay asked me if I&amp;rsquo;d like to try something new, I knew what it would be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Red Hairing</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/red-hairing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 13:32:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/red-hairing/</guid>
      <description>A little over two weeks ago, I got my hair colored red. Not completely, just highlights, but very prominent highlights. Nothing unique because millions of people do this sort of thing, so the only reason I&amp;rsquo;m writing about it is because I can. Kind of the same reason why I colored my hair. It had been on my mind since last year, but the stars started aligning a month ago when a friend referred me to a place in Oakland.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Being a Tourist in India</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</guid>
      <description>I recently got back to California after spending four full weeks in India. My previous trip was two years ago, at the end of 2014. Until moving to the US in 2012, I&amp;rsquo;d only ever lived in India. Immediately after moving, life in California seemed very attractive, especially by virtue of the things India could not offer (primarily better facilities, a more peaceful lifestyle, and opportunities for individual growth). Whenever I visited India after that, I&amp;rsquo;d often complain about the lack of infrastructure, pollution, poor traffic, general disorder, and a host of other problems that might affect any developing country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was Asked to Give a Motivational Speech</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/i-was-asked-motivational-speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 15:29:03 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/i-was-asked-motivational-speech/</guid>
      <description>On December 18, 2016, my parents celebrated the 25th anniversary of Totla Hospital. It has been a long and impressive journey for them, starting out from literally nothing when they arrived in Aurangabad, to having built a very successful and highly respected hospital in the city. To celebrate this anniversary, they had organized a grand function, inviting a lot of former patients, friends, family, and others out of the gigantic community they&amp;rsquo;ve built during this time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016 Year in Review</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/2016-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 01:20:02 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/2016-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>Precisely a year ago, I went to Hawaii to try and regain some sanity after what was a terrible 2015. It offered little apart from endless pain, suffering, depression, lack of community, and an uncontrollable feeling of helplessness. So much so that the second half of the Hawaii trip was full of panic attacks and attempts to cut the trip short. I was due to start a new job upon returning, and my Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis was still pending.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference Travel in 2016</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 03:32:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been fortunate to have traveled extensively during the Fall of 2016. A good chunk of that travel was because of work. Back in September, I visited London and St. Louis (Missouri), and attended three different conferences. Later in October, I flew back to Europe, this time to Berlin to attend my fourth conference in two months1. This post focuses on the conferences. I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about the sightseeing I did in future posts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Moved to a Static Website</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/why-i-moved-to-static-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2016 00:52:35 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/why-i-moved-to-static-website/</guid>
      <description>As some of you know, I&amp;rsquo;ve maintained a personal website/blog for a few years now. I&amp;rsquo;ve always liked writing, because I consider it to be a natural extension of thinking. While I&amp;rsquo;m not great with words, I do love keeping track of things I learn &amp;ndash; that&amp;rsquo;s really what a blog means to me. Over time, I went through several iterations to find the right platform. Things always revolved around WordPress, and regardless of what I tried, the experience of writing never got much better.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2015 Year in Review</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/2015-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2015 19:16:02 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/2015-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>Are you already sick of people writing their yearly review posts? I bet! I’m going to add more more to the pile though, but mostly as a milestone for myself, and for others who might find value in reading it.
To start, I have to say that 2015 has been the most unusual year of my life. I’ve experienced many different things and changed a lot as a person. This is also the year when I finally decided and went through the process of quitting grad school to venture out into the real world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Off to Hawaii - a Good End to a Miserable Year</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/off-to-hawaii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2015 15:39:26 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/off-to-hawaii/</guid>
      <description>2015 will go down as the worst year in my life so far, no doubts about that! It has been a year when I suffered a lot, learned some hard lessons, and had to face several uncomfortable truths about myself. I’ve battled terrifying depression and felt things I wasn’t ready to handle. As painful as that has been, I’m glad to be ending the year right – by taking a break from everything, and heading to Hawaii on my first real solo trip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>India&#39;s Undercurrent of Propaganda</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/india-undercurrent-propaganda/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 16:01:47 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/india-undercurrent-propaganda/</guid>
      <description>India is currently at an interesting political standpoint. We finally have a single party forming the central government without needing support from other parties (last this happened was in 1984). The average Indian person seems to be much more aware and concerned about the political situation, and invested in the country’s future, especially young people. All of this is a major shift compared to a few years ago. There have been several contributing factors – dissatisfaction with the UPA govt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about Empathy</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/learning-about-empathy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2015 15:46:09 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/learning-about-empathy/</guid>
      <description>Empathy is such a simple concept to understand, yet so difficult to practice! Kids are taught about it. The word itself is lazily thrown around, assuming everyone knows how to empathize, that it’s something we’re naturally good at. Well we’re not! Even if we care enough to look outside our own busy lives to try and want to empathize with someone, it’s too easy to fall into the trap of making judgments or believing we know everything about another person’s situation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supporting a Football Club</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/supporting-a-football-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2015 19:10:35 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/supporting-a-football-club/</guid>
      <description>Sunday, March 28, 2004 : Arsenal vs Manchester United at Highbury, London was the first live football game I watched (on TV, of course). I’d only ever followed cricket before that and played some football, but this was unlike anything I knew in sport. It was fast and full of action. These players were really passionate and the tension was palpable. Then on 50 minutes, Arsenal’s number 14 scored from a brilliant long range effort, a stunning goal by any standard!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rediscovering Podcasts</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/rediscovering-podcasts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 15:50:52 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/rediscovering-podcasts/</guid>
      <description>This summer, I was interviewing at several companies. Among other things, it involved a lot of travel, and there was little I could do while traveling. If I was driving, I’d mostly listen to my usual Spotify playlists, although they got boring pretty soon. Taking the train allowed me to read in addition, but I’d usually get distracted or fall asleep since the interviews were exhausting. Soon enough, all this travel time started feeling wasteful, but I wanted to reclaim it, so I constantly tried to find ways to engage in something productive, or learn something new.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eight Lessons I Learned in College</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/x-lessons-i-learned-in-college/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2012 19:26:42 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/x-lessons-i-learned-in-college/</guid>
      <description>I’m writing a post after around five months! Whoa! What a ride the last semester has been! I’ve now graduated (provided they give me my degree) from one of the best colleges in India, with new hopes and dreams, some knowledge, passion and a lot of friends. The past few months have been a blur, and I’ve done loads of new things. Most importantly, I’ve had the opportunity to think about and look at all that I accomplished (or failed to accomplish) during college, I’ve thought about where my motivations lie, what I want from life and ultimately how I’m going to achieve that.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>