<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Non Technical on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/series/non-technical/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Non Technical on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/series/non-technical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On Being a Tourist in India</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently got back to California after spending four full weeks in India. My
previous trip was two years ago, at the end
of 2014. Until moving to the US in 2012, I&amp;rsquo;d only ever lived in India.
Immediately after moving, life in California seemed very attractive, especially by
virtue of the things India could not offer (primarily better facilities,
a more peaceful lifestyle, and opportunities for individual growth). Whenever I visited
India after that, I&amp;rsquo;d often complain about the lack of infrastructure, pollution,
poor traffic, general disorder, and a host of other problems that might
affect any developing country. Typical NRI behavior, I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trip was so different though! Although it was my first proper
long vacation in over four years, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t explain everything. Over the last
two years, my life in the US hasn&amp;rsquo;t exactly been a smooth ride, and I&amp;rsquo;ve felt
increasing loneliness, conflated with other personal struggles, including those
with healthcare and bureaucracy. All of that has surely dulled the sheen that
California once held for me. It&amp;rsquo;s not a radical idea that each place has its
problems, but to truly feel and internalize it, and move past the
first world fetishism that many in India grow up with is quite
empowering. I&amp;rsquo;ve also been extremely fortunate in the last 2-3 years to
have traveled to multiple places and made friends with people
from diverse backgrounds.
As a result, I find that I&amp;rsquo;m quite willing to look past trivial (and
sometimes even big) inconveniences and focus on the positives whenever I travel
to a new place. Once again, none of this is very unique, and seasoned travelers
are often quite patient people (I&amp;rsquo;m not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I felt compelled to write about this is that adopting a different attitude
made my recent India experience extremely positive. On an absolute level, the India
I went to did not feel remarkably different. Some infrastructure had improved for
sure, but a lot still felt the same. Traffic was noticeably worse, air quality poor,
and the streets dirty. These aren&amp;rsquo;t new problems, as any Indian will tell you, and
they&amp;rsquo;ve annoyed me a lot in the past. This time though, I had decided to travel like
I&amp;rsquo;d travel to any other country &amp;ndash; as a tourist. This might feel like a small thing,
but it was an epiphany. I found it easier to ignore a lot of the negative
aspects, and focus on the good things &amp;ndash; and India does have a lot of good things
to offer. In the past, I&amp;rsquo;d get tired of being in India after about three
weeks and want to return, but this time I did not quite feel like coming back. Of
course, going to India is different from visiting any other country, since I&amp;rsquo;ve
grown up there, and it remains one of the likely countries I could move to in the
future. Still, this new attitude was helpful with realizing what really mattered
and what was tolerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to add the disclaimer that all of this says nothing about
actually living in India&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Additionally, this is not a good attitude to adopt
if one is living in a place, since it can very easily breed apathy. Still, as I
continue to evaluate whether or not I want to move to India in the near future,
this helped me think more clearly and filter out the unimportant considerations.
Without that, I&amp;rsquo;m predisposed to hyperbolizing annoyances and never creating a
balanced picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;I often complain that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what it&amp;rsquo;s like to live as an independent adult in India, since I left right after college.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9e61b69be6f1f06be70c82f0bcc41327:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was Asked to Give a Motivational Speech</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/i-was-asked-motivational-speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 15:29:03 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/i-was-asked-motivational-speech/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;On December 18, 2016, my parents celebrated the 25th anniversary of Totla Hospital.
It has been a long and impressive journey for them, starting out
from literally nothing when they arrived in Aurangabad, to having built a very
successful and highly respected hospital in the city. To celebrate this anniversary,
they had organized a grand function, inviting a lot of former patients, friends, family,
and others out of the gigantic community they&amp;rsquo;ve built during this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks prior, I was asked to speak at the event. Several people in the city know
me due to some good exam results from 2008 that got a lot of publicity,
though I have always found it hard to deal with the attention.
As a result, I&amp;rsquo;ve often overcompensated and vehemently opposed anything that would
draw similar attention to me. Besides, I always maintained that good exam results
are down to a lot of luck, and mine were too long in the past anyway. So while
my first reaction was to protest the fact that I even had to speak at the event,
I later decided that this was a rare opportunity to engage with the people of
Aurangabad (the event was expected to have 1500 attendees!) and put forward my point
of view. It took me some days to come up with the key points, and roughly a day to write
them down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expectation was that I&amp;rsquo;d say something motivational, given all my &amp;ldquo;success&amp;rdquo;.
Instead, I decided to talk about things I personally feel strongly about, including
questioning what success means. Here&amp;rsquo;s my original draft of the speech. The actual
transcript differs slightly because I improvised on stage, but it sticks to the outline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speech-outline:c926fc76b4b01d7c5aa3351fb0bb8c80&#34;&gt;Speech Outline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good evening everyone, my name is Nishant Totla, and I&amp;rsquo;m the son of Dr Rajgopal Totla
and Santosh Totla. Today I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about how I think about success, looking
at the past. I wanted to say something motivational, but I think it is far
more important to talk about what success means and the factors
behind it, before trying to motivate others towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll only talk for 10 minutes, but my talk is meant for young
students aspiring to be successful, and their parents who want to support them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does success look like? We&amp;rsquo;ve all seen what it looks like in the newspapers.
You know, people see all these flashy results, or news about how some kid
out of college is getting a huge salary, and wonder if they&amp;rsquo;re being left behind.
Well let me tell you this &amp;ndash; news like this is meant to deceive, not inform.
It hides all the other factors that are involved in becoming a successful person.
I have done well enough in the last few years that many people consider me
successful. But from my point of view, looking back, here is what I think
contributes to success. There are, broadly speaking, four things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privilege&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(and to some extent, talent)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[I define what each of them mean]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that the only thing in your hands, is hard work. Successful people
often downplay the role of other things in their success, and they are often
as important as hard work. Don&amp;rsquo;t let any successful person tell you they were not lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll give you an example. When my parents arrived in Aurangabad a long time
ago to start Totla Hospital, they came with no money and support,
just a strong desire to start practicing and serve people. They did not have
the privilege of a comfortable familiar place, or financial backing. But
they worked really hard, and were fortunate to be supported by some amazing people
in this journey, which makes them as successful as they are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own case, I had everything one can ask for &amp;ndash; I worked very hard, I
was lucky in many places (like not falling sick at the wrong times), and
I was very privileged because my parents supported me at every step, despite
all the inconvenience it caused them. I could not have achieved anything without
support from them, the hospital staff, family, and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went to college, I met some people who had nothing like what I had.
There were people from really poor families, or very unfortunate circumstances,
who worked really hard to get there, and did well in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born in Aurangabad, and grew up here for a good part of my life.
I&amp;rsquo;ve heard a lot of times that our region lacks infrastructure and awareness
for our youth to be successful. I agree that we still have a lot of
catching up to do, and it will happen with time. But with the above points,
my message to all of you who hold aspirations to be successful is this &amp;ndash;
remember that situations will never be perfect. You will probably not get
all these things, and the only thing you can do is to be sincere in your efforts
and work hard. The rest is not always in your control. To the parents, my
message is that if your kids fail despite hard work, recognize that many other factors are involved, and don&amp;rsquo;t blame them right away. Their talents
might be elsewhere, or they might have just been unlucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now I will move on to the second part &amp;ndash; what is success?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, I used to believe that doing well in school was success.
Then I believed doing well in competitive examinations, and getting into a good
college was success. Then I thought getting a good job was success. But after all
those things, and some more experience, I want to say that these things are
not as important as we think. Yes they help, and we must work hard towards them,
but they don&amp;rsquo;t define us. Lot of people in good colleges end up
unsuccessful, and many remarkable people in the world did not
go to a very good college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I look at what my parents have achieved, they have no doubt built and
done a lot of great things over the last 25 years. But the most important thing that
I believe makes them successful is their kindness and compassion for their patients.
When so many patients speak highly of them, it is not because they have great
education and degrees. It is because they understand people&amp;rsquo;s pain, empathize with
them, and they are kind. In the long term, it is these qualities that will give you
a lot more success and happiness, than just things on paper. Right now, when I
think about what I want to do in the future, it is always related to how I can
help people &amp;ndash; especially those are are poor, or lack privilege. Look at so many
rich people (such as Bill Gates), who end up living very modest lives and
help others through philanthropy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a society, we need to start telling people that it is not only these
fancy achievements that make a person successful and useful to society. The will
to help people around us, and kindness are extremely underrated qualities that
should be cultivated from a young age. Let us stop narrowly defining what success
means, and instead focus on what we can do to become happy and satisfied with
our lives. I cannot tell you how to achieve that, because you must find it
for yourself. What I can tell you though, is to work hard, and not
get caught up in narrow definitions of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ummmm:c926fc76b4b01d7c5aa3351fb0bb8c80&#34;&gt;Ummmm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, probably sounds like one of those cheesy speeches that doesn&amp;rsquo;t really say anything
actionable (because it is!), but it was my first attempt at putting these ideas out there.
More selfishly, I have started relishing the opportunity to speak publicly, thanks partly
to my job that has given me several chances to present my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/umang.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;I had the outline on my phone!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have become much more
comfortable and confident on stage, and have begun treating each occasion like an
exciting opportunity to be enjoyed, rather than a scary challenge to overcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016 Year in Review</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/2016-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 01:20:02 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/2016-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Precisely a year ago, I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/off-to-hawaii&#34;&gt;Hawaii&lt;/a&gt; to try and
regain some sanity after what was a terrible 2015.
It offered little apart from endless pain, suffering, depression,
lack of community, and an uncontrollable feeling of helplessness.
So much so that the second half of the Hawaii trip was full of
panic attacks and attempts to cut the trip short. I was due to start a new job upon returning, and my Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis was still pending. I had no idea how I was going
to deal after getting back, manage personal relationships, and stop feeling
that life was pointless every other day&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2016 for me was a story in two parts &amp;ndash; pre-September, and post. The first part was
incredibly hard with a few positive blips, while the second was rosy,
with renewed hope going into 2017. I&amp;rsquo;m going to avoid any mention of politics
in this post, even though the events of the year deeply affected me on a personal level.
Although 2016 was painful to live through, it will be memorable. This is a feeling
I had failed to experience for several years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;master-s-thesis:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Master&amp;rsquo;s Thesis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big part of my woes was my Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis, which had dragged out for too long. After
failing to finish it at the end of 2015 and getting on filing fee status&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, expecting
to get done with it by February. But lack of progress for extended periods (in part due
to severe depression), coupled with a full-time job, and spending most of my free time
struggling with the thesis was a recipe for disaster. I failed to finish it by the May
deadline, had to register for the summer session (and pay nearly $2000 for it). Despite
finally managing to make good progress by the end of July and get a draft ready,
my committee refused to sign it, and the EECS department showed an immense lack
of desire to help me out. This left me looking at a $16000 tuition payment for the Fall
semester. I fought the bureaucracy and it was only in mid-November that I managed
to get the thesis submitted, in time to extend my immigration status, without which
I&amp;rsquo;d be forced to leave the country. The details of that
will be the subject of another post, but if there&amp;rsquo;s a lesson to be learned, it is that
&lt;em&gt;the department is not your friend&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/commencement.gif&#34; style=&#34;width:70%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Commencement - Pradeep walked on the same day&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, after over four years of struggle at UC Berkeley, I&amp;rsquo;m finally out of that
depressing environment and looking at better things, with at least a degree to show.
I even got to walk for commencement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;health:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Health&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this front, the year was mostly bad. I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned depression a few times
already, but 2016 was remarkable because I&amp;rsquo;m
finally ending a year on a reasonably good note. If the first half was about
lack of motivation, often to the extent of death ideation, then the second half
presented a renewed faith in my own abilities, along with a future that I at least
want to consider. Thanks to input from my girlfriend and some close friends, I also
got the opportunity to deeply introspect and work on personal flaws that have
always caused me great anxiety. Health issues for someone very close to me
were also a factor in an utterly disappointing time for the first part of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, I continued to work on my chronic physical injuries, with the hope of
one day getting back to endurance running and biking. I have a pretty solid understanding
of shoulder and hip anatomy as a result, and have tried literally every rehab technique
out there. Hopefully 2017 is the year I get a breakthrough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;work:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started working at Docker as a software engineer in early 2016.
I recovered some of the productivity I lost during grad
school, and got several new opportunities and experiences along the way. For one,
I learned a lot about working on open-source projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/github.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;My GitHub profile has never looked greener&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I got to &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016&#34;&gt;travel to multiple conferences&lt;/a&gt;
and give talks. These were among the primary reasons I had joined Docker in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/talk.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;First conference talk, at ContainerCamp 2016, London&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were slow periods too, but the year was overall a positive change on the work front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;travel:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Travel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all problems, 2016 was one of the best years for travel. Traveling was
easier since I had more money, opportunities, and time (post September).
I did make several trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boulder and Rocky Mountain National Park, Colorado (May) for a long weekend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seattle and Olympic National Park, Washington (June) for DockerCon, extended the trip by a few days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crater Lake National Park, Oregon (July) for a random weekend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/colorado.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/craterlake.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;White snow at 12,000ft in Rocky Mountain National Park, and deep blue water at Crater Lake&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;London, UK (September) for ContainerCamp, spent 4 extra days exploring the city&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;St. Louis, Missouri (September) for Strange Loop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bike camping trip to Samuel P Taylor State Park (September)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berlin, Germany (October) for the Docker Distributed Systems Summit, plus 3 extra days to explore the city&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mendocino, California (October) for a relaxing weekend getaway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/london.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/bikecamping.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/berlin.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/mendocino.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;London, start of the bike camping trip in SF, festival of lights at the Berliner Dom, California coastline in Mendocino&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portland, Oregon (November) for a friend&amp;rsquo;s bachelor trip weekend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maui, Hawaii (November) for the Thanksgiving break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tokyo, Japan (December) for vacation, and (finally) a new country for 2016&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;India (December), also for vacation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/portland.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/maui.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:40%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/tokyo.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:80%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Hipster Indian food in Portland, stunning ridges in Maui, street market in Tokyo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, this includes 3 international trips, 4 national parks, and several new
cities. I also spend a lot of time exploring locally in Oakland and San Francisco.
Up until the late May trip to Colorado, the only travel I had done was a weekend
trip to Seattle in March, but I&amp;rsquo;m glad with the way things turned out in the second
half of the year&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-highlights:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Other Highlights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I fulfilled a long standing dream of watching Arsenal play at the Emirates stadium. During my trip to London in September, I managed to get a ticket to the Arsenal vs Southampton game and thoroughly enjoyed it. Interestingly, just the month before, I&amp;rsquo;d watched the team play MLS All-Stars during their US tour but had no idea I&amp;rsquo;d actually be traveling to London soon after!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/2016-year-in-review/emirates.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Arsenal vs Southampton at the Emirates Stadium in September&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wrote a short Docker tutorial for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.creativebloq.com/net-magazine&#34;&gt;Netmag&lt;/a&gt;, a UK magazine. This is the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve done something like this, and I&amp;rsquo;m pretty excited! The issue goes on sale in late January 2017.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some close friends got married (and several others got engaged). Wedding season was a lot of fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After several years of being indifferent, I celebrated my birthday (in difficult circumstances too, following my thesis rejection!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vasuki, Vaishnavi, and I organized a Bollywood costume themed Diwali party at our apartment, the first such party I&amp;rsquo;ve been part of organizing!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My adventure of the year was jumping into the freezing cold water of Crater Lake, after failing to carry swimming shorts but judging that the opportunity was not to be missed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;After some hiking on Wizard Island, I found the courage to jump into the frigid waters of Crater Lake! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/8Z2L1XKchn&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/8Z2L1XKchn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Traveler Boy (@nrt_travel) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nrt_travel/status/754849467581341696&#34;&gt;July 18, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I made the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/why-i-moved-to-static-website&#34;&gt;current version of my website and blog&lt;/a&gt; this year. It was a lot of work, but has been a net positive effort because it encouraged me to write more easily and frequently (hopefully more next year).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;looking-at-2017:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17&#34;&gt;Looking at 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a private list of specific goals to pursue to next year, but the most
important thing I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to is settling down. For
too long now, life has felt like someone else in the driver&amp;rsquo;s seat, and I want to
end that. Hopefully, that will free up some time to devote to things I actually care
about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:1&#34;&gt;The irony here is that I&amp;rsquo;m still pretty privileged and &amp;ldquo;successful&amp;rdquo;, and that only adds up to a lot of guilt. One of my major goals is to get over this chronic depression.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:2&#34;&gt;A special kind of student registration that you can avail when only a thesis is due, and all course requirements are done. The upside is that you&amp;rsquo;re no longer required to pay tuition and can get a job.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:3&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a curious thing how despite being utterly depressed for long periods, my travelogue is pretty elaborate. It was more chance than anything that I managed to cover as much ground as I did, but satisfying that I took the opportunities that came my way. When I tried to reach out to a friend saying I was really sad, he mentioned that&amp;rsquo;s not at all how my Instagram profile looked like. Now you have another example of the pain hidden behind glittery social media profiles.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fb87175bd9d8d1c271c0241c5bfcdf17:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference Travel in 2016</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 03:32:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been fortunate to have traveled extensively during the Fall of 2016.
A good chunk of that travel was because of work. Back in September, I visited London
and St. Louis (Missouri), and attended three different conferences. Later in October,
I flew back to Europe, this time to Berlin to attend my fourth conference in two months&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
This post focuses on the conferences. I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about the sightseeing I did
in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;containercamp:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;ContainerCamp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://container.camp/uk/2016&#34;&gt;ContainerCamp&lt;/a&gt; was a one day conference in London, focusing
on topics in software container technology, with 12 talks by people in different
areas. I gave a talk on the project I&amp;rsquo;m currently working on,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.github.com/docker/swarmkit&#34;&gt;Docker SwarmKit&lt;/a&gt;,
the open-source container orchestration framework, which was also my
first conference talk ever! That I would be delivering this talk was confirmed
rather late, which gave me little time to prepare and get a UK visa, but things
somehow worked out (my visa arrived the morning I was scheduled to leave), and I
made it to London &amp;ndash; my second visit to the city after last year&amp;rsquo;s UK trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference itself was held at Picturehouse Central, a movie theater in
Piccadilly Circus, which I thought was a very unique venue for a conference.
Talks were projected on to a huge movie screen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;From the source: how &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/docker&#34;&gt;@docker&lt;/a&gt; sees orchestration and tolerating failure in orchestration &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nishanttotla&#34;&gt;@nishanttotla&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/containercamp&#34;&gt;@containercamp&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Ju7OH8qeCB&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Ju7OH8qeCB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alex Ellis (@alexellisuk) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alexellisuk/status/774194023208738816&#34;&gt;September 9, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I did a decent job for a first talk, which also included a live demo and
a shoutout by Mark Shuttleworth! The talk video is
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SLHMkVQnJOs&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, in case you&amp;rsquo;re interested.
Among other talks, I particularly enjoyed the following ones&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Utf-A4rODH8&#34;&gt;Building a container from scratch in Go&lt;/a&gt; by Liz Rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0z3yusiCOCk&#34;&gt;Why we need a different container purely for apps&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All talks, including the ones above are on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCvksXSnLqIVM_uFB7xyrsSg&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After ContainerCamp, I had roughly four days to explore London. From there, I flew
directly to St. Louis, for the next couple of conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;papers-we-love-conference-pwlconf:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;Papers We Love Conference (PWLConf)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://paperswelove.org/&#34;&gt;Papers We Love&lt;/a&gt; is a series of meetups in different cities
around the world, where people come together to discuss research papers they love
from different fields. Given its popularity, the organizers decided to set up the
first PWL conference, which was co-located with Strange Loop in St. Louis.
PWLConf was actually the only conference I was meant to attend, until some
fortuitous events allowed me to attend Strange Loop as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the talks, particularly because they were quite academic in
nature, and I&amp;rsquo;ve missed academic talks since leaving grad school. There were some
I particularly enjoyed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gxf5glthqrk&amp;amp;index=1&amp;amp;list=PLGRqfvsPiRShwIXMA5P3WR_9LgBOAdvw4&#34;&gt;Randomized Gossip Methods&lt;/a&gt; by Dahlia Malkhi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aR_UOSGEizE&amp;amp;list=PLGRqfvsPiRShwIXMA5P3WR_9LgBOAdvw4&amp;amp;index=5&#34;&gt;Design Philosophy in Networked Systems&lt;/a&gt; by Justine Sherry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, all videos are on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLGRqfvsPiRShwIXMA5P3WR_9LgBOAdvw4&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;strange-loop:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;Strange Loop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My attendance at Strange Loop was fortunate. Strange Loop is an annual software
conference held in St. Louis, covering really intriguing and eclectic topics
related to software, mathematics, or their applications to other areas. Other
industry conferences that I&amp;rsquo;ve been to have had extremely specific focus, including
a lot of vendors advertising their products. Strange Loop was nothing like that, and
all talks I attended could basically be put under one umbrella &amp;ndash;
&amp;ldquo;the joy of Computer Science&amp;rdquo;. I also got to meet and talk to some people whom
I&amp;rsquo;d only followed on Twitter before. Since there were too many parallel tracks,
I couldn&amp;rsquo;t attend all interesting talks, but out of the ones I did, some really
stood out&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C4rT0lgJr6U&#34;&gt;Government Hacking and Human Rights: The Why and the How&lt;/a&gt; by Amie Stepanovich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fNe1i7nVbXI&#34;&gt;Humanities x Technology&lt;/a&gt; by Ashley Nelson-Hornstein&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HfD9IMZ9rKY&#34;&gt;Systems programming as a swiss army knife&lt;/a&gt; by Julia Evans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, all talk videos are now online on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C4rT0lgJr6U&amp;amp;list=PLcGKfGEEONaDvuLDFFKRfzbsaBuVVXdYa&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;, and worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;docker-distributed-systems-summit:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;Docker Distributed Systems Summit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small invitation-only event, the summit was a great way to meet people
directly engaged in the Docker community. A part of the attraction was also the
chance to visit Berlin for the first time. Once again, late confirmations led to
rushed planning, and some good fortune allowed me to get a visa in time. My job was
only to attend the talks, engage with people, and lead some discussions. I thought
this was a great format for two reasons &amp;ndash; I got to learn more about Docker&amp;rsquo;s
other products myself, and the small size of the conference enabled many
personal interactions that allowed for deeper conversations.
The &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.docker.com/2016/10/docker-distributed-system-summit-videos-podcast-episodes/&#34;&gt;official blog post&lt;/a&gt; contains links to
the talk videos, slides, and other information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-conference-travel-in-general:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1&#34;&gt;On Conference Travel in General&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, these were rewarding trips, albeit tiring. Being away from home for all
these days sounds great in principle, but as I found out, travel is rather
disruptive when it&amp;rsquo;s not purely for vacation. Still, I&amp;rsquo;m incredibly lucky to
have had all these opportunities. In fact, this was one of the primary reasons I
joined Docker. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to doing more of this in 2017, but
probably with a little more focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;I also attended a fifth conference this year, back in June &amp;ndash; DockerCon 2016. This was my first DockerCon, and a pretty interesting affair. For one, it gave me significant motivation to work hard preceding the event, and the project I was working on was at the center of major announcements. I also ended up staying for the week in Seattle, so that was great as well. I decided not to write much about DockerCon in this post because I barely attended any talks (booth duty!), and enough has already been written by others about it.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:438665085d42b12aa98e7fb2070409e1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2015 Year in Review</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/2015-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2015 19:16:02 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/2015-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Are you already sick of people writing their yearly review posts? I bet! Iâ€™m going to add more more to the pile though, but mostly as a milestone for myself, and for others who might find value in reading it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, I have to say that 2015 has been the most unusual year of my life. Iâ€™ve experienced many different things and changed a lot as a person. This is also the year when I finally decided and went through the process of quitting grad school to venture out into the real world. Iâ€™ll try to keep it short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;depression-and-personal-growth:b28868909f74bdd4f426ebee08db720a&#34;&gt;Depression and Personal Growth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What started in late 2014 as a series of depressive episodes turned into a full-blown depression that lasted for most of 2015. It affected nearly every area of my life, most notably my ability to work. Research suffered and I failed to make any meaningful progress, which in turn only made it harder to recover. My ability to make friends, and keep in touch with existing ones also took a hit as I became increasingly lonely. It took a lot of time to accept this and start taking steps to get better, and Iâ€™m still on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it has been a very troubling period where I came in touch with some of the darkest emotions in me, it has also been full of trememdous learning about self and personal growth. It taught me to take a hard look at my priorities. It showed me which people are really well-wishers and were willing to help when I needed it most. I realized the value of community and investing in relationships, something Iâ€™d never thought important because I believed I could survive on my own. It also made me a lot more empathetic to the suffering of other people, and I think I emerge from it a better person. Probably more cynical, but better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;world-view:b28868909f74bdd4f426ebee08db720a&#34;&gt;World View&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps as a consequence of my struggles, I became much more attuned to the struggles of other people, in particular underprivileged groups. I realized that the world isnâ€™t always a fair place, and is heavily biased in favor of those already predisposed to success. Causes like equality (gender, race etc.) gained new meaning for me, and my opinions of right and wrong evolved to a large extent. I also started participating in discussions and voicing opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;work:b28868909f74bdd4f426ebee08db720a&#34;&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I donâ€™t think I was ever as productive in grad school as I would like, but 2015 turned out to be the tipping point. Things got to a stage where my lack of progress had become a chronic problem and nothing I was trying seemed to work. Changing research groups didnâ€™t seem quite possible then, so leaving grad school completely was the only plausible option. It took me a while to come to terms with the decision, but it became clearer as time passed. I had some great interviews and got several job offers which was good for my confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I&amp;#39;m joining &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/docker&#34;&gt;@docker&lt;/a&gt; later this year! Super excited, looking forward to work with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aluzzardi&#34;&gt;@aluzzardi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/vieux&#34;&gt;@vieux&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/abronan&#34;&gt;@abronan&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sam_alba&#34;&gt;@sam_alba&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nishant Totla (@nishanttotla) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nishanttotla/status/647555264699219968&#34;&gt;September 25, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still the battle was only half won, and consistent efforts to gain back my lost productivity have finally bore some fruit, and I feel confident I can do great things with my new job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;travel:b28868909f74bdd4f426ebee08db720a&#34;&gt;Travel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travel wise, 2015 was a decent year. I managed to stick to my resolution of visiting at least one new country each year. This year, it was an amazing summer trip to the UK (England+Scotland), and a (just concluded) winter trip to Hawaii.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Goodbye Hawaii, it&amp;#39;s been a meaningful trip! Time to go back to normal life and start afresh. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/NzS1Pnftk4&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/NzS1Pnftk4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Traveler Boy (@nrt_travel) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nrt_travel/status/682771096320409602&#34;&gt;January 1, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a few other short trips too, but not nearly enough! The overwhelming guilt that comes from not being productive is a big adversary of travel, and Iâ€™ve been trying hard to control it. Still, Iâ€™m proud and happy for the travel I managed to do, but looking forward to all the more that I will do in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;health:b28868909f74bdd4f426ebee08db720a&#34;&gt;Health&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped running long distances after the hip injury I had in late 2014, hoping to get to its root before starting again. I picked up biking instead and started riding long distances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not having learned my lesson from running, I built up mileage too much too soon, and ended up with an overuse injury to the back that would keep me out for much of the year. What finally did put me in touch with my body was picking up Yoga, which not only showed me how ill-prepared I was to go through extreme physical stresses, but also gave me a framework to think about how to treat my body and be gentle with it. Most importantly, to listen to my body. Mental stress also contributed most likely, and is as much part of overall recovery as anything else. I hope to take these learnings into the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;in-2016:b28868909f74bdd4f426ebee08db720a&#34;&gt;In 2016&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think my work is laid out clearly. I need to rediscover my productivity by performing well at work, while simultaneously giving more importance to community both in my personal and professional lives. I will travel more. I will recover from my injuries and respect my body. I will remember to apply everything Iâ€™ve learned the hard way this year to similar problems. Life isnâ€™t going to be any easier, but I will be wiser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I write this post next year, I hope there will be more positivity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Off to Hawaii - a Good End to a Miserable Year</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/off-to-hawaii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2015 15:39:26 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/off-to-hawaii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;2015 will go down as the worst year in my life so far, no doubts about that! It has been a year when I suffered a lot, learned some hard lessons, and had to face several uncomfortable truths about myself. Iâ€™ve battled terrifying depression and felt things I wasnâ€™t ready to handle. As painful as that has been, Iâ€™m glad to be ending the year right â€“ by taking a break from everything, and heading to Hawaii on my first real solo trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Booked tickets to Hawaii today, leaving in 5 days!! ðŸ™ŒðŸ™ŒðŸ™Œ Now gotta figure the rest out. Any suggestions?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nishant Totla (@nishanttotla) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nishanttotla/status/678304771921436672&#34;&gt;December 19, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iâ€™m leaving tomorrow, for 8 days, and relishing the opportunity to relax, contemplate, and plan for the coming year. Iâ€™m going to spend a few days in Honolulu, and the rest living on an organic farm not far from some hills. I plan to run, hike, eat, read, and swim at the beach. Iâ€™ll do what I want, go where I like. There will be plenty of time to write too, and prepare for my new job which I start soon after returning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fully intend to cut down social media use during the stay, and concentrate on the moment. The stress and poor lifestyle during 2015 have diminished my focus and severely affected my ability to think deeply about hard problems. I want to start recovering some of that. For starters, I have a book to read, along with some exciting new research papers. Hoping to have a great trip!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>India&#39;s Undercurrent of Propaganda</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/india-undercurrent-propaganda/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 16:01:47 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/india-undercurrent-propaganda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;India is currently at an interesting political standpoint. We finally have a single party forming the central government without needing support from other parties (last this happened was in 1984). The average Indian person seems to be much more aware and concerned about the political situation, and invested in the countryâ€™s future, especially young people. All of this is a major shift compared to a few years ago. There have been several contributing factors â€“ dissatisfaction with the UPA govt., anti-corruption activism by AAP, strong leadership in the BJP to name a few. Optimism has been brewing for a while and people are looking forward to progress. Whether the current political setup will deliver on all promises remains to be seen, but as the collective euphoria fades, thereâ€™s a different kind of problem surfacing in the country now. Itâ€™s difficult to describe precisely, but it includes a deepening chasm between different groups of people, lack of constructive criticism and the ability to handle it, and a seeming absence of nuanced public discourse. Of course, these are my opinions, but the explosion of Indiansâ€™ social media presence has made it easy to quickly process a lot of diverse opinions to try and make sense of what people really think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, religious intolerance is a hot topic right now after &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2015/09/indian-mob-kills-man-cow-slaughter-rumour-150930193719666.html&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-34504434&#34;&gt;unsavory&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/features/2015/11/indian-scholars-return-awards-demand-free-speech-151102101213399.html&#34;&gt;events&lt;/a&gt; over the last few weeks. This has led several people to express concern, while many others think of these events as outliers. Going further, some believe in a full fledged international conspiracy to bring the country down. It doesnâ€™t help that opposing political parties readily exploit the situation, the news media is downright sensationalist and often insensitive, and the ruling party remains selectively silent. I will NOT try to pick sides in these debates, because that is futile and painful&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:e27ad0a7be6c3af4d3da2b23560dabef:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:e27ad0a7be6c3af4d3da2b23560dabef:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. What I do want to talk about is how bigoted propaganda is proliferating in the country right now, aided both by easier access to technology and peopleâ€™s unwillingness to see eye to eye on complex issues that donâ€™t have straightforward answers. As a result, the answers arenâ€™t coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason itâ€™s an undercurrent is because it is largely based on viral sharing of propagandist messages across social media and messaging platforms. It consists of hate speech, wrongly attributed quotes, and fabrication of facts to emotionally manipulate people who donâ€™t know what to believe, or will not put in effort to verify what theyâ€™re reading. Some central themes keep coming up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;India is a Hindu country, and Hindus must have their wishes respected at any cost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ruling party (and prime minister) are mostly faultless and doing great work, while some anti-national elements are trying to ruin it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indiaâ€™s intellectuals are complicit with those who are conspiring against the country, and are &amp;ldquo;minority-sympathizers&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/india/comments/18vfcg/who_does_sickular_refer_to_isnt_secularism_a/&#34;&gt;sickulars&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Muslims are responsible for a lot of Indiaâ€™s problems (social and economic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All those who canâ€™t handle Hindu nationalism should go to Pakistan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no religious intolerance in the country, and anyone who speaks up against the government or Hindus deserves retaliation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list goes on, and these are all complex points, given how strongly theyâ€™re being voiced now. Itâ€™s true that people are pretty tired of weak and corrupt governments from the past, and have pinned a lot of hopes on the current one, so itâ€™s natural to be defensive and find other avenues to pin blame. Politics in the country has always been heavily influenced by religion, but maybe this is the first time a prime minister has strongly advertised himself as an ardent Hindu, while also convincing people he can lead the countryâ€™s development. The prime ministerâ€™s strong persona and lack of leadership among other parties was a prime reason for the overwhelming majority during elections, but the ruling party is a large and eclectic one â€“ in terms of ideology and methods. And even though the prime minister doesnâ€™t endorse any violence or hatred, his silence and &lt;a href=&#34;http://indianexpress.com/article/india/india-others/bjp-leader-vijayvargiya-attacks-shah-rukh-khan-says-his-soul-in-pakistan/&#34;&gt;occasional  hateful statements by fringe party members&lt;/a&gt; are seen as endorsement by fanatics who want to push their own agendas. All this might not be an issue given India has a large Hindu majority anyway â€“ except India is a much more complicated country. Even at 80% Hindu, we still have more than 270 million people who donâ€™t identify as Hindu. For context, this is comparable to the population of the entire United States (~320 million). If weâ€™re going to keep building up propaganda that alienates such a large number of people, it could possibly divide society irreparably, because none of these people are going anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding what public figures say, how are common citizens actually forming opinions? After all, public opinion can hold huge sway in a democracy, and itâ€™s really important that people get their facts right. This is my biggest beef with this whole undercurrent of propaganda â€“ pure BS spreading around virally. As mobile phones and internet access spread quickly, exposing many people to the internet for the first time, we can expect that what they will be fed a lot of new ideas. If seasoned internet users sometimes canâ€™t tell whatâ€™s true online, I fear that new users are especially prone to believing everything they read. Especially content that is articulate and sounds legitimate. Consider this WhatsApp message thatâ€™s been going around&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/propaganda-post/msg1.png&#34; style=&#34;width:50%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need a translation, click &lt;a href=&#34;https://paper.dropbox.com/doc/Translations-for-propaganda-messages-forwarded-in-India-Fk3IGFAI5WiDA2aSOH9m5&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This is a great example of a message that sounds so harmless at first, but eventually subtly tries to pass off a positive correlation between not killing cows and a countryâ€™s progress. Thereâ€™s no such correlation obviously, and Uruguay doesnâ€™t hang people if they kill a cow. On the contrary, Uruguay is a leading exporter of premium quality beef, often lauded for its &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-latin-america-30210749&#34;&gt;advanced practices&lt;/a&gt;. See how this further fuels the controversy around beef, in a country where &lt;a href=&#34;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Haryana-makes-sale-of-beef-a-non-bailable-offence/articleshow/46590961.cms&#34;&gt;itâ€™s already a storm&lt;/a&gt;? As if it doesnâ€™t matter that Uruguay has an entirely different economy, size, and social structure. This might seem like a trivial example, but innocuous things like these can end up being influential in shaping peopleâ€™s ideas. Just consider the following tweet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The writer of the Moody&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;warning&amp;quot; to Modi is the son in law of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/AwardWapsi?src=hash&#34;&gt;#AwardWapsi&lt;/a&gt; Irfan Habib?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; rati parker (@ratigirl) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ratigirl/status/660336942186409984&#34;&gt;October 31, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Itâ€™s a question, and (surprise surprise!) the answer is NO. But the tweet went viral anyway and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newslaundry.com/2015/11/05/how-the-irfan-habib-son-in-law-rumour-made-its-way-from-twitter-to-prime-time-news/&#34;&gt;people bought it, it was news&lt;/a&gt;. The problem is that this isnâ€™t a one-off thing, it happens all the time, and can consolidate opinions based on absolutely false information. Itâ€™s a sad state of affairs when people just wonâ€™t bother checking facts, and comfortably use (or worse, fabricate) anything that suits their cause. Because when it comes to public discourse, rhetoric rules and facts are for losers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iâ€™m not saying that this is exclusively Indiaâ€™s problem. Most countries in the world have their own internal clashes and propaganda, and suffer because of it. What IS Indiaâ€™s problem though, is people interested in fueling an atmosphere of hatred and misunderstandings, even though the current government has opportunities and the support to undo several past grievances. This problem includes trolls and haters who spread misinformation, normal people who spread it further without bothering to verify it, the media that likes to &lt;a href=&#34;http://indianexpress.com/article/entertainment/bollywood/salman-khan-on-the-intolerance-issue-my-mother-is-susheela-charak-father-is-salim-khan/&#34;&gt;put people on the spot to extract juicy quotes&lt;/a&gt;, politicians who keep making regressive statements, and also intellectuals who often try to ignore the problem and stay away, instead of trying to educate those who are missing the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another issue that I consider unique to India (as far as Iâ€™m aware) is sharing propaganda via private messaging services such as WhatsApp. These have exploded in popularity over the last few years. Communities and groups on these services are also ripe grounds for spreading misinformation â€“ but with an additional downer â€“ there is no liability or a way to verify anything. For instance, who knows where the message about Uruguay above came from, how many people read or questioned it. There is no way to know, nor can you call someone out for manufacturing information (like you can with tweets or Facebook posts). Whatâ€™s commonly shared here are messages that paint a one-sided picture, reinforcing whatever people believe or want to believe. Peopleâ€™s social circles are often largely composed of other people with similar views, and there is little opportunity to see the broader context, or have healthy debates. This leads to them saying things like â€œI donâ€™t see any religious intolerance around me, itâ€™s all fakeâ€ etc. This also makes it easy for them to generalize their views about other groups of people. Hereâ€™s another example&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/propaganda-post/msg2.png&#34; style=&#34;width:50%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;img data-action=&#34;zoom&#34; src=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/images/propaganda-post/msg2_2.png&#34; style=&#34;width:50%; float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&#34;https://paper.dropbox.com/doc/Translations-for-propaganda-messages-forwarded-in-India-Fk3IGFAI5WiDA2aSOH9m5#:h=Message-2&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for a translation. Notice how this message makes tall claims, and signs off as the PMO (Prime Ministerâ€™s Office). Itâ€™s not hard to craft messages like these, and there are several people who believe that this is actually coming from the PMO. That canâ€™t be right at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might think that Iâ€™m nitpicking. And I really hope so, because after having seen how fake stories and propaganda blew up the debate against vaccines&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:e27ad0a7be6c3af4d3da2b23560dabef:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:e27ad0a7be6c3af4d3da2b23560dabef:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, or still bogs down progress on climate change, Iâ€™m paranoid about how easy it is to create fear among unsuspecting people. The cold war was a grand spectacle of exactly this. Fear is a strong emotion, and can easily lead entire societies to make irrational or emotional decisions that halt progress or prove costly over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, some of the points raised in some other forwarded messages are legitimate questions to ask, but are often buried under loads of generalization and lies. Itâ€™s hard to separate the two, and the audience is often gullible. Most people will probably not react to such propaganda, but there are always those who will use these to justify criminal activities. And weâ€™re not even starting to talk about prejudice and subliminal bias. Whether or not you agree with everything Iâ€™ve written, the next time you get any sort of message or read something that is leveling accusations or blaming someone, be extra careful, verify facts (Google is your friend!), try to critically analyze and discuss with someone, and only then consider passing it on. Itâ€™s easy to hit that forward button, but you never know who youâ€™re sending messages to. You might be very calm and nice yourself, but maybe your recipients arenâ€™t, so be mindful of that and make sure you think twice, especially if youâ€™re in an influential position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iâ€™m not proposing any solutions or suggesting I have answers, but itâ€™s probably worthwhile to introspect the small actions we perform on a daily basis, because sometimes itâ€™s not a few very bad people who bring the group down, but a large number of â€œslightly badâ€ people who are okay with the occasional wrong action. Weâ€™ve seen our apathy lead to problems before, letâ€™s not have hatred create more. I canâ€™t tell you what to believe in, because I donâ€™t know the solutions, but Iâ€™m pretty sure that hateful propaganda isnâ€™t going to benefit anyone. The reality for a large country like India is very complex, and &lt;strong&gt;EVERYTHING YOU READ ON THE INTERNET IS NOT TRUE&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:e27ad0a7be6c3af4d3da2b23560dabef:1&#34;&gt;Besides, I donâ€™t live in India currently, and have to accept that I might not have the full picture.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:e27ad0a7be6c3af4d3da2b23560dabef:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:e27ad0a7be6c3af4d3da2b23560dabef:2&#34;&gt;I still canâ€™t believe that became a thing!
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:e27ad0a7be6c3af4d3da2b23560dabef:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about Empathy</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/learning-about-empathy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2015 15:46:09 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/learning-about-empathy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Empathy is such a simple concept to understand, yet so difficult to practice! Kids are taught about it. The word itself is lazily thrown around, assuming everyone knows how to empathize, that itâ€™s something weâ€™re naturally good at. Well weâ€™re not! Even if we care enough to look outside our own busy lives to try and want to empathize with someone, itâ€™s too easy to fall into the trap of making judgments or believing we know everything about another personâ€™s situation. Empathy is especially tough because it requires us to not only understand a different person, but also to set aside our own biases and keep an open mind, all of which are notoriously difficult things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having gone through a rough patch involving several personal struggles over the last two years, and distinctly feeling that nobody understood my situation, Iâ€™ve realized an important lesson. Empathy is defined as â€œthe ability to understand and share the feelings of another personâ€, and that is really the key â€“ &lt;strong&gt;understanding feelings&lt;/strong&gt; â€“ as opposed to just understanding the problem at hand or trying to find a solution. The best way to do it is simpler than you can imagine, you just have to ask! Think about it, how many people have asked you in the last few days how you feel? Have you asked anyone? We all struggle with the stresses of modern life, but rarely ask each other how we feel. To add to it, we immediately make up our minds about others, and this only blocks out further communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remembering to focus on how someone is feeling rather than what theyâ€™re talking about, or how theyâ€™re behaving, helps me better understand and help people. This is especially valuable while dealing with conflicts â€“ someone might be upset at you but if you understood how they felt, your opinion and even reaction might change. If a friend berated you for being late, you might be upset because sheâ€™s being too touchy. But if you knew that she lost her job that day and is feeling down, not only are you likely to let it go, but might also alter your behavior and try to make her feel better instead of getting upset yourself. For someone like me who usually tends to get upset quickly, this is a VERY useful tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who empathize with others are more likable and less likely to pick up extended conflicts. I believe lack of empathy is a prime ingredient in a lot of the hatred and stereotyping that is perpetrated today. Everyone conveniently judges others from their own safe points of view. Iâ€™m guilty too, but have been trying hard to correct it. While empathy is not the solution to every problem in the world, it can certainly alleviate some!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize, the only takeaway from this post is to always keep your mind open for what the other person is feeling. If you canâ€™t figure it out, remember to ask! People can be pleasantly surprised when you do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supporting a Football Club</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/supporting-a-football-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2015 19:10:35 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/supporting-a-football-club/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport2/hi/football/eng_prem/3553027.stm&#34;&gt;Sunday, March 28, 2004 : Arsenal vs Manchester United at Highbury, London&lt;/a&gt; was the first live football game I watched (on TV, of course). Iâ€™d only ever followed cricket before that and played some football, but this was unlike anything I knew in sport. It was fast and full of action. These players were really passionate and the tension was palpable. Then on 50 minutes, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zWhCegHpQJc&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=257&#34;&gt;Arsenalâ€™s number 14 scored&lt;/a&gt; from a brilliant long range effort, a stunning goal by any standard! The game ended at 1-1, but Arsenal were beautiful to watch. They counter-attacked with breathtaking speed, defended like a rock, and had brilliant individuals. I would go on to watch a few more Arsenal games that season. When I visited Mauritius the following summer and saw a banner proclaiming â€œArsenal â€“ Champions 2003-04â€, the clubâ€™s global reach made an impression on me â€“ I had made my choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I support Arsenal Football Club. I watch their games, follow their activities, feel happy when they win, disappointed when they donâ€™t. But why all this long-term affection for a team thatâ€™s based thousands of miles away, in a city Iâ€™ve never lived in? Why spend so much time and energy worrying about what is â€œjust a game after allâ€? In short, what does it mean to support a club?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The football season, to be honest is pretty much the same affair every year. Each team will play every other team twice â€“ home and away in the league, and there may be two or three cup competitions. It might look painfully monotonous to an outsider. To quote from the movie Fever Pitch&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:77fce4fd1418c0509b702f30679a8dd6:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:77fce4fd1418c0509b702f30679a8dd6:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;custom-quote&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h1 class=&#34;icon-quote-left&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Anthropologists have always had a hard time with Football. The trouble is, you can only see whatâ€™s on the outside, but there IS an inside, believe it or not. We all have our reasons for loving things the way we do.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inside for me is that itâ€™s not about the season, year after year. Itâ€™s about having something to look forward to in a normal week. I can have a disastrous week, yet, I will tune into the weekend game with unsullied fresh hope, hoping for a victory. And when it happens, I temporarily forget all there is to worry about, and rejoice. Each week presents a new challenge, and this is what keeps fans going on. The flip side is that a bad day for the team can make it worse for you. But then, thatâ€™s a gamble weâ€™re all willing to take. Football fans often believe that the fortunes of their favorite team are invariably linked to their own. The team doing well coincides with life moving uphill, and the team doing badly means life sucks. Iâ€™ve experienced that, and it honestly is irrational and crazy. Yet itâ€™s a very comforting and hopeful feeling, one that I donâ€™t want to give up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oneâ€™s relationship with the football club evolves over time. I think there are three broad stages â€“ What, How and Why. At the start (the What), it is greedy, you want results from your team. You want to have bragging rights. If you manage to stay in it long enough, things change, and you come into the How of it. You gradually start taking more interest in the teamâ€™s affairs. You start being worried about how individuals combine to actually make the team work. How is it that the team plays as it does? How does the coach contribute? When this happens, youâ€™ve crossed a certain threshold. After this, it will be hard to start following a new team. Finally, the Why of it. This is the part when you have surpassed your purely on-the-field relationship with the team, and you see it as something more. You know the history. You know club legends, and you have finally accepted the team as a part of your life. The team influences you, and you feel your support makes a difference, however small. It is an obsession of some sort, but then this is what Hornby says about it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;custom-quote&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h1 class=&#34;icon-quote-left&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Why is it that adults arenâ€™t supposed to go mad about anything? Youâ€™ve got to keep a lid on it, and if you donâ€™t, then people are apparently entitled to say what they like. You havenâ€™t grown up, youâ€™re a moron. Your conversation is trivial and boorish, you canâ€™t express your emotional needs. You canâ€™t relate to your children, and you die, lonely and miserable. But you know, what the hell?
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, there are certainly social aspects of football, being the one true global sport that it is. If you want one example of absolutely diverse people coming together, forgetting their differences and cheering for the same thing, then you need to look no further. Iâ€™ve bonded with people just because we support the same team. This makes it worthwhile, and fosters a lot of positivity around the world&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:77fce4fd1418c0509b702f30679a8dd6:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:77fce4fd1418c0509b702f30679a8dd6:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Quoting from The Fever Pitch again&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;custom-quote&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h1 class=&#34;icon-quote-left&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Itâ€™s not easy to become a football fan. It takes years. But if you put in the hours, youâ€™re welcomed without question into a new family. Except in this family, you care about the same people and hope for the same things. Whatâ€™s childish about that?
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But teams arenâ€™t constant entities, they change. What happens if an important player leaves your club and joins another team? Many people do not buy the idea of supporting a club. Of course, players will rarely keep playing for one club their entire careers, but supporting a club is different from rooting for your favorite player. It is an involvement with the entire philosophy, style and ideas of the organization as a whole. A single player can be important, but never bigger than the club. Supporting the club is about feeling connected with its history, being bothered with its present, and hoping for a successful future. Players will come and go, but a club stays on. You pin hopes on a player, feel sad or angry when he leaves, but you move on. How is that very different from life anyway?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking back to why I started supporting Arsenal, it was the way they played â€“ slick movement and ruthlessly effective â€“ qualities I hugely admired. Those were also Arsenalâ€™s glory years, when they won trophies and were feared. I was a defiant young person and it was a match made in heaven. I watched every game expecting a win, and that was a good feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, a lot changed, including the clubâ€™s fortunes. Arsenal went from being the best in the country to a good team that famously stopped winning trophies, until only recently. All those years were about hope and belief. It was the time when I grew as a person, and learned that things werenâ€™t always good or easy, that disappointments were real. Arsenal frustrated me, but also let me enjoy moments of pure joy. Iâ€™m not the same person I was a decade ago, but my support for this team has stayed all along. Iâ€™ve grown with it, and it feels like an integral part of the things I believe in. Does that sound ridiculous? Maybe, but I donâ€™t care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal arenâ€™t your average club. Itâ€™s one of the few that value their history and try to stick to their philosophy and style of play. A club that has persistently shown class and maintained standards. A big factor in this is the current manager, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ars%C3%A8ne_Wenger&#34;&gt;ArsÃ¨ne Wenger&lt;/a&gt;, and the way he has kept the team competitive despite financial constraints and immense pressure. Make no mistake, the modern football managerâ€™s job is both glamorous and risky, several get fired in a season for underperforming. Yet Arsenal are one of the rare clubs that have stuck with the manager for more than 19 years now. He hasnâ€™t seen as much success as I think he deserves, but he has provided stability and nurtured some great talent in a climate where clubs are often left with two choices â€“ pile on more debt, or lose their edge (and players). None of that for Arsenal, who have successfully built a new stadium and are now gradually getting back to being the best. Despite &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23WengerOut&amp;amp;src=typd&#34;&gt;frequent vocal opposition against him&lt;/a&gt;, he has set a great example, so much that for many fans (including me), heâ€™s a major part of the clubâ€™s current identity (his first name helps too I guess!). Heâ€™s a man who breathes football, protects his players, believes in maintaining standards, is passionate not just about his job, but the club too. Of course he wonâ€™t be around forever, but what he has achieved here will be hard to emulate. If football clubs are built in the image of people associated with them, then Arsenal is the club Iâ€™d want to support without doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success is only one part of the equation. Itâ€™s true that Arsenal have never recaptured the glory of 2004, are no longer title contenders by default, constantly written off by the media. But that doesnâ€™t affect me anymore. My bond to this team is different now. It still looks the same on the outside, but has been tempered by many strong feelings over the years. Trophies were an expectation before, but now theyâ€™re just a response to those that write us off. Winning against the odds is totally different from winning when youâ€™re favorites. Winning isnâ€™t always important, because this team has made me see failure, defiance, and ultimate success. A few years ago, I maintained a safe and objective distance, like the single-minded love of the new fan. Today, itâ€™s about memories and moments that swept me off my feet. I no longer wave my allegiance around in peopleâ€™s faces, nor do I expect others to adore the team. Itâ€™s just a constant source of joy, like a successful long-term relationship with its highs and lows, but never doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to intermittent memorable moments, football abounds in them. Going back to May 26, 1989, when Michael Thomas scored in the last 10 seconds, the goal that won Arsenal the championship, you can see the drama and emotion that Iâ€™m talking about&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4jiBIdtUKhs&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:77fce4fd1418c0509b702f30679a8dd6:1&#34;&gt;The 1997 movie, based on the novel of the same name, by Nick Hornby (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fever_Pitch&#34;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fever_Pitch&lt;/a&gt;). It relates the authorâ€™s life, its highs and lows to the fortunes of the football club he supports, which incidentally is also Arsenal.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:77fce4fd1418c0509b702f30679a8dd6:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:77fce4fd1418c0509b702f30679a8dd6:2&#34;&gt;Not to say there arenâ€™t problems. For instance, thereâ€™s racism, but football is a microcosm of society. It reflects society, and can also affect it in return. Todayâ€™s clubs are involved with both local and global initiatives, and can be strong leaders in bringing about social change.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:77fce4fd1418c0509b702f30679a8dd6:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rediscovering Podcasts</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/rediscovering-podcasts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 15:50:52 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/rediscovering-podcasts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This summer, I was interviewing at several companies. Among other things, it involved a lot of travel, and there was little I could do while traveling. If I was driving, Iâ€™d mostly listen to my usual Spotify playlists, although they got boring pretty soon. Taking the train allowed me to read in addition, but Iâ€™d usually get distracted or fall asleep since the interviews were exhausting. Soon enough, all this travel time started feeling wasteful, but I wanted to reclaim it, so I constantly tried to find ways to engage in something productive, or learn something new. Then one day I was reading an article in which CEOs of some companies described how they made their commutes productive. One of the ideas was to listen to audiobooks. I didnâ€™t have any books in mind, but I immediately remembered how Iâ€™d once wanted to try podcasts, and never did. I downloaded an &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.bambuna.podcastaddict&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;Android app&lt;/a&gt; and loaded some interesting podcasts. I quickly realized that this was what I was looking for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know why I only recently discovered how nice it is to listen to podcasts while driving. It&amp;#39;s educative + makes me feel less lonely.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nishant Totla (@nishanttotla) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nishanttotla/status/634283994704535552&#34;&gt;August 20, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with listening to some podcasts about people sharing their experiences, and soon moved on to human behavior and social skills. I also tried some economics, culture, and science. I found podcasts refreshing for several reasons. First of all, I was listening to very stimulating and engaging content, which excited me and kept me alert. This was especially welcome during long lonely drives, often in rush hour traffic. Second, podcasts often featured people having a conversation, where I would laugh and grimace and feel actively involved. Most importantly though, I learned a great deal about diverse topics, and this is something I love to do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iâ€™m just going to emphasize that podcasts are brilliant and unrivaled when you want to productively use time when only your auditory senses are free. This is their biggest advantage compared to all other information media, especially seeing how everyone is constantly â€œengagedâ€ these days. Podcasts are a regular fixture for drives now, and Iâ€™m gradually trying to add them to other tasks like cooking, cleaning, and in general anything that doesnâ€™t require immense concentration. Of course, there are still times when I just want silence, or music, but in general, Iâ€™m a big fan of trying to find opportunities to learn small bits that could eventually add up to major life changes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eight Lessons I Learned in College</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/x-lessons-i-learned-in-college/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2012 19:26:42 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/x-lessons-i-learned-in-college/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Iâ€™m writing a post after around five months! Whoa! What a ride the last semester has been! Iâ€™ve now graduated (provided they give me my degree) from one of the best colleges in India, with new hopes and dreams, some knowledge, passion and a lot of friends. The past few months have been a blur, and Iâ€™ve done loads of new things. Most importantly, Iâ€™ve had the opportunity to think about and look at all that I accomplished (or failed to accomplish) during college, Iâ€™ve thought about where my motivations lie, what I want from life and ultimately how Iâ€™m going to achieve that. And in this post, Iâ€™m going to try and summarize all that. I entered this place as a high-on-success and low-on-wisdom defiant individual. I now leave as a mature and responsible, motivated and slightly wiser person. So here are some of the most important lessons I would want to pass on after having survived the jungle that undergraduate life is&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-be-liberal:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Be Liberal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you asked me for the single most important lesson college life taught me, then it would without doubt be the ability to take a liberal stand on any issue (moral, philosophical or legal) that may or may not affect me directly. When I came in as a freshman&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I must admit I was as dumb as one can get. I had strong ideas â€“ they were strong not because I had seen the world and come to well thought-of conclusions. My ideas were just a product of my upbringing, the popular media (mostly Indian), and the conversations with self that one usually has when theyâ€™ve been sitting alone in a room for hours. So what happened during college? Surely, not all those ideas changed. What changed was my approach to them, what I thought of my convictions, how I defended them and how I urged others to see my point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I used to be vegetarian in first year, and still am, but unlike then, I no more think that eating meat is â€œwrongâ€. I have realized that all my opinions are results of my thoughts, and no more right than yours. Contrary to what a lot of people think, being liberal for me is not about trying my hand at everything â€“ yes you can be liberal and a vegetarian, a teetotaler, and staunchly religious all at the same time. By being liberal, I mean the ability to take into account everyone elseâ€™s point of view, all the data available, and then consciously and justifiably form opinions. It incorporates the basic premise that no opinion is sacred, and as long as people are happy with their choices and lives, you have no right, or reason to meddle. This is the simple secret to leading uncomplicated lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-think-independently-and-explore-recklessly:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Think independently and explore recklessly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I strongly feel that we have stopped thinking. As a student community, there seems to be less emphasis on independent thought and charting out our own course. Most of us (and Iâ€™m no less guilty) just try to follow the golden path laid down before us. Itâ€™s either that high-paying job, or the highly ranked university somewhere in the USA. While thereâ€™s nothing wrong with these choices, whatâ€™s wrong is making these choices just because they are the in-thing. Do we ever stop to think what our motivation in life is? We all need to ask this question to ourselves sooner or later â€“ do we really plan to do something with lasting value, something different? Are we willing to take risks, do something our peers arenâ€™t doing? College may or may not be sufficient for us to find our lifeâ€™s calling, but just the realization that one needs to do what they love the most, is important. It might seem trivial to think about, but if you look around, people easily forget this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent thought comes out of knowing a lot of things, which is in turn borne out of having explored a lot of avenues. You like watching that sport? Try playing it. You like music? Try your hand at learning how to play your favourite tune. Learn how to write code. Learn a new language. Explore how it is to work in a company. Dabble your hands in research. Explore other fields of work, try to figure out the arts. Donâ€™t waste your time sitting upon things you already have. You will never have the kind of freedom you can afford in college, so donâ€™t let it be wasted on nothing. Learn to get your hands dirty, learn to make yourself curious, who knows you might find diamonds in the dirt!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-lose-some-inhibitions:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Lose some inhibitions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iâ€™ve had a few friends whoâ€™ve been living frightened lives â€“ inside a cocoon of their own making, one that keeps them far away from things theyâ€™re scared of. I was no different when I started, and unfortunately, I believe I wasted a couple of years sticking to myself, until I found friends who would pull me out of my shell. Iâ€™ve realized that college is the first (and probably the last) time when you have the opportunity to overcome your fears, to make an effort to challenge yourself on the personal front. Have you ever tried singing in front of few dozen unknown people? Have you ever taken part in a debate and publicly made a fool of yourself? Are you afraid of wearing shorts in public lest you show your sexy (or ugly) legs? Are you enraged if your beliefs are questioned? If yes, then are you doing something about it? Shouldnâ€™t you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why all this trouble? It is because quite a few of the qualities developed this way surely help later in life, directly or indirectly. And you would never know you had those qualities, unless you loosened up and dirtied your hands with a few scary-looking activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Iâ€™m not saying that you should try everything just for the heck of it, but it does make a lot of sense to put yourself in situations you have no idea how to handle yourself in. This teaches you one very important life lesson, which is that of standing up to unexpected scenarios and deal with new kinds of emotions. Isnâ€™t this what life is about anyway?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-interact-with-the-opposite-sex:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Interact with the opposite sex&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a society as prudish as ours, this is always a tricky issue. More so in an environment like IITB, with a highly polarized sex-ratio. Firstly, why is this important? From what I know, males and females often have differences in their points of view, perhaps due to different upbringing. Understanding this is important. Life will eventually make you interact with people of the opposite sex. You will have colleagues, a spouse, friends. You will want to know what they find offensive or how open to certain ideas you can expect them to be etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a male point of view, Iâ€™ve seen some guys becoming excessively abusive, and outright disrespectful towards the females they see daily. Blame this on a testosterone-intense environment if you will, but unless youâ€™ve been friends with a girl, you might tend to develop sexist attitudes, or be uncomfortable in one-on-one interactions. And this will surely cause problems at some point, on a personal level or more. Learn to look at boy-girl communication in an uncomplicated way. Encouraging and taking part in healthy interactions with the opposite sex are a certain step towards creating a healthy society based on mutual respect. The same applies to girls, while interacting with males.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So meet people of the opposite sex. Make friends with them, learn about their ideas, opinions and constraints. Donâ€™t worry about being close to someone. These exchanges go a long way in making you comfortable in any group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-procrastination-will-take-you-down:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Procrastination will take you down&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procrastination can be a bane for anyone, even the most brilliant mind out there. Truth be told, it canâ€™t be avoided. We all do it, and probably need it in healthy amounts. But when it gets out of control, it threatens to take over and leave you irritated and frustrated with a feeling of zero-accomplishment in the end. Iâ€™ve learned this the hard way. For most of my college life, Iâ€™ve procrastinated like any outrageously shameless and careless procrastinator youâ€™ll see out there. On days when I ought to have worked, I spent my time doing stuff like finding patterns in the genres of the songs in my iPod, or adding every movie Iâ€™ve watched to my IMDb account. Not bad things to do, but when a deadline is looming, not the kind of stuff one should get into. An hour before final exams, Iâ€™ve gotten bouts of compulsively playing Minesweeper, or of just lying down and day dreaming. Yes life seems to have passed very peacefully, but all the procrastination didnâ€™t do me much good. When I was supposed to work, I wasted time, and when I ought to have partied, I was suddenly hit by the stark realization that I hadnâ€™t worked at all, and I could not party. Now thatâ€™s a bad situation, isnâ€™t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iâ€™m still learning my lesson, and trying to correct this habit. This isnâ€™t uncommon among college students, but I have the feeling that unless youâ€™re super sharp, and can earn your living based on momentary strokes of brilliance, you canâ€™t afford to procrastinate too much. Thereâ€™s no substitute to hard work and putting in the hours. In other words, if youâ€™re a reasonably smart and motivated person, then motivation is the biggest gift you have. Itâ€™s a gift that is easily lost, so make it (and your time) count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;6-make-friends-with-all-kinds-of-people:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Make friends with all kinds of people&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Close friendships formed in college are special. They are probably more mature than the ones you form in school, which usually weather down with time and physical distance. A college student is more mature, and the connections that form here are based on mutual interests or similarity in points of view. These tend to last longer. Meeting a friend from college is a sure shot way to reminisce â€œgood old daysâ€ when you had the time of your lives. Having friends teaches you various things â€“ it opens you up to new points of view, teaches you how to compromise, how to be part of a motley and still enjoy yourself. Friends support you when youâ€™re down, share your joy when youâ€™re happy, and empty your purse when you accomplish. Friends fool around with you, discuss with you â€“ from gossip to philosophy. Friends introduce you to new experiences, help you lose inhibition, motivate you to follow your heart â€“ be it love or work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iâ€™ve had a wonderful group of friends whoâ€™ve done all the above to me, and I owe a major chunk of my development to them. A few years down the line, I wonâ€™t remember the grades I managed to score, what will be remembered are moments that shaped me as a person, and those moments will invariably have been spent with friends. You need memories to live life by, and memories are even better with people in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, also make friends with some professors that you like. They might not fool around with you, but will be of great help and mentor you when it comes to choosing your career. Thereâ€™s no substitute to having great mentors. Additionally, a lot of wisdom can be gained from friendly professors â€“ wisdom which is often quirky, amusing and might apply to you directly. Also make friends with people in the administrative divisions, so that you can break free of the red tape and get your work done faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;7-get-along-with-people-who-are-better-than-you:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Get along with people who are better than you&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how much of a superstar you were before getting into college, you would do well to realize as quickly as possible â€“ that in almost any conceivable activity, there will be someone better than you. In a college like IITB, with so many talented and diverse people, a very essential lesson I learned was that of humility. Whatever high opinions of myself I might have had when I joined were shattered when I realized that there were people who could do a lot of things I was very bad at, or I couldnâ€™t do at all. And I benefited very much from having such an amazing peer group around me. By learning from people who did things better than me, I either got better myself, or realized where I was going wrong. Respecting others for what theyâ€™re worth is an important trait for dealing with people, and is also a quality learned simultaneously with humility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;8-keep-your-health-in-check:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Keep your health in check&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless youâ€™re planning to become a gym instructor after college, or get into a job that requires basic physical fitness, youâ€™re going to regret not exercising in college. Most of us are careless individuals, we eat whatever is served to us, we donâ€™t care to lose the calories, we ignore the slight paunch or the double chin. We think that just a little exercise can put us back in shape. The truth is that the more you postpone it, the harder it will be to regain fitness. It is easy to be lazy, but everyone should get into some sort of activity. Once you get out of college, exercising regularly is going to be real hard so it is essential to build up great fitness during college. If you bloat up during college, then god save you afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay so thatâ€™s about it. Of course, there are many more things I learned, but these stand out as the essential points that I really wanted someone to tell me much earlier. In any case, Iâ€™m spending this summer feeling nostalgic about the past four years. Whether or not you learn something, the memories last really long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:1&#34;&gt;I donâ€™t intend to preach at all, but these are some ideas I could have done with when I started college.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:2&#34;&gt;Iâ€™ve made little effort to shorten the post. I just canâ€™t do it. So if youâ€™re in TL;DR mood, the headings should do for you.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:3&#34;&gt;They called us Chutya freshie ðŸ˜€.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9b58b0368b70bddebc221d8554995d35:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>