<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/categories/personal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 22:56:12 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/categories/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About Acting Class</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/about-acting-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 22:56:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/about-acting-class/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to try acting for a really long time, since college in fact. Back then I never managed to get started and it just became one of those bucket list items. While I was preparing for my recent conference talk (April), my co-worker (and co-speaker) Drew suggested that an acting class might really help with public speaking. I love speaking, so when a few days later my friend Vijay asked me if I&amp;rsquo;d like to try something new, I knew what it would be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Red Hairing</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/red-hairing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 13:32:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/red-hairing/</guid>
      <description>A little over two weeks ago, I got my hair colored red. Not completely, just highlights, but very prominent highlights. Nothing unique because millions of people do this sort of thing, so the only reason I&amp;rsquo;m writing about it is because I can. Kind of the same reason why I colored my hair. It had been on my mind since last year, but the stars started aligning a month ago when a friend referred me to a place in Oakland.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Being a Tourist in India</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</guid>
      <description>I recently got back to California after spending four full weeks in India. My previous trip was two years ago, at the end of 2014. Until moving to the US in 2012, I&amp;rsquo;d only ever lived in India. Immediately after moving, life in California seemed very attractive, especially by virtue of the things India could not offer (primarily better facilities, a more peaceful lifestyle, and opportunities for individual growth). Whenever I visited India after that, I&amp;rsquo;d often complain about the lack of infrastructure, pollution, poor traffic, general disorder, and a host of other problems that might affect any developing country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016 Year in Review</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/2016-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 01:20:02 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/2016-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>Precisely a year ago, I went to Hawaii to try and regain some sanity after what was a terrible 2015. It offered little apart from endless pain, suffering, depression, lack of community, and an uncontrollable feeling of helplessness. So much so that the second half of the Hawaii trip was full of panic attacks and attempts to cut the trip short. I was due to start a new job upon returning, and my Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis was still pending.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2015 Year in Review</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/2015-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2015 19:16:02 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/2015-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>Are you already sick of people writing their yearly review posts? I bet! I’m going to add more more to the pile though, but mostly as a milestone for myself, and for others who might find value in reading it.
To start, I have to say that 2015 has been the most unusual year of my life. I’ve experienced many different things and changed a lot as a person. This is also the year when I finally decided and went through the process of quitting grad school to venture out into the real world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Off to Hawaii - a Good End to a Miserable Year</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/off-to-hawaii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2015 15:39:26 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/off-to-hawaii/</guid>
      <description>2015 will go down as the worst year in my life so far, no doubts about that! It has been a year when I suffered a lot, learned some hard lessons, and had to face several uncomfortable truths about myself. I’ve battled terrifying depression and felt things I wasn’t ready to handle. As painful as that has been, I’m glad to be ending the year right – by taking a break from everything, and heading to Hawaii on my first real solo trip.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>