<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Travel on nRT</title>
    <link>https://nishanttotla.com/categories/travel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Travel on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nishanttotla.com/categories/travel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>On Being a Tourist in India</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:59:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/on-being-tourist-in-india/</guid>
      <description>I recently got back to California after spending four full weeks in India. My previous trip was two years ago, at the end of 2014. Until moving to the US in 2012, I&amp;rsquo;d only ever lived in India. Immediately after moving, life in California seemed very attractive, especially by virtue of the things India could not offer (primarily better facilities, a more peaceful lifestyle, and opportunities for individual growth). Whenever I visited India after that, I&amp;rsquo;d often complain about the lack of infrastructure, pollution, poor traffic, general disorder, and a host of other problems that might affect any developing country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference Travel in 2016</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 03:32:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/conference-travel-2016/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been fortunate to have traveled extensively during the Fall of 2016. A good chunk of that travel was because of work. Back in September, I visited London and St. Louis (Missouri), and attended three different conferences. Later in October, I flew back to Europe, this time to Berlin to attend my fourth conference in two months1. This post focuses on the conferences. I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about the sightseeing I did in future posts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Off to Hawaii - a Good End to a Miserable Year</title>
      <link>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/off-to-hawaii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2015 15:39:26 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nishanttotla.com/blog/off-to-hawaii/</guid>
      <description>2015 will go down as the worst year in my life so far, no doubts about that! It has been a year when I suffered a lot, learned some hard lessons, and had to face several uncomfortable truths about myself. I’ve battled terrifying depression and felt things I wasn’t ready to handle. As painful as that has been, I’m glad to be ending the year right – by taking a break from everything, and heading to Hawaii on my first real solo trip.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>