<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Notes on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Notes on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 23:03:38 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Black Mirror</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/black-mirror/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 23:03:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/black-mirror/</guid>
      <description>Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve been exploring interesting neighborhoods in San Francisco by leisurely walking through them. So far these jaunts have been focused on the Mission and Castro, with the occasional venture into Haight-Ashbury or Hayes Valley. A couple of weeks ago, I visited Dijital Fix, an electronics+design store on Valencia Street. It had some pretty retro electronics and other cool things. I clicked this photo on the way out, and only later realized why I liked it so much.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deciding to Stop</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/deciding-to-stop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:44:06 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/deciding-to-stop/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a slow reader with a short attention span, but I&amp;rsquo;d like to read a lot more books than I currently manage. So I&amp;rsquo;m like the armchair analyst who dreams of changing the world &amp;ndash; tons of ambition, but lack of skills (and possibly desire?). A recurrent problem for me has been that I start some books, partly or nearly finish them, have no interest in continuing, but can&amp;rsquo;t start other books until I finish the earlier ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adronitis</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/adronitis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 15:09:14 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/adronitis/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a word that struck me immediately. I found it on one of those listicles that pull up obscure words that mean very specific things, and then advertize to young adults trying to make sense of their emotions.
 Adronitis
n. frustration with how long it takes to get to know someone—spending the first few weeks chatting in their psychological entryway, with each subsequent conversation like entering a different anteroom, each a little closer to the center of the house—wishing instead that you could start there and work your way out, exchanging your deepest secrets first, before easing into casualness, until you’ve built up enough mystery over the years to ask them where they’re from, and what they do for a living.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Brothers, Not the Brotherhood</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/brothers-not-the-brotherhood/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2016 12:55:36 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/brothers-not-the-brotherhood/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve grown to love this quote from Shantaram, a book by Gregory David Roberts.
 But I was alone, and for two reasons: The mafia was theirs, not mine. For them, the organisation always came first. But I was loyal to the men, not the mafia; to the brothers, not the brotherhood. I worked for the mafia, but I didn&#39;t join it. I&#39;m not a joiner. I never found a club or clan or idea that was more important to me than the men and women who believed in it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m Not Here to Get Things Done</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/not-here-to-get-things-done/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 12:05:11 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/not-here-to-get-things-done/</guid>
      <description>I was talking to my friend Abhay recently, and he brought up a very interesting idea. He works at a software startup that&amp;rsquo;s still relatively small, which means that there&amp;rsquo;s a certain amount of pressure to make quick progress and produce results. This requires having to churn out functioning code on a regular basis. Unfortunately, it&amp;rsquo;s often easy to write code by pattern-matching or copying from other sources &amp;ndash; but an entirely different thing to fully understand, and internalize what you&amp;rsquo;re doing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So Who Wants to Volunteer?</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/who-wants-to-volunteer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 15:01:35 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/notes/who-wants-to-volunteer/</guid>
      <description>In yesterday&amp;rsquo;s Yoga class, our instructor wanted to demonstrate a certain asana (pose). She could have easily done it herself, but she wanted a volunteer, perhaps so that she could point out common mistakes people make in this asana. So she asked &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;who wants to volunteer?&amp;rdquo;. As is common in such a situation, most people look around trying to deflect attention. I often do that too, but this time I just raised my hand, albeit a little reluctantly.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>