<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Uncategorized on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/categories/uncategorized/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Uncategorized on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 15:29:03 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/categories/uncategorized/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I was Asked to Give a Motivational Speech</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/i-was-asked-motivational-speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 15:29:03 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/i-was-asked-motivational-speech/</guid>
      <description>On December 18, 2016, my parents celebrated the 25th anniversary of Totla Hospital. It has been a long and impressive journey for them, starting out from literally nothing when they arrived in Aurangabad, to having built a very successful and highly respected hospital in the city. To celebrate this anniversary, they had organized a grand function, inviting a lot of former patients, friends, family, and others out of the gigantic community they&amp;rsquo;ve built during this time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>India&#39;s Undercurrent of Propaganda</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/india-undercurrent-propaganda/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 16:01:47 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/india-undercurrent-propaganda/</guid>
      <description>India is currently at an interesting political standpoint. We finally have a single party forming the central government without needing support from other parties (last this happened was in 1984). The average Indian person seems to be much more aware and concerned about the political situation, and invested in the country’s future, especially young people. All of this is a major shift compared to a few years ago. There have been several contributing factors – dissatisfaction with the UPA govt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about Empathy</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/learning-about-empathy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2015 15:46:09 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/learning-about-empathy/</guid>
      <description>Empathy is such a simple concept to understand, yet so difficult to practice! Kids are taught about it. The word itself is lazily thrown around, assuming everyone knows how to empathize, that it’s something we’re naturally good at. Well we’re not! Even if we care enough to look outside our own busy lives to try and want to empathize with someone, it’s too easy to fall into the trap of making judgments or believing we know everything about another person’s situation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supporting a Football Club</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/supporting-a-football-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2015 19:10:35 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/supporting-a-football-club/</guid>
      <description>Sunday, March 28, 2004 : Arsenal vs Manchester United at Highbury, London was the first live football game I watched (on TV, of course). I’d only ever followed cricket before that and played some football, but this was unlike anything I knew in sport. It was fast and full of action. These players were really passionate and the tension was palpable. Then on 50 minutes, Arsenal’s number 14 scored from a brilliant long range effort, a stunning goal by any standard!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rediscovering Podcasts</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/rediscovering-podcasts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 15:50:52 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/rediscovering-podcasts/</guid>
      <description>This summer, I was interviewing at several companies. Among other things, it involved a lot of travel, and there was little I could do while traveling. If I was driving, I’d mostly listen to my usual Spotify playlists, although they got boring pretty soon. Taking the train allowed me to read in addition, but I’d usually get distracted or fall asleep since the interviews were exhausting. Soon enough, all this travel time started feeling wasteful, but I wanted to reclaim it, so I constantly tried to find ways to engage in something productive, or learn something new.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eight Lessons I Learned in College</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/x-lessons-i-learned-in-college/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2012 19:26:42 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/x-lessons-i-learned-in-college/</guid>
      <description>I’m writing a post after around five months! Whoa! What a ride the last semester has been! I’ve now graduated (provided they give me my degree) from one of the best colleges in India, with new hopes and dreams, some knowledge, passion and a lot of friends. The past few months have been a blur, and I’ve done loads of new things. Most importantly, I’ve had the opportunity to think about and look at all that I accomplished (or failed to accomplish) during college, I’ve thought about where my motivations lie, what I want from life and ultimately how I’m going to achieve that.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>