<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Weekly-log on nRT</title>
    <link>http://nishanttotla.com/weekly-log/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Weekly-log on nRT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2016 18:20:16 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://nishanttotla.com/weekly-log/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Log (2016-06-19)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-06-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2016 18:20:16 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-06-19/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The last two weeks have been quite busy, leading up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://2016.dockercon.com/&#34;&gt;DockerCon&lt;/a&gt; and travel. I haven&amp;rsquo;t had time to publish, so I&amp;rsquo;m merging the log from the last two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:a190b7214091234985f457ce3847cb0d&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/culture/culture-desk/how-silicon-valley-nails-silicon-valley&#34;&gt;How &amp;ldquo;Silicon Valley&amp;rdquo; Nails Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt; [The New Yorker] &amp;ndash; A lot of amazing behind the scenes info about how Silicon Valley (the show) is created. And in some cases, real life is even weirder than the show, even though the show is meant to be a caricature of the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeed.com/devangp/aavite-rovay-nai?utm_term=.wy3e0EKJo#.eiYYn8x4&#34;&gt;Indians are never taught to talk to their parents as adults, and that’s a problem&lt;/a&gt; [BuzzFeed] &amp;ndash; Continuing the series of some genuinely good articles on BuzzFeed, this one focuses on how interactions between Indian kids and parents are comically shallow on the emotional front, especially when the kids grow up. While this has not entirely been my experience, I can relate to some of it, and definitely have friends who can relate to all of it. It also appears that the original article appeared on a blog, then Reddit, then here, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried to track down the source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;movies-and-tv-shows:a190b7214091234985f457ce3847cb0d&#34;&gt;Movies and TV Shows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2575988/&#34;&gt;Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I first watched a bit of the show when it first came out, but didn&amp;rsquo;t find it quite appealing. But after having worked at a software startup for a few months now, I can appreciate the satire and humor much better. It&amp;rsquo;s crude, brash, over the top, and does a great job at making fun of the seemingly strange culture that pervades Silicon Valley. If you find an aspect of the show offensive or peculiar (eg. overt sexism, racism, conceit, etc.), then remember that the real thing is even weirder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4044364/&#34;&gt;Citizenfour&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A thrilling documentary about Edward Snowden&amp;rsquo;s correspondence with the journalists who helped him break the story on government surveillance. It features all the real people involved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:a190b7214091234985f457ce3847cb0d&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bankofamerica.com/privacy/accounts-cards/shopsafe.go&#34;&gt;ShopSafe&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Bank of America offers a program where you can create a temporary credit card online, that links to an existing card you own (one level of indirection). You can also set an expiry date and maximum (possibly recurring) limit on the card! This is extremely useful in places where you don&amp;rsquo;t trust the vendor enough to provide your real credit card number. I&amp;rsquo;m going to use this extensively now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Log (2016-06-05)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-06-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2016 08:54:04 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-06-05/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had an extremely busy week and didn&amp;rsquo;t find much time to do anything else. I considered not publishing a log this week, and merging it with the following week, but  &lt;code&gt;¯\_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:d006f9ed6a06c509524b22f45172c1cc&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeed.com/katiejmbaker/heres-the-powerful-letter-the-stanford-victim-read-to-her-ra?utm_term=.bwwlobVyk#.gsqJBEQDP&#34;&gt;Here Is The Powerful Letter The Stanford Victim Read Aloud To Her Attacker&lt;/a&gt; [BuzzFeed] &amp;ndash; An unconscious woman was raped by a 20 year old Stanford student behind a dumpster, and he was convicted but only got jail time of 6 months as punishment. This article is powerful, and has been evoking a lot of outrage over the awful treatment that rape victims are regularly subjected to, and the leniancy of the sentence. You&amp;rsquo;ve likely seen it shared everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vitals.lifehacker.com/the-medical-screenings-all-men-need-and-when-1779846310&#34;&gt;The Medical Screenings All Men Need, and When&lt;/a&gt; [Lifehacker] &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve been considering figuring out a regular medical treatment plan (annual health checkup etc.) and this article seemed like a good starting point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music:d006f9ed6a06c509524b22f45172c1cc&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Masala Coffee is a band from Kerala. I don&amp;rsquo;t know much about them, except that this cover is beautiful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AB2ACJ22fhY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Log (2016-05-29)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-05-29/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 00:03:18 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-05-29/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There isn&amp;rsquo;t much to share this week because it&amp;rsquo;s been a busy one, and I was away in Colorado all weekend. I&amp;rsquo;ll publish a post about the trip soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:bfa236bdbc2b2b250d236b5dc0a2d2a8&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vox.com/2016/5/26/11790878/google-oracle-fight-explained&#34;&gt;Why Google&amp;rsquo;s victory in a copyright fight with Oracle is a big deal&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A short summary of the background between the Google vs. Oracle case that&amp;rsquo;s been all over the news. This includes the current status of the case and legal implications of either party winning. A good start if you know absolutely nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music:bfa236bdbc2b2b250d236b5dc0a2d2a8&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shakar Wandaan Re again! Last week I shared the Coke Studio version, but it&amp;rsquo;s also a song from the Pakistani movie called &lt;em&gt;Ho Mann Jahaan&lt;/em&gt;. The movie version is more of a dance number, but still extremely likable and funky.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/231087059&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:bfa236bdbc2b2b250d236b5dc0a2d2a8&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.getairhelp.com/en/&#34;&gt;AirHelp&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A website that helps you get rightful compensation when your flight is delayed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/blog/2176-diversity-and-inclusion-at-github&#34;&gt;Diversity and Inclusion at GitHub&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; GitHub faced public criticism over harassment and poor work culture within the company, but have since worked hard to pull their act together. Good to see such a turnaround.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Log (2016-05-22)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-05-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2016 00:03:18 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-05-22/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:4a983cb1bbddb46cf15cf0063ad16a5b&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/01/fashion/modern-love-netflix-relationship.html&#34;&gt;The Entire Netflix History of Us&lt;/a&gt; [The New York Times] &amp;ndash; A story of when a couple broke up and their shared Netflix account was the only remaining connection between them. I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/column/modern-love&#34;&gt;Modern Love&lt;/a&gt; columns on NYT, because they explore the idea of love at levels and in contexts that are extremely thought-provoking. In many cases, they bring me agonizingly close to feeling painful emotions, but that is probably why I read them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/16/world/americas/dying-infants-and-no-medicine-inside-venezuelas-failing-hospitals.html&#34;&gt;Dying Infants and No Medicine: Inside Venezuela’s Failing Hospitals&lt;/a&gt; [The New York Times] &amp;ndash; I had no idea things were so bad in Venezuela. This article reports a disastrous failure of infrastructure in the country, under political instability and poor economic planning. In particular, hospitals seem to be very badly affected leading to growing mortality rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music:4a983cb1bbddb46cf15cf0063ad16a5b&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the good music I&amp;rsquo;ve recently discovered has been from Coke Studio, thanks to Soundcloud. Tum Naraz Ho is a soothing melody about the time when a person&amp;rsquo;s lover is upset with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/168257758&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shakar Wandaan Re is a very energetic composition with catchy and playful lyrics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/171491148&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:4a983cb1bbddb46cf15cf0063ad16a5b&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nishanttotla/status/732313216768843776&#34;&gt;commencement&lt;/a&gt; this week as a Masters student. It was fun, especially since I couldn&amp;rsquo;t attend the one after college.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to Colorado next weekend! For more than two years now, I&amp;rsquo;ve really wanted to go there and never managed to. This time though, I took the initiative before a long weekend and I&amp;rsquo;m finally doing it! I&amp;rsquo;m also traveling with friends, something I don&amp;rsquo;t do quite often.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/MyDepressionLooksLike?src=hash&#34;&gt;#MyDepressionLooksLike&lt;/a&gt; seemed to be trending on Twitter for a little while, with people describing their experience of depression. It was strangely reassuring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Log (2016-05-15)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-05-15/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 00:03:18 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-05-15/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:28527d4e425ed1ec89fa7ba6da390a2c&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@lydiapolgreen/why-people-pay-to-read-the-new-york-times-60720880e707#.n7zkrugsv&#34;&gt;Why people pay to read The New York Times&lt;/a&gt; [Medium] &amp;ndash; This is a brilliant point of view, and one that fully aligns with how I think of journalism in the digital age. At a time when Facebook and social media have immense control over platforms, there is still a lot of value in good journalism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://gizmodo.com/former-facebook-workers-we-routinely-suppressed-conser-1775461006&#34;&gt;Former Facebook Workers: We Routinely Suppressed Conservative News&lt;/a&gt; [Gizmodo] &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve long believed that the algorithms run by giant tech companies have immense power when it comes to swaying public opinion, even if inadvertently. But if there&amp;rsquo;s intent, things can get really tricky. It&amp;rsquo;s okay to have biases in news reporting, and be explicit about them, but for people to believe that the content they read online is organic is dangerous if it&amp;rsquo;s false. When viewed in conjunction with the above article, a few people at a few companies controlling the most used information channels sounds very dystopian, especially since accountability is suspect. Key lesson though? Get your news from multiple sources!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zachholman.com/posts/the-new-10-year-vesting-schedule&#34;&gt;The New 10-Year Vesting Schedule&lt;/a&gt; [zachholman.com] &amp;ndash; A timely and appropriate rant about how the rules around stock options are created such that regular startup employees have the least flexibility and control over how they can retain their hard-earned share in the company, while investors and founders get away with much more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeed.com/sonaligupta2/single-female-disabled-apps-are-saving-me-from-inaccessible?utm_term=.ugdnMXv5W#.vge5kwLAl&#34;&gt;Single With A Disability: Apps Are Saving Me From Awkward Dates And Awful Rishtas&lt;/a&gt; [BuzzFeed] &amp;ndash; A personal account of a woman with muscular dystrophy regarding her experience with dating and arranged marriage in India. Finding an accepting partner can be extremely challenging as a disabled person, and this is a rare story on the topic. I wish it were longer, but good read nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:28527d4e425ed1ec89fa7ba6da390a2c&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bayareadrama.company/the-domestic-crusaders&#34;&gt;The Domestic Crusaders&lt;/a&gt; was a play I watched on Saturday. This was Bay Area Drama Company&amp;rsquo;s version of the original play by Wajahat Ali, focusing on the Muslim immigrant experience in post &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt; America.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.twitter.com/2016/track-the-pulse-of-the-us-presidential-race&#34;&gt;Track the pulse of the US presidential race&lt;/a&gt; [Twitter Blog] &amp;ndash; Twitter often makes really neat visualizations using tweet data. This one explores &amp;ldquo;how the Twitter buzz about each candidate has shifted week over week since September&amp;rdquo;. Look &lt;a href=&#34;https://interactive.twitter.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should follow &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jaythenerdkid&#34;&gt;Aaminah&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter, she often does very intriguing tweetstorms. This week she&amp;rsquo;s done some amazing ones about mental illness. If you&amp;rsquo;ve experienced mental illness, or know someone who has, or just want to be helpful, read these: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jaythenerdkid/status/730131499262062592&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jaythenerdkid/status/730133438460727296&#34;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jaythenerdkid/status/730420676570566656&#34;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jaythenerdkid/status/730434924654804992&#34;&gt;four&lt;/a&gt;. Remember to scroll up and wait for all tweets to load.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Log (2016-05-08)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-05-08/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2016 00:05:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-05-08/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:a3f8edc431d836d20fafa3ce81f90639&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rkoutnik.com/2016/04/21/implementers-solvers-and-finders.html&#34;&gt;Implementers, Solvers, and Finders&lt;/a&gt; [rkoutnik.com] &amp;ndash; This article describes three types of roles software engineers can fulfill in a company. Implementers implement solutions handed to them, solvers solve problems handed to them, finders discover those problems. It points out how most engineers only become finders when they choose the management ladder, and how there might still be hope for those who don&amp;rsquo;t want to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:a3f8edc431d836d20fafa3ce81f90639&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blockstack.org/&#34;&gt;Blockstack&lt;/a&gt; is the application stack for building decentralized, blockchain-based applications that don&amp;rsquo;t need any servers to operate. Blockstack applications can be built quickly by plugging into Blockstack&amp;rsquo;s services for identity, naming, storage and authentication. I don&amp;rsquo;t quite understand how this works yet, but is very intriguing and will spend time understanding blockchains. &lt;a href=&#34;https://onename.com/&#34;&gt;Onename&lt;/a&gt; seems to be one such service.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://projectinclude.org/&#34;&gt;Project Include&lt;/a&gt; is a cool new initiative by some influential tech ladies to address diversity and inclusion in the tech industry, by creating an opt-in system of accountability for startups. The website also has some nice reading material that I&amp;rsquo;ll gradually make my way through.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11650721&#34;&gt;One of my research projects&lt;/a&gt; from my first year of grad school made it to the front page of Hacker News for a while on Saturday. It was unexpected, and probably not a big deal, but was cool since I haven&amp;rsquo;t been there before.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Log (2016-05-01)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-05-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 09:13:07 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-05-01/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:644a9c6ec0be42ecc309e552f878dc56&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pulitzer prizes were announced last week, and I&amp;rsquo;d been meaning to catch up on a couple of interesting articles that won. This week I could only do one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2015/07/20/the-really-big-one&#34;&gt;The Really Big One&lt;/a&gt; [The New Yorker] &amp;ndash; This is a great piece of journalism, describing how the Pacific Northwest is due for a MAJOR earthquake. This is not one of your regular doomsday articles &amp;ndash; it goes through a great deal of background (made understandable for the non-expert) and history behind the tectonic activity in the region. It also describes how poorly equipped the region really is to deal with the consequences, and how things will go down if this earthquake hits in the next few years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there were other nice articles that came up in my various feeds&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://randsinrepose.com/archives/shields-down/&#34;&gt;Shields Down&lt;/a&gt; [randsinrepose] &amp;ndash; Job resignations don&amp;rsquo;t happen when you decide you&amp;rsquo;re doing it. They happen when a certain event or situation leads you to lower your shields and consider the possibility of an alternative future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://randsinrepose.com/archives/bored-people-quit/&#34;&gt;Bored People Quit&lt;/a&gt; [randsinrepose] &amp;ndash; A post for engineering managers to detect boredom in their teams, and how to deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/this-is-hard/the-other-side-of-diversity-1bb3de2f053e#.7ll31ndb5&#34;&gt;The Other Side of Diversity&lt;/a&gt; [Medium] &amp;ndash; An old article by the awesome &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/EricaJoy&#34;&gt;Erica Baker&lt;/a&gt; describing her experience with how diversity in the workplace is also about helping marginalized groups build communities for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music:644a9c6ec0be42ecc309e552f878dc56&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ali Zafar again 💜💜💜 alongside Sara Haider, with this rendition of a beautiful song from 1963 sung by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saleem_Raza_(Pakistani_singer&#34;&gt;Saleem Raza&lt;/a&gt;). I&amp;rsquo;ve been sadder than usual this week, but listening to this song helped.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/222734241&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also been letting Soundcloud just play suggested music in the background, and discovered some interesting stuff as a result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/97173470&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
James Blunt&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Your Beautiful&amp;rdquo; translated to Punjabi, pretty cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/167677079&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
I discovered this acapella version of Strings&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;Mera Bichra Yaar&amp;rdquo; two weeks ago, but found it again and really loved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/217632953&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
I don&amp;rsquo;t have (and didn&amp;rsquo;t find out) much background about this track, but it&amp;rsquo;s good nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far these suggestions have been 👌👏🤘and I&amp;rsquo;ve just kept the tab open as an anytime go-to radio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:644a9c6ec0be42ecc309e552f878dc56&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I subscribed to &lt;a href=&#34;https://modelviewculture.com/&#34;&gt;Model View Culture&lt;/a&gt; and hope to keep in touch with some extremely thought-provoking writings there. It describes itself as a magazine about technology, culture and diversity. Highly recommended!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Log (2016-04-24)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-04-24/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 16:29:46 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-04-24/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:98abedd9c62a85bccb8ad1cb2fde3ebf&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2016/04/pornography-industry-economics-tarrant/476580/&#34;&gt;The Hidden Economics of Porn&lt;/a&gt; [The Atlantic] &amp;ndash; Some very intriguing insights about the porn industy by a gender-studies professor. The porn industry is really BIG, many big-name sites are owned by a single company (MindGeek) and contain pirated content. It&amp;rsquo;s also very interesting to know that porn preferences of people are shaped by the keywords they use, which only reflect some stereotyped categories (that are often sexist, racist, or narrow-minded). Overall, the article contains several questions that ought to be asked about our relationship to porn and our consumption of it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@milistjohn/i-am-alex-st-john-s-daughter-and-he-is-wrong-about-women-in-tech-4728545e7c0e#.o0x2dflzr&#34;&gt;I am Alex St. John’s Daughter, and He is Wrong About Women in Tech&lt;/a&gt; [Medium] &amp;ndash; A fitting reply to the misogynistic and regressive views publicly peddled by Alex St. John, by his own daughter Amilia. It&amp;rsquo;s a well-written response that details her own experiences and why her father&amp;rsquo;s views are misguided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;movies-and-tv-shows:98abedd9c62a85bccb8ad1cb2fde3ebf&#34;&gt;Movies and TV Shows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2085059/&#34;&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; It&amp;rsquo;s a British TV anthology series that features speculative fiction with dark and satirical themes examining modern society, especially wrt the unanticipated consequences of new technologies. I started watching this week, and have liked it a lot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:98abedd9c62a85bccb8ad1cb2fde3ebf&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://camlistore.org/&#34;&gt;Camlistore&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; From the website, &amp;ldquo;Camlistore is a set of open source formats, protocols, and software for modeling, storing, searching, sharing and synchronizing data in the post-PC era. Data may be files or objects, tweets or 5TB videos, and you can access it via a phone, browser or FUSE filesystem.&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;ve been worrying about backing up my data for a while, especially with the amount of trust I currently need to have in Google or other third-party tools. I&amp;rsquo;ll be following Camlistore closely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gmail.googleblog.com/2016/04/inbox-by-gmail-better-way-to-keep-track.html&#34;&gt;Saving links to Google Inbox&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Google recently announced a Chrome extension for saving links directly into Inbox, and they get bundled too! This is an amazing feature since I did often use Inbox to do the same. &lt;a href=&#34;https://getpocket.com/&#34;&gt;Pocket&lt;/a&gt; has serious competition! This also works on the phone app, although I didn&amp;rsquo;t see bundling there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Log (2016-04-17)</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-04-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2016 15:25:57 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-04-17/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;articles:95bd810bcc3ec763a4760e676ae3a6d6&#34;&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lesswrong.com/lw/f1/beware_trivial_inconveniences/&#34;&gt;Beware Trivial Inconveniences&lt;/a&gt; [LessWrong] &amp;ndash; This is a nice post about how The Great Firewall of China works by making it a little inconvenient and time-consuming to view subversive sites, thereby discouraging casual exploration. Even though it&amp;rsquo;s easy to bypass it with little technical knowledge or instructions, most people don&amp;rsquo;t do it. There are many more situations where it&amp;rsquo;s easy to discourage people from doing certain things simply by making them slightly inconvenient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music:95bd810bcc3ec763a4760e676ae3a6d6&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended my first &lt;strong&gt;Anoushka Shankar&lt;/strong&gt; concert this week. Despite not having been a huge fan of her music in the past, I fell in love with the performance and the music. Perhaps my tastes are changing now. Music was from her new &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sVd3o9OuyxM&amp;amp;list=PLGjLVtehjLeV_z6twUDRKzDkJFhzYbXIV&#34;&gt;Land of Gold album&lt;/a&gt;. Especially look out for the Secret Heart, Land to Nowhere, and Dissolving Boundaries tracks. The album is inspired by the pain and frustration of the recent refugee crisis, and reflects both anger and hope.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Equivalnce&#34;&gt;Abhinav&lt;/a&gt; introduced me to a couple of cool Coke Studio (Season 8) songs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/220247852&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
Umair Jaswal and Quratulain Balouch are amazing singers, and I particularly adore the flute and violins in this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/220248535&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
This one is all about Ali Zafar. I always thought he was a good performer, but his vocal range and swagger are stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both the above, the videos are worth watching too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yet another source of new music was &lt;a href=&#34;http://bolly923fm.com/&#34;&gt;Bolly 92.3 FM&lt;/a&gt;, Bay Area&amp;rsquo;s new Bollywood-only radio channel! I can&amp;rsquo;t describe how glad I am to have this, even though a lot of modern Bollywood music is very forgettable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous:95bd810bcc3ec763a4760e676ae3a6d6&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://slither.io/&#34;&gt;Slither&lt;/a&gt; is an online multiplayer snake game, with 400-600 players on a board at any point of time. It&amp;rsquo;s wildly addictive, and has been my second-most visited site behind Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.betterthansmalltalk.com/#end-small-talk&#34;&gt;Better Than Small Talk&lt;/a&gt; was an experimental event I attended this week, where the focus was to create an atmosphere that encouraged people to quickly dive into deep conversations. It was interesting, and I&amp;rsquo;ve written more about it &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/better-than-small-talk&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning about online security and encryption, and wrote a couple of blog posts about it (&lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/playing-with-keybase-io&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/signing-git-commits-gpg&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next week!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a Weekly Log</title>
      <link>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/creating-weekly-log/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 15:27:06 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nishanttotla.com/blog/creating-weekly-log/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently got a cool idea from &lt;a href=&#34;http://thirld.com/blog/&#34;&gt;Constantin&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;. On a more or less monthly basis, he writes about the books, podcasts, and other stuff he reads. I thought that this was great for two reasons &amp;ndash; firstly for keeping track of interesting things which are otherwise too easy to move past and forget, and secondly (for me) building motivation to actually find and engage with more such things, because I get to write about them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So starting this week, I will try to write a weekly note on the books, articles, music, movies, websites, observations, and pretty much anything that comes up during the week. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to publish on Sundays, but there&amp;rsquo;s no pressure to stick to a strict schedule. We&amp;rsquo;ll see how this goes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first post is &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/blog/weekly-log-2016-04-17&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. All posts are tagged &lt;code&gt;weekly-log&lt;/code&gt;, so you can check the entire list &lt;a href=&#34;http://nishanttotla.com/tags/weekly-log&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>